<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>U.S. Air Force Awards Contracts to Small Businesses Under NETCENTS-2</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 20, 2012</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>News  Briefs</tag>
    <tag>Air Force Technologies</tag>
    <tag>ActioNet</tag>
    <tag>Array Information Technology</tag>
    <tag>Datum Software</tag>
    <tag>Digital Management</tag>
    <tag>Diligent Consulting</tag>
    <tag>Diversified Technical Services</tag>
    <tag>DSD Laboratories</tag>
    <tag>Excellus Solutions</tag>
    <tag>Exeter Government Services</tag>
    <tag>IndraSoft</tag>
    <tag>Seque Technologies</tag>
    <tag>SI Systems Technology</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>U.S. Air Force organizations soon could begin awarding task orders to 12 small businesses under the potential $960 million Network Centrics-2 (NETCENTS-2) contract—a vehicle designed to make it faster and easier for warfighters to obtain innovative information technology services and capabilities. The NETCENTS-2 team already awarded its Application Services Small Business Companion contracts, which were the first of two application services contracts that will be available to Air Force personnel. The second services contract is a full and open competition that is still in source selection.
The multiple-award, indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contracts were awarded to ActioNet Incorporated, Array Information Technology Incorporated, Datum Software Incorporated, Digital Management Incorporated, Diligent Consulting Incorporated, Diversified Technical Services Incorporated, DSD Laboratories, Excellus Solutions LLC, Exeter Government Services LLC, IndraSoft, Seque Technologies and SI Systems Technology.
	The NETCENTS-2 Application Services acquisition provides a vehicle for warfighters to access a wide range of services, including sustainment, migration, integration, training, help desk support, testing and operation support. Air Force personnel must use the application services contract; however, the U.S. Defense Department and other federal agencies may choose to use the vehicle when the work relates to requirements for interoperability with Air Force capabilities; supports the service's information technology infrastructure, applications or operations; supports host-tenant arrangements that involve Air Force units; or involves joint operations and solutions.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
