<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Firms to Provide U.S. Navy C5ISR</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>October 24, 2012</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>AASKI Technology Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Ocean</tag>
    <tag>Advanced C4 Solutions Inc.</tag>
    <tag>By Light Professional IT Services Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Cybrix Group Inc.</tag>
    <tag>GStek Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Juno Technologies Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Mercom Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Mystikal Solutions LLC</tag>
    <tag>STARGATES Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Syneren Technologies Corp.</tag>
    <tag>C5ISR</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>AASKI Technology Inc., Ocean, N.J.; Advanced C4 Solutions Inc., Tampa, Fla.; By Light Professional IT Services Inc., Arlington, Va.; Cybrix Group Inc., Tampa, Fla.; GStek Inc., Chesapeake, Va; Juno Technologies Inc., Rancho Santa Fe, Calif.; Mercom Inc., Pawleys Island, S.C.; Mystikal Solutions LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; STARGATES Inc., Arlington, Va.; and Syneren Technologies Corp., Lanham, Md., are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, performance-based, multiple award contracts, with provisions for fixed-price-incentive and firm-fixed-price orders, to provide command, control, communications, computers, combat systems, intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance electronics and communications services and solutions in support of mission capabilities within the transport and computing infrastructure portfolio to provide the full system life cycle support including research, development, test, evaluation, production and fielding of sustainable, secure, survivable, and interoperable C5ISR, information operations, enterprise information services and space capabilities. These contracts include options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these multiple award contracts to an estimated $98,760,000. These 10 contractors may compete for the task orders under the terms and conditions of the awarded contracts. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, S.C., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
