<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DHS Awards 34 Cyber Research and Development Contracts </title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>October 29, 2012</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DHS</tag>
    <tag>Homeland Security</tag>
    <tag>science and technology</tag>
    <tag>research and development</tag>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Department of Homeland Security Science and Technology Directorate (DHS S&amp;T) has awarded 34 contracts to 29 academic and research organizations for research and development of solutions to cyber security challenges. The contracts were awarded by the DHS S&amp;T Cyber Security Division (CSD) under Broad Agency Announcement (BAA) 11-02 which solicited proposals in 14 technical topic areas aimed at improving security in federal networks and across the Internet while developing new and enhanced technologies for detecting, preventing and responding to cyber attacks on the nation’s critical information infrastructure. Four of these contracts include co-funding from international partners ­ two from the United Kingdom and two from Australia. Negotiations are currently underway for additional international co-funding from partner agencies in Canada, Sweden and The Netherlands. Contracts were awarded to: Applied Visions, Inc, Northport, NY; Carnegie-Mellon University, Pittsburgh; Columbia University, New York; Def-Logix, Provo, Utah; George Mason University, Fairfax, Va; Georgia Tech Research Corp., Atlanta; HRL Laboratories LLC, Malibu, Calif; IBM Research, Yorktown Heights, NY; International Computer Science Institute, Berkeley, Calif; ITT Advanced Engineering &amp; Sciences Division, Rome, NY; Kestrel Technology LLC, Palo Alto, Calif; Merit Network Inc., Ann Arbor, Mich; Morgridge Institute for Research, Madison, Wis; Naval Postgraduate School, Monterey, Calif; Northrop Grumman Information Systems, McLean, Va.; Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tenn.; Pacific NW National Laboratory, Richland, Wash; Purdue University, West Lafayette, Ind; Raytheon BBN Technologies, Cambridge, Mass; Rutgers University - New Brunswick, NJ; The Trustees of Princeton University, Princeton, NJ; The University of Alabama at Birmingham; The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; Trustees of Dartmouth College, Hanover, NH; Trustees of Indiana University, Bloomington; University of California, San Diego; University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign; University of Maryland, College Park; and the University of Southern California Information Sciences Institute, Marina del Rey. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
