<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: Operation Covert Santa	</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>December 6, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Ever wanted to be one of Santa's elves? Here's the perfect chance to try it out and help wounded warriors at the same time. Operation Covert Santa gathers the wish lists from recently injured troops and their families, removes all identifying information and asks volunteers to supply the presents. All the gifts are given and received anonymously. It isn't charity—it's the magic of Christmas.
Last year, more than 175 elves provided presents for 74 severely injured soldiers and their families. People who want to participate this year can help in several ways:
	Donate cash by sending a check made out to the Aleethia Foundation at:
	Aleethia Foundation?
	Operation Covert Santa?
	1718 M Street NW Suite 1170
	?Washington DC 20036
Put "Operation Covert Santa VI" in the memo line.
	Or
	Go to the Aleethia Foundation website and donate electronically by choosing "Ed Meagher's Covert Santa Program." Whether you send a check or use the Web option, email Ed Meagher at huskyelf@cox.net with "Cash Donation" in the subject line so the program can know how much to budget.
	Elves also can sign up to buy a single gift, support an individual soldier, or adopt a small or large family. Send an email to the huskyelf@cox.net address with the appropriate choice in the subject line. Participants then will receive the information about what to buy, so they can shop for it, wrap it and put on the number they will receive. The packages can be delivered in person or shipped to:
	Operation Covert Santa
	?453 Walker Road?
	Great Falls, Virginia 22066
	Donations are requested as soon as possible but no later than December 16. Email Ed Meagher for more information.?????
Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information. If you know of a program that is helping service personnel, veterans or their families please submit that information to Rita Boland, SIGNAL’s senior news editor.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
