<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Thirteen Firms to Compete for C5ISR Task Orders</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>November 17, 2012</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Altron Inc.</tag>
    <tag>American Electronics Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Command Decisions Systems and Solutions</tag>
    <tag>Centuria Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Del Rey Systems and Technology Inc.</tag>
    <tag>ISHPI Information Technologies Inc.</tag>
    <tag>K3 Enterprises Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Mandex Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Sentek Global; SPARC LLC</tag>
    <tag>The Cameron Bell Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Gov. Solutions Group</tag>
    <tag>The Cybrix Group</tag>
    <tag>Ursa Navigation Solutions Inc.</tag>
    <tag>C5ISR</tag>
    <tag>SPAWAR</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Altron Inc., Mt. Pleasant, S.C.; American Electronics Inc., California, Md.; Command Decisions Systems and Solutions, Stafford, Va.; Centuria Corp., Reston, Va.; Del Rey Systems and Technology Inc., San Diego, Calif.; ISHPI Information Technologies Inc., Mt. Pleasant, S.C.; K3 Enterprises Inc., Fayetteville, N.C.; MANDEX Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Sentek Global, San Diego, Calif.; SPARC LLC., Charleston, S.C.; The Cameron Bell Corp., doing business as Gov. Solutions Group, Daniel Island, S.C.; The Cybrix Group*, Tampa, Fla.; and Ursa Navigation Solutions Inc., Chesapeake, Va., are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, performance-based, multiple award contract, with provisions for fixed-price-incentive and firm-fixed-price orders, to provide command, control, communications, computers, combat systems, intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance (C5ISR) electronics and communications services and solutions in support of mission capabilities within the decision superiority portfolio to improve customers’ ability to enable utilization of information and decision aids to support decision making in support of the warfighter's mission. These contracts include options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these multiple award contracts to an estimated $98,764,531. These 13 contractors may compete for the task orders under the terms and conditions of the awarded contracts. The contracting activity is the U.S. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, S.C.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
