<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Navy Awards Nearly $250 Million for C5ISR</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>December 21, 2012</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Barling Bay LLC</tag>
    <tag>Cambridge International Systems</tag>
    <tag>Centuria Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Chugach Information Technology Inc.</tag>
    <tag>CommIT Enterprises</tag>
    <tag>Compass Systems Inc.</tag>
    <tag>DEL REY Systems and Technology</tag>
    <tag>Forward Slope Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Imagine One StraCon Venture</tag>
    <tag>KinetX</tag>
    <tag>Mandex Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Product Data Integration Technologies</tag>
    <tag>Modulant</tag>
    <tag>Trace Systems Inc.</tag>
    <tag>C5ISR</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text> 
Barling Bay LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; Cambridge International Systems Inc., Arlington, Va.; Centuria Corp., Reston, Va.; Chugach Information Technology Inc., Anchorage, Alaska; CommIT Enterprises Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Compass Systems Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; DEL REY Systems and Technology Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Forward Slope Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Imagine One StraCon Venture LLC, Fort Worth, Texas; KinetX, Tempe, Ariz.; MANDEX Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Product Data Integration Technologies Inc. doing business as Modulant, North Charleston, S.C.; Trace Systems Inc., Tysons Corner, Va., are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee with fixed-price incentive (firm target) and firm-fixed-price provisions, multiple-award contract for the procurement of decision superiority support (DS) services. The services required include research, development, test, evaluation, production and fielding of sustainable, secure, survivable, and interoperable command, control, communications, computers, combat systems, intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance (C5ISR), information operations, enterprise information services (EIS) and space capabilities. These contracts include options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these contracts to an estimated $249,951,000. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, S.C. is the contracting activity.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
