<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Firms Awarded C5ISR Contracts</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>February 1, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Ace Info Solutions Inc.</tag>
    <tag>aVenture Technologies LLC</tag>
    <tag>Barling Bay LLC</tag>
    <tag>Centuria Corp.</tag>
    <tag>DKW Communications Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Dynamic Network Enterprises</tag>
    <tag>ECSI International Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Imagine One StraCon Venture LLC</tag>
    <tag>Integrated Technology Solutions Group JV</tag>
    <tag>Mandex Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Product Data Integration Technologies Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Network Security Systems Plus Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Sysorex Government Services Inc.</tag>
    <tag>C5ISR</tag>
    <tag>SPAWAR</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text> 
Ace Info Solutions Inc., Reston, Va.; aVenture Technologies LLC, Vienna, Va.; Barling Bay LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; Centuria Corp., Reston, Va.; DKW Communications Inc., Washington. D.C.; Dynamic Network Enterprises, Stafford, Va.; ECSI International Inc., Clifton, N.J.; Imagine One StraCon Venture LLC, Fort Worth, Texas; Integrated Technology Solutions Group Joint Venture, Fairfax, Va.; Mandex Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Product Data Integration Technologies Inc., North Charleston, S.C.; Network Security Systems Plus Inc., Falls Church, Va.; and Sysorex Government Services Inc. Herndon, Va., are each being awarded an indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, with provisions for fixed-price-incentive (firm target) and firm-fixed-price task orders, performance based contract for the procurement of business and force support services including the entire spectrum of non-inherently governmental services and solutions (equipment and services) associated with the full system lifecycle support including research, development, test, evaluation, production and fielding of sustainable, secure, survivable, and interoperable Command, Control, Communication, Computers, Combat Systems, Intelligence, Surveillance, Reconnaissance (C5ISR), Information Operations, Enterprise Information Services and Space capabilities. The cumulative, estimated value of the base year is $49,918,000. These contracts include options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these contracts to an estimated $249,590,000. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, S.C., is the contracting activity. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
