<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>University Fills Procurement Education Gap</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 14, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Acquisition</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Old Dominion University (ODU) now offers a graduate-level procurement program that focuses on how to support cost savings, improve efficiencies and determine other strategic goals for public-sector organizations.
 </abstract>
  <text>Old Dominion University (ODU) now offers a graduate-level procurement program that focuses on how to support cost savings, improve efficiencies and determine other strategic goals for public-sector organizations. The graduate certificate stand-alone program comprises 15 credits: four required courses and one elective. Students can take these courses online or at the university in Norfolk, Virginia.
	Core program courses include public sector contract administration, public sector procurement law and ethics, and public-private partnership. Electives that can be applied toward earning a certificate include courses on leadership, public financial management, and negotiation and dispute resolution.
	Stephen Gordon, faculty member in ODU’s Department of Urban Studies and Public Administration, helped found this program based on his 35 years of experience as a leading expert in public procurement. “Most people don’t realize that procurement is a strategic function. It can impact whether an organization succeeds or fails,” he says. Gordon also was instrumental in rolling out the country’s first U.S. university to offer a for-credit graduate-level procurement program that does not focus exclusively on federal government procurement at Florida Atlantic University.
	Anyone who has completed a bachelor’s or master’s degree at an accredited educational institution can apply for admission to the certificate program. More information about the program and registration forms are available online.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
