<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Nuclear Agency's Cloud Computing Plan Comes Together</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>March 20, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cloud computing</tag>
    <tag>Energy</tag>
    <tag>mobile</tag>
    <tag>SIGNAL Extras</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The U.S. National Nuclear Security Administration (NNSA) began working on its Yourcloud solution about two years ago and expects to have the cloud computing solution in place by year's end. You can read more about this in "U.S. Nuclear Agency Enhances Cybersecurity With Cloud Computing?." 
One of the surprises along the way to cloud was that NNSA is not alone in the problems it needs to solve, according to Travis Howerton, NNSA chief technology officer. "When we first started putting this together, I would have thought that we were more unique than we are, but when I traveled around talking to other chief information officers and other leaders in government agencies, or even in the commercial sector, everybody's struggling with the same set of issues," Howerton observes. "In general, what surprised me is how much synergy there is in trying to solve this problem government-wide. We're happy to be part of that overall ecosystem and to share with others what we're doing that may be helpful."
	Agency officials spent about a year developing a strategic plan for transformation, which includes three pillars: the NNSA Network Vision (2NV), which modernizes the current computing environment by providing a secure, mobile, agile and adaptive IT infrastructure that will allow the NNSA workforce to perform their duties from any device, anywhere, any time; the Joint Cybersecurity Coordination Center (JC3), which provides the agency a capability for understanding the health of the systems, data and network; and the Cyber Sciences Laboratory (CSL), which establishes a process through which theoretical research in IT and cybersecurity can be rapidly applied to operational computing environments.
	 
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
