<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>With Government Training Hamstrung by Sequestration, Alternatives Appear</title>
  <author>Beverly Cooper</author>
  <date>May 3, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Extras</tag>
    <tag>East Joint Warfighting 2013</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Budget sequestration has made obtaining government-mandated training more difficult—this despite government requirements that individuals earn continuing education units (CEUs) and certification maintenance units (CMUs)”to keep current in their professions. Many of the opportunities in the past were centered around large-scale, efficient training that could certify more people by bringing groups together. However, travel restrictions have complicated this centralized collaboration.
	Many organizations and defense-related associations now are providing the training and education needed in unique ways at low or no cost as part of their missions in support of military and government. By using local conference formats, they can deliver the content needed for CEUs, and industry and government are able to maintain the essential dialogue that eliminates waste and leads to relevant and needed services and programs.
	For example, through the Engagement Theater concept at the upcoming AFCEA-USNI East: Joint Warfighting in Virginia Beach, May 14 to 16, individuals can hear from preferred providers and other subject matter experts on topics that qualify for CEUs. The Cyber Theater offers CompTIA CEUs through Cypherpath LLC. Several panels at the conference offer CEUs as well, including one at 10 a.m. on May 14 called, “A Contested Environment: How Do We Provide Effective Command and Control to Operators?” An individual can attend the panel and Engagement Theater without cost.
	Another option for training credits is called NetWars, and it is being offered through the SANS Institute through AFCEA at half price during this conference starting May 15. NetWars is a computer and network security challenge that will test experience and skill in a controlled environment with other security professionals. The scoreboard is public, so players and spectators can keep track of the standings. Participants must bring their own laptops to participate. NetWars qualifies for up to 12 SANS CMUs in support of GIAC certifications and seven CompTIA CEUs in support of A+, Network+ and Security+ certifications. Additional technical information is available at http://www.afcea.org/events/jwc/13/netwars.asp. 
	Additional affordable professional development courses are available at the same venue during the week. More information on CEUs and CMUs at East: Joint Warfighting can be found on the conference website.
	To register for East: Joint Warfighting, visit http://www.afcea.org/events/register.cfm?ev=200.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
