<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Firms Awarded C5ISR Contracts</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>May 10, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>C5ISR</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text> 
BAE Systems, Rockville, Md.; Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Va.; CACI Inc., Federal, Chantilly, Va.; CGI Federal, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Computer Sciences Corp., Falls Church, Va.; Deloitte Consulting LLP, Alexandria, Va.; General Dynamics One Source, Fairfax, Va.; HP Enterprise Services LLC, Herndon, Va.; Engility Corp., Mount Laurel, N.J.; Lockheed Martin Information Systems &amp; Global Solutions, Herndon, Va.; MC Dean Inc., Dulles, Va.; SAIC Inc., McLean, Va.; Scientific Research Corp., Atlanta, Ga.; Secure Mission Solutions LLC, Washington D.C.; and URS Federal Services Inc., Germantown, Md., are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, with provisions for fixed-price-incentive (firm target) and firm-fixed-price task orders, performance based contract. The contracts are for the procurement of business and force support services including the entire spectrum of non-inherently governmental services and solutions (equipment and services) associated with the full system lifecycle support including research, development, test, evaluation, production and fielding of sustainable, secure, survivable, and interoperable command, control, communication, computers, combat systems, intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance, information operations, enterprise information services and space capabilities. The cumulative, estimated value (ceiling) of the base year is $179,908,000. These contracts include options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value (ceiling) of these contracts to an estimated $899,543,000. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, S.C., is the contracting activity. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
