<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Awards Nearly $900 Million in Cyber Operations Contracts</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>July 17, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Cyber Operations</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Booz Allen Hamilton Inc., McLean, Va.; CACI Technologies Inc., Chantilly, Va.; Computer Sciences Corp., Falls Church, Va.; General Dynamics One Source LLC, Fairfax, Va.; Honeywell Technology Solutions Inc., Columbia, Md.; Engility Corp., Mount Laurel, N.J.; Lockheed Martin Services Inc., Gaithersburg, Md.; Science Applications International Corp., McLean, Va.; Scientific Research Corp., Atlanta, Ga.; Secure Mission Solutions, Fairfax, Va.; STG Inc., Reston, Va.; Systems Research and Applications Corp., Fairfax, Va.; and URS Federal Services Inc., Germantown, Md., are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, with provisions for fixed-price-incentive (firm target) and firm-fixed-price task orders, performance based contract. The contracts are for the procurement of integrated cyber operations services including the entire spectrum of non-inherently governmental services and solutions (equipment and services) associated with the full system lifecycle support, including research, development, test, evaluation, production and fielding of sustainable, secure, survivable, and interoperable command, control, communication, computers, combat systems, intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance (C5ISR), information operations, enterprise information services (EIS) and space capabilities. The cumulative, estimated value (ceiling) of the base year is $179,908,600. These contracts include options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value (ceiling) of these contracts to an estimated $899,543,400. Work will be performed worldwide as the task orders are issued. Work is expected to be completed by July 2014. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, S.C., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
