<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Halvorsen: DISA Cloud Contract Will Simplify Things</title>
  <author>Max Cacas</author>
  <date>July 18, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>AFCEA Answers</tag>
    <tag>cloud computing</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>In the coming months, the Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) is expected to issue its multiaward contract for cloud computing services.
	Terry Halvorsen, chief information officer with the Department of the Navy, believes that the contract will make his life simpler.  “Much as we have done with our software enterprise licencing program, where we have bundled up the requirements, and we can go to the marketplace, DISA will be able to bundle the requirements, and we’ll be able to go in, and we will represent a much bigger share of the market, more money on the table, and that will get us much more competitive pricing,” he says in a recent episode of the new AFCEA Answers radio program.
	In addition, the military services will have even more options for using cloud computing to perform their missions, according to Henry Fleischman, chief technologist, Federal Cloud Solutions, Hewlett-Packard in Washington.
“It will provide a mechanism to consume cloud services that are certified for government use [and] safe for the end users at different agencies to consume, and I think it will open up an ecosystem of cloud service providers that agencies can have a direct relationship with,” he explains.
	Another outcome, says Fleischman, is that it will, “drive a level of standardization in the cloud offerings for government, in that, by being a certified DISA cloud provider, it will allow agencies to be more direct about what we want today.”
	He also believes that in the long-run, a successful multi-award contract for cloud computing services will also offer his service more competitive pricing, and at the same time make the contract more valuable to cloud service providers chosen to offer commercial cloud services to the military. What do you think?  Will a multi-vendor cloud services contract be a win-win for both industry and government? And how will it affect your agency or company?Got a question? Got an answer? AFCEA Answers wants to hear from you – join in the conversation!Max Cacas is the host and producer of AFCEA Answers, heard every other Friday on Federal News Radio 1500 AM in Washington, D.C., and online at FederalNewsRadio.com. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
