<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>FBI Creates New Cyber Information Sharing Portal</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>July 30, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
    <department>Intelligence</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Law Enforcement Technologies</tag>
    <tag>Security</tag>
    <tag>Global Intelligence Forum 2013</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The FBI has created an information sharing portal for cyber defense modeled on its Guardian counterterrorism portal. Known as iGuardian, the trusted portal represents a new FBI thrust to working more closely with industry on defeating cyberthreats. It is being piloted within the longtime InfraGard portal, according to an FBI cyber expert.
 </abstract>
  <text>The FBI has created an information sharing portal for cyber defense modeled on its Guardian counterterrorism portal. Known as iGuardian, the trusted portal represents a new FBI thrust to working more closely with industry on defeating cyberthreats. It is being piloted within the longtime InfraGard portal, according to an FBI cyber expert.
	Rick McFeely, executive assistant director of the FBI’s Criminal, Cyber, Response and Services Branch, told the audience at the AFCEA Global Intelligence Forum in the National Press Club in Washington, D.C., that information sharing with private industry is absolutely essential for defeating the cyberattacks on private networks.
	McFeely admitted that this increased information sharing with the private sector is a relatively recent development. “The FBI was not a good partner in this arena until a year and a half ago,” he allowed. Previously, the FBI would be afraid to notify companies of intrusions out of fear of revealing collection methods. Now, the bureau is going after those intruders, even those who are overseas, and it wants help from industry. Vital information on intrusions can help prevent and deter future attacks.
	“About 90 percent of the intelligence that sits out there resides with private industry,” McFeely declared.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
