<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>New Capabilities, Though Needed, May Not Be a Panacea for Cybersecurity</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>July 30, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
    <department>Intelligence</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Security</tag>
    <tag>Global Intelligence Forum 2013</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Information sharing, automated intelligence reporting and all-source analysis capabilities are cited by many experts as being necessary for helping ensure cybersecurity. However, the human element must remain not only present, but also dominant, in any cybersecurity process.
	That was one point presented in a panel discussion at the AFCEA Global Intelligence Forum in the National Press Club in Washington, D.C. Rear Adm. Elizabeth Train, USN, director for intelligence, J-2, the Joint Staff, cited an automated unclassified intelligence reporting system as one capability that is needed but is still a way off.
	She added that all-source analysis is still the key to good intelligence. Information sharing is another desirable capability, although achieving it is a challenge across the entire intelligence community, not just in cyber, she noted.
	While endorsing the need for new capabilities, Mark Young, former executive director, Directorate for Plans and Policy, U.S. Cyber Command, sounded a cautionary note. “Correlation does not necessarily mean causation—the role of the analyst is even more critical,” he declared. “We use these automated tools to find the needle, but so what?
	“We can talk about the pace of technology all we want, but if you have the proper mindset for analysis, the technology doesn’t matter,” Young emphasized.
	Young agreed that industry can help with cyber threat intelligence, but it may be elusive. “We need information sharing legislation, but I don’t think it’s going to happen,” he offered.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
