<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Supports Missile Defense for Multiple Nations</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>August 13, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
    <department>International</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>missile defense</tag>
    <tag>Foreign Military Sales</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Missile Systems, Tucson, Ariz., is being awarded a $200,504,841 modification to a previously awarded firm-fixed-price, fixed-price-incentive-firm target contract (N00019-11-C-0001) for the procurement of 354 each AIM-9X Block II All Up Round Tactical Low Rate Initial Production Lot 13 Missiles and Block II Active Optical Target Detectors for the U.S. Navy (92), U.S. Air Force (92), and the governments of Morocco (20), Malaysia (20), Kuwait (80); and Oman (50). In addition, this modification provides for the procurement of 178 Block II Captive Air Training Missiles for the U.S. Navy (58), U.S. Air Force (58), and the governments of Morocco (10), Malaysia (8), Kuwait (20), and Oman (24); nine Special Air Training Missiles for the U.S. Navy (7) and the government of Saudi Arabia (2); 147 All Up Round Containers for the U.S. Navy (43), U.S. Air Force (39), and the governments of Saudi Arabia (1), Morocco (9), Malaysia (8), Kuwait (28), and Oman (19); 19 Guidance Unit Containers for the governments of Malaysia (6), Kuwait (6) and Oman (7); three Spare Propulsion Steering Sections for the U.S. Navy (1), U.S. Air Force (1) and the government of Morocco (1); one Spare Missile Tube Assembly for the government of Morocco; three Spare Advanced Optical Target Detectors for the U.S. Navy (1) and U.S. Air Force (2); 20 Spare Tactical Guidance Units for the U.S. Navy (4), U.S. Air Force (4), and the governments of Morocco (2), Malaysia (2), Kuwait (2) and Oman (6); one Spare Inertial Measuring Unit for the government of Switzerland; and 26 Spare Captive Air Training Missile Guidance Units for the U.S. Navy (4), U.S. Air Force (8), and the governments of Morocco (4), Malaysia (4), Kuwait (2) and Oman (4). The Naval Air Systems Command, Patuxent River, Md., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
