<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Is Big Data the Way ?Ahead for Intelligence?</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 1, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Intelligence</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cloud computing</tag>
    <tag>data management</tag>
    <tag>big data</tag>
    <tag>Point-Counterpoint</tag>
    <tag>Viewpoint</tag>
    <tag>October 2013</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>
				Another Overhyped Fad
				By Mark M. Lowenthal
				Director of National Intelligence Lt. Gen. James R. Clapper, USAF (Ret.), once observed that one of the peculiar behaviors of the intelligence community is to erect totem poles to the latest fad, dance around them until exhaustion sets in, and then congratulate oneself on a job well done.
				One of our more recent totem poles is big data. Big data is a byproduct of the wired world we now inhabit. The ability to amass and manipulate large amounts of data on computers offers, to some, tantalizing possibilities for analysis and forecasting that did not exist before. A great deal of discussion about big data has taken place, which in essence means the possibility of gaining new insights and connections from the reams of new data created every day.
					Or does it?Read the complete perspective
			
			
				A Longtime Tool of the Community
				By Lewis Shepherd
				What do modern intelligence agencies run on? They are internal combustion engines burning pipelines of data, and the more fuel they burn the better their mileage. Analysts and decision makers are the drivers of these vast engines; but to keep them from hoofing it, we need big data.
				The intelligence community necessarily has been a pioneer in big data since inception, as both were conceived during the decade after World War II. The intelligence community and big data science always have been intertwined because of their shared goal: producing and refining information describing the world around us, for important and utilitarian purposes.
				Read the complete perspective
			
		
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
