<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Georgia Tech Racks Up Five Awards</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>September 23, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Georgia Tech Applied Research Corp.</tag>
    <tag>sensors</tag>
    <tag>electronic warfare</tag>
    <tag>modeling and simulation</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text> 
Georgia Tech Applied Research Corp., Atlanta, Ga., was awarded a $25 million delivery order to contract HC1047-05-D-4000-0249 for development and support of Multi-spectral Missile Warning System Systems Integration Lab for U.S. Army Communication and Electronic Command, Software Engineering Center/Army Reprograming and Analysis Team Electronic Warfare. The organization also was awarded a $24,999,999 delivery order to contract HC1047-05-D-4000-0252 for PMA209 systems engineering, design and development. The delivery order will focus on achieving sensor suite integration, supporting sensor fusion algorithm development, making situational awareness enhancements and better supporting the system's organic sustainment efforts for a variety of fixed wing and rotary aircraft. The third award was a $19,182,573 delivery order to contract HC1047-05-D-4000-0256 for joint electronic advanced technology engineering (JEAT). The delivery order will focus on enhancing JEAT's ability to provide offensive and defensive capabilities throughout the electromagnetic spectrum for dominance while formulating strategies related to electronic warfare's convergence with other domains. The fourth was a a $14,980,979 delivery order to contract HC1047-05-D-4000-0257 for AATTC sensor, EW, tactics, integration, engineering and training. The delivery order will focus on generation of threat system modeling and simulation roadmaps, engineering studies to identify investment alternatives; generation of system roadmaps with investment strategies; technology insertion including hardware and software design, prototyping, debugging, integration and qualification; modeling and simulation analysis; and flight test engineering to include test strategies. The fifth award was an $8,989,312 delivery order to contract HC1047-05-D-4000-0261 for AATC sensor, modernization and EWCTF integration engineering and test. The delivery order will focus on identification, generation, evaluation, test and documentation of modernization solutions to address modernization requirements for aircraft, sensors and support systems. The Enterprise Sourcing Group at Offutt Air Force Base, Neb., is the contracting activity for all awards.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
