<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>C4 Integration with Tactical Vehicles Demonstrated</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 24, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>One of the U.S. Army’s top priorities is ensuring the right information is available in any environment down to the lowest tactical level on the battlefield. Oshkosh Defense, recently demonstrated its command, control, communications and computers (C4) and systems integration capabilities to connect soldiers to the network on its MRAP All-Terrain Vehicle (M-ATV).</abstract>
  <text>One of the U.S. Army’s top priorities is ensuring the right information is available in any environment down to the lowest tactical level on the battlefield. Oshkosh Defense, recently demonstrated its command, control, communications and computers (C4) and systems integration capabilities to connect soldiers to the network on its MRAP All-Terrain Vehicle (M-ATV). Oshkosh integrates C4 equipment and a full range of weapons and other systems in the initial vehicle design process to reduce potential system conflicts or interference. Complete assembly line installation and quality control processes also eliminate the cost and quality issues related to tearing apart and reassembling the vehicle to run wiring harnesses and connectors. 
	 
	For its Joint Light Tactical Vehicle (JLTV) solution, Oshkosh Defense developed multiple JLTV mission package configurations. The 22 JLTV prototypes that Oshkosh delivered to the government in August for the Engineering and Manufacturing Development phase were fully integrated and tested by Oshkosh. Responding to an urgent need in Afghanistan for the M-ATV in 2009, Oshkosh Defense delivered its vehicles pre-wired and ready for C4 equipment. This contributed to the life-saving vehicles being designed, produced and delivered at a rate of more than 1,000 per month, all in less than one year’s time.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
