<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>The Price of Life in the United States: 1946 vs. 2006</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Magazine Staff</author>
  <date>September 2006</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Anniversary Section</tag>
    <tag>September 2006</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Among the most pervasive changes of the past 60 years has been the cost of living. No costs or salaries could remain static during six decades of capitalism, as 1946 saw the beginning of the removal of wartime wage and price controls. Major economic growth </abstract>
  <text>Among the most pervasive changes of the past 60 years has been the cost of living. No costs or salaries could remain static during six decades of capitalism, as 1946 saw the beginning of the removal of wartime wage and price controls. Major economic growth ensued, aided and abetted by technology innovations that continue to transform society.The figures below represent the average costs of U.S. items in 1946 and in 2006. Between those 60 years, the inflation rate depreciated the dollar’s buying power elevenfold, such that $1 in 2006 buys roughly what 9 cents bought in 1946. But, while many prices rose considerably, salaries often increased to a greater degree during that period, so individuals had much greater relative earning power. And, if inflation is factored in, the cost of some commodities actually dropped over time. Still, some of the numbers offer an interesting contrast: Item19462006Federal Minimum Hourly Wage$0.40    $5.15Average Annual Income$2,600  $37,900House   $5,150  $266,000Monthly Rent     $35       $950New Car            $1,125  $28,800First-Class U.S. Postage$0.03$0.39One-Year Tuition at Harvard            $420     $30,275 Movie Ticket      $0.55    $6.04Gallon of Gasoline          $0.21    $3.03Gallon of Milk$0.67    $3.231 Dozen Eggs    $0.59    $0.98Loaf of White Bread        $0.10    $0.97AFCEA Membership      $4 (SIGNAL $3 extra)$35 (with SIGNAL)Computer          $486,804.00 (ENIAC)            $299.99(2.93-GHz HPa1200y desktop)(U.S. government, professional and trade association averages derived through second quarter of 2006.) ENIAC = electronic numerical integrator and computer.  </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
