<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Selects 914 SeaPort-e Contractors</title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 22, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>SeaPort-E</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Navy is awarding indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, multiple-award contracts to 914 contractors that will provide for their competition for service requirements solicited by Naval Sea Systems Command, Naval Air Systems Command, Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, Naval Supply Systems Command, Military Sealift Command, Naval Facilities Command, Strategic Systems Programs, Office of Naval Research and the U.S. Marine Corps. The 22 functional service areas within the scope of the contracts include: 1) research and development support, 2) engineering system engineering and process engineering support, 3) modeling, simulation, stimulation and analysis support, 4) prototyping, pre-production, model-making and fabric support, 5) system design documentation and technical data support, 6) software engineering, development, programming and network support, 7) reliability, maintainability and availability support, 8) human factors, performance and usability engineering support, 9) system safety engineering support, 10) configuration management support, 11) quality assurance support, 12) information system development, information assurance and information technology support, 13) ship inactivation and disposal support, 14) interoperability, test and evaluation, trials support, 15) measurement facilities, range and instrumentation support, 16) acquisition logistics support, 17) supply and provisioning support, 18) training support, 19) in-service engineering, fleet introduction, installation and checkout support, 20) program support, 21) functional and administrative support, and 22) public affairs and multimedia support. These contracts are in addition to the existing 2,838 contracts previously awarded under the SeaPort Enhanced (SeaPort-e) acquisition program for services procurements. The government estimates a maximum of $5,300,000,000 of services will be procured per year via orders issued under the SeaPort-e multiple award contracts. The Naval Surface Warfare Center, Dahlgren Division, Dahlgren, Va., is the contracting activity (N00178-14-D-7128 -- N00178-14-D-8045). The list of contractors involved are:  1 Source Consulting, Inc., Germantown, Md.; 2Is Inc., Walpole, Mass.; 4M Research Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; A2 Systems Engineering Inc., El Segundo, Calif.; A2B Tracking Solutions, Inc., Portsmouth, R.I.; AAR Parts Trading Inc. doing business as (dba) AAR Defense Systems and Logistics, Wood Dale, Ill.; A-B Computer  Solutions, Inc., Mandeville, La.; Accent Controls, Inc., Riverside, Mo.; Access Personnel Services, Inc., Lancaster, Pa.; Acquisition Systems Associates, Inc., Great Falls, Va.; Adaptive Consulting &amp; Training Services, LLC dba ACTS, Stafford, Va.; Adela Technologie, Leonardtown,, Md.; Aderas, Inc., Reston, Va.; Advanced Mission Systems, LLC, Charlotte, N.C.; Advanced Professional Consulting, Inc. dba Veteran Technologists, Aberdeen, Md.; Advanced Sciences and Technologies, LLC., Berlin, N.J.; Advanced Technology Services dba OptiDo, Marietta, Ga.; Advanced Technology Systems Co., Inc. (Of Virginia), Mclean, Va. ; Advantage SCI, LLC, El Segundo, Calif.; Advent Business Co., Inc., Aurora , Ill.; Advent SVCS LLC, Panama City Beach, Fla.; AED, Inc., Hyattsville, Md.; Affinity Fidelis Consulting and Technologies, LLC dba Affinity Fidelis , Fredericksburg, Va.; AFGlobe Communications Inc. dba ACI Solutions, Sterling, Va.; Agile Government Services, Inc., Overland Park, Kan.; Ahtna Support and Training Services, LLC, Anchorage, Alaska; AINET Corp., Beltsville, Md.; Air Logistics and Engineering Consultants, LLC, Warner Robins, Ga.; Aitheras, LLC dba Aitheras, Rockville, Md.; Alexandria Insights, Inc., Fairfax Station, Va.; All U Need Temporary Services dba All U Need Personnel, Washington, D.C.; Allen Corp. of America, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Allied Reliability, Inc., North Charleston, S.C.; AlphaSix Corp., Sterling, Va.; American Computer Development Inc. dba ACDI, Frederick, Md.; American Society for Engineering Education dba ASEE, Washington, D.C.; America's Staffing Partner, Inc., Bethlehem, Pa.; AMP Management Consulting LLC, Fredericksburg, Va.; Ampcus Inc., Chantilly , Va.; Anderson Solutions &amp; Associates dba ASA, Fredericksburg, Va.; Anglicotech LLC, Washington, D.C.; Apex Data Systems Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; Apogee Engineering, LLC, Colorado Springs, Colo.; Applied Computer Science Group, Inc., Bowie, Md.; Applied Visual Technology, Inc. dba AVT Simulation, Orlando, Fla.; Aranea Solutions, Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; Arch Systems, Baltimore, Md.; Ardent Technologies, Inc., Dayton, Ohio; Armada, Ltd, Powell, Ohio; Art Anderson Associates, Inc., Bremerton, Wash.; ASP Web Solutions, LLC, Bartlett, Tenn.; Augustine Consulting, Inc., Monterey, Calif.; AURA Systems Technologies, San Dimas, Calif.; Avanco International, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Avani Technology Solutions Inc., Rochester, N.Y.; Averalink Information Systems, LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; Avion Solutions, Inc. dba Avion, Huntsville, Ala.; AVOSYS Technology, Inc., San Antonio, Texas; AVPOL International LLC dba AIL, Memphis, Tenn.; Axiom Resource Management, Inc. , Falls Church, Va.; B&amp;L Machine &amp; Fabrication, Norfolk, Va.; Badger Defense Group Inc., Orlando, Fla.; Banner Staffing, Washington, D.C.; Barba Consulting, Inc., Marlton, N.J.; BarnAllen Technologies, Inc., Rockville, Md.; Barnett Engineering &amp; Signaling Laboratories, Colorado Springs, Colo.; Bayfield Technology Group, Inc., Luray, Va. ; Bayonet Inc., San Diego, Calif.; BFG Systems LLC dba: BFG Systems, Saint Petersburg, Fla.; BITHOP Systems, Inc., Springfield, Va.; Bitterroot Services &amp; Technology LLC dba BST, Florence, Mont; BleuForce, LLC, Chula Vista, Calif.; Blue Tang Solutions, Inc., Coronado, Calif.; Boarhog LLC, San Diego, Calif.; Boulevard Consulting Group, LLC, Arlington, Va.; Bowhead Professional Solutions, LLC dba BPS, Alexandria, Va.; Bowler Pons Solutions Consultants, LLC dba Immigration Integrity Group, Arnold, Md.; Bridge Group, LLC, Bumpass, Va.; BuddoBot Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Business Enterprises &amp; Systems Technology, Inc. dba BESTech, McLean, Va.; C Parker Consulting, Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; Carolina Growler Inc., Star, N.C.; Catalyst Solutions, LLC, Stafford, Va.; CATVIDEO, Inc. dba CATMEDIA, Tucker, Ga.; Caulfield Consulting, Inc., Ashburn, Va.; CB Technologies, Inc., Westminster, Calif.; C-Edge Software Consultants LLC, Saint Louis, Mo.; Center for Applied Innovation, Yorktown, Va.; Center for Organizational Excellence, Inc., Rockville, Md.; Cherokee Nation Red Wing, LLC, Tulsa, Okla.; CHP Solutions, Stafford, Va.; Citadel Logic, LLC, Hampton, Va.; Claxton Logistics Services, LLC, Stafford, Va.; Cobec Consulting, Inc., Manassas, Va.; Comptech PC, Fort Pierce, Fla.; Computational Physics, Inc., Springfield, Va.; Computer Technologies Consultants, Inc. dba CTC, Seabrook, Md.; Concord Crossroads, Manassas, Va.; Conetsco, Inc., Manassas, Va.; Consortium for Ocean Leadership Inc., Washington, D.C.; Constellation Software Engineering Corp., Lanham, Md.; Converge IT Solutions, LLC, Clinton, Md.; Mager, William Grant dba Core Services Group, Virginia Beach, Va.; CoreSys Consulting Services, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Coronata Systems, Inc., Ardmore, Tenn.; Cougaar Software, Inc., Vienna, Va.; Covell Solutions, Vienna, Va.; Creative Business Solutions, Inc., Washington, D.C.; Crewestone Technologies, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; Crown Consulting, Inc., Arlington, Va.; CTCA.info, LLC, Edgewater, Md.; Customer Inspired Solutions, LLC, King of Prussia, Pa.; Cyber Security Engineering Associates LLC dba CSEA, Baltimore, Md.; Cyber Technology Services, Inc. dba Cytech Services, Manassas, Va.; Daniel Eke and Associates, PC, Silver Spring, Md.; Data Tactics Corp., McLean, Va.; Datalis Solutions Corp., Montvale, N.J.; Daylight Defense, LLC, San Diego, Calif.; DeNovo Solutions LLC, Centennial, Colo.; Designed Consulting LLC, Yuma, Ariz.; DCAPS Inc., Shalimar, Fla.; Digital Consultants LLC, Mclean, Va.; Dignitas Technologies LLC, Orlando, Fla.; Dilks - Simone Enterprises, Inc., North Charleston, S.C.; DirectViz Solutions LLC, Chantilly, Va.; DuChancell Engineering Consulting, Del Mar, Calif.; Durbin Group, LLC, Spotsylvania, Va.; Dynamic Computer Corp. dba Connecting Point Computer Center, Farmington Hills, Mich.; Dynamic Management Associates, Woodbridge, Va.; Dynamic Pro Inc., Alexandria, Va.; ECLAT Integrated Software Solutions, Inc.., Stafford, Texas; Edwards Group LLC dba Polaris Technology Solutions, Aldie, Va.; Effecture, LLC, San Diego, Calif.; eKuber Ventures Inc., Herndon, Va.; Elda and Edwina International Inc., Columbia, Md.; Electro Standards Laboratory Inc. dba Electro Standards Laboratories, Cranston, R.I.; e-Management Consultants, Inc., Silver Spring, Md.; Emerging Technology Support LLC, Mooresville, N.C.; Eminent IT, LLC dba Eminent, Arlington, Va.; Energy Plus Limited dba Energy Research Consultants, Laguna Hills, Calif.; Enformatica, San Diego, Calif.; Engineering Solutions and Products LLC, Eatontown, N.J.; Envision, LLC., Saint Louis, Mo.; ENX Group, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; EPIC Consulting Planning &amp; Business Information LLC, Springfield, Va.; ESEA, Los Altos, Calif.; Estuate Inc., Sunnyvale, Calif.; Etelic Inc., Glen Allen, Va.; eTRANSERVICES LLC, Fredericksburg, Va.; Evanhoe &amp; Associates, Inc. dba AIDC Solutions, Dayton, Ohio; Evergreen Fire Alarms, LLC dba Evergreen Fire &amp;Security, Tacoma, Wash.; Evigilant.com Inc. dba eVigilant Security, Lorton, Va.; Explosive Ordnance Mission Focused Defense LLC dba EOMFD, Goose Creek, S.C.; Extreme Data Technologies LLC, Norwalk, Conn.; EyeIT.com, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Fathom 4, LLC, Charleston, S.C.; FedForce, Inc., Reston, Va.; Field Data Technology, LLC, Fairfax, Va.; Flight Test Aerospace, Inc., Chantilly, Va.; G2SF, INC., Reston, Va.; GameSim Inc., Orlando, Fla.; Gantec Corp., Schaumburg, Ill.; Gartner, Inc., Stamford, Conn.; GCorp Consulting dba GKORP, Chula Vista, Calif.; Gemini Industries Inc., Burlington, Mass.; GeoNorth, LLC, Anchorage, Alaska; Germanos Defense Services, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; GET Engineering, El Cajon, Calif.; GINIA Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Global Services International, LLC, Killeen, Texas; Global Solutions Group Inc., Detroit, Mich.; Government Contracting Services LLC, Roy, Wash.; Government Contracting Specialists, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; GRAVICOM LLC, Elnora, Ind.; GS5, LLC, Dumfries, Va.; Haven 365 LLC, Stafford, Va.; HCH Enterprises, LLC, Providence, R.I.; Heritage Services Corp., Cocoa, Fla.; Hester Group, Jacksonville, Fla.; Highbury Defense Group, San Diego, Calif.; Hosted Records Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Howard &amp; Co., Inc., Reston, Va.; HPT Advisory Services, LLC, McLean, Va.; H.T. Innovations, L.L.C., Chesterfield, Va.; Hyperion Biotechnology Inc., San Antonio, Texas; ICS Technologies, Inc., McLean, Va.; Ideation Inc., Chantilly, Va.; Identity Management Systems, LLC, Fredericksburg, Va.; IERUS Technologies, Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; Immersive Media Tactical Solutions, LLC, Fredericksburg, Va.; INADEV Corp., McLean, Va.; Incident Communication Solutions, LLC, Stevensville, Md.; Infinity Support Services, Aldie, Va.; Infolob Solutions, Inc., Irving, Texas; Information Innovators, Inc., Springfield, Va.; InfoStructures, Inc., Rockville, Md.; Innoflight, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Innovation Business Partners, Inc., Lavallette, N.J.; Innovative Algorithms, LLC, San Diego, Calif.; Innovative Services &amp; Solutions dba ISS, Mansfield, Texas; Innovim Defense Services LLC dba IDS, Oxon Hill, Md.; Integrated Defense Applications, LLC dba IDA Technology, El Paso, Texas; Integrated Financial Analysts, Ltd. dba INFINA, Tysons Corner, Va.; InteliTrac, Inc., Fort Worth, Texas; Intellectual Concepts, LLC, Atlanta, Ga.; Intelligent Automation Inc., Rockville, Md.; Interactive Government Holdings, LLC, Washington, D.C.; Interdyne Corp., Mooresville, N.C.; International Business Sales &amp; Services Corp. dba IBSS Corp, Silver Spring, Md.; INTER-OP.NET Inc. dba INTER-OP, Virginia Beach, Va.; InterOptions, LLC, Tampa, Fla.; IPSecure Inc., San Antonio, Texas; ISI Telemanagement Solutions, Inc., Schaumburg, Ill.; ISYS Inc. dba ISYS Technologies, Littleton, Colo.; IT Concepts, Inc., Ashburn, Va.; ITC Defense Corp., Arlington, Va.; IT-CNP, INC., Columbia, Md.; I-Three Solutions, LLC, Lexington Park, Md.; ITMC Solutions, LLC, Bristow, Va.; IWON, LLC, Colonial Beach , Va.; Jamison Professional Services, Inc., East Point, Ga.; JDR Unlimited, LLC, Melbourne, Fla.; Jered LLC dba PHR, Brunswick, Ga.; JETPUBS Inc., Hudson, WI; Joiner Associates LLC, Norfolk, Va.; Jones Lang LaSalle Americas, Inc. dba Public Institutions, Washington, D.C.; JRM Enterprises, Inc. dba JRM Technologies, Fredericksburg, Va.; Kalon, LLC, Supply, N.C.; KAMMS Group LLC, Woodbridge, Va.; Karsun Solutions LLC, Herndon, Va.; KCK Technologies, LLC, Fairfax, Va.; Kenific Group, Fairfax, Va.; Kilda Group, LLC, Annapolis, Md.; Kiple Acquisition Science Technology Logistics &amp; Engineering dba Kiple Consulting, Bel Air, Md.; Knowledge Capital Associates, LLC, Springfield, Va.; Knowledge Management Inc., Tyngsboro, Maine; Kutta Technologies, Inc., Phoenix, Ariz.; KZF Design, Inc., Cincinnati, Ohio; LDM &amp; Associates LLD dba LDM Group, LLC, Bethesda, Md.; Leading Edge Solutions, LLC, Fort Washington, Md.; Lee Defense Group, LLC  dba  Lee Defense Group, Springville, Ind.; Lexicon Consulting, Inc., El Cajon, Calif.; Lightspeed Technologies dba LP3, Fairfax, Va.; Links Media LLC dba Links Global, Rockville , Md. ; Lixis Technology LLC, Washington, D.C.; LLUCAS Corp., Washington, D.C.; Logistics Applications Inc., Alexandria, Va.; LR-Associates, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Lukos, LLC, Tampa, Fla.; Lumbee Resource Management Group, Jacksonville, Fla.; Lumbee Tribe Enterprises, LLC, Pembroke, N.C.; M1 Support Services LP, Denton, Texas; MacDonald-Bedford LLC, Alameda, Calif.; Macray Services and Solutions, LLC, Washington, D.C.; Mansai Corp., Greenbelt, Md.; MartinFederal Consulting, L.L.C., Auburn, Ala.; Masy Group LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Materials Sciences Corp., Horsham, Pa.; McFarland Technology, Inc., Murrysville, Pa.; McKenna Principals, Inc., Woodbridge, Va.; McKinney &amp; McKinney Techical Services Inc. dba M&amp;M Technical Services, Woodbridge, Va.; McLane Advanced Technologies, LLC, Temple, Texas; McNally Industries, LLC, Grantsburg, WI; MCS of Tampa, Inc. dba Mission Critical Solution, Tampa, Fla.; MDM Technical Services Corp. dba SASI Defense Technologies, Pittsburgh, Pa.; MDW Associates, LLC, McLean, Va.; Meridian Technologies, Inc., Jacksonville, Fla.; MESMO Inc. dba MESMOLSS, Waldorf, Md.; Metasystems, Inc., North Royalton, Ohio; MillerWilson Consulting, LLC dba MWC, North Charleston, S.C.; Minerva Systems &amp; Technologies, LLC, Lexington, KY; Mobius Consulting, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Mobius Industries USA, Inc., Kirkland, Wash.; Morgan 6, LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; Moriarty and Associates Consulting Corp. dba Moriarty and Associates, Fairfax, Va.; MSDS Consultant Services, LLC, Clinton, Md.; Murtech, Glen Burnie, Md.; NATECH Network Solutions LLC, Plano, Texas; National Technology &amp; Service Group LLC, San Diego, Calif.; Navigant Consulting, Inc., Chicago, Ill.; NAVTEC, Inc., Chula Vista, Calif.; NetCentrics Corp., Herndon, Va.; NetSecurity Corp. dba Netsecurity, Dulles, Va.; Network Runners, Inc., Ashburn, Va.; Nevins Software , Inc., Morris, Ill.; Nexagen Networks Inc., Aberdeen, Md.; Nexus Technology Solutions, LLC, Panama City Beach, Fla.; Nguyen Information Consulting dba Net-Integrated Consulting, West Des Moines, IA; NLT Corp. dba NETCOM Group, Springfield, Va.; North Star Group LLC, Washington, D.C.; northRamp LLC, Reston, Va.; Novitas Global Solutions LLC dba Novitas Group, Reston, Va.; NSC Technologies, Inc., Portsmouth, Va.; ODME Solutions, LLC, San Diego, Calif.; Old Breed, LLC, Quantico, Va.; Operational Support Group, Virginia Beach, Va.; OpTempo, LLC, Stafford, Va.; Optima Global Solutions, Inc., Lawrenceville, N.J.; Ordnance Holdings, Inc., Reisterstown, Md.; Orion Networking Inc., Great Falls, Va.; P2P Holdings LLC dba TekPartners Government Solutions, Coral Springs, Fla.; PAC Solutions, Stafford, Va.; Pacific Rim Aerospace Corp. dba PacRim Aero, Kirkland, Wash.; Patriot Maritime Compliance, LLC, Concord, Calif.; Payne Consulting Inc. dba Payne Consulting Services, Los Lunas, N.M.; PCI Strategic Management, LLC, Columbia, Md.; Pegasus Support Services, LLC, Woodstock, Ga.; Perceptium Group, Fredericksburg, Va.; Perceptix, LLC, Washington, D.C.; Perfecta Aviation, LLC dba PAVN, Alexandria, Va.; Persistent Systems, LLC, New York, N.Y.; Pharos Group, Inc., Stafford, Va.; Phoenix Data Security Inc., Phoenix, Ariz.; Phoenix Soft, Phoenix, Ariz.; Pinnakle Technologies Inc., Naperville, Ill.; Pioneer Corporate Services, Inc., Ashburn, Va.; Pioneer Technologies Corp., Las Vegas, Nev.; Piping Systems International, Inc., Bay Minette, Ala.; PKL Services Inc., Poway, Calif.; POGO Inc., Oceanside , Calif.; Portage, Inc. dba Portage Environmental Inc., Idaho Falls, Idaho; Porter Scientific, Inc. dba Porter Environmental, Pembroke, N.C.; Positioning Systems Research, La Jolla, Calif.; Premier Professional Systems, Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; Premier Solutions HI, LLC, Honolulu, Hawaii; PrimeTech International, Inc. , North Kansas City, Mo.; Professional Performance Development Group, Inc., San Antonio, Texas; Professional Services of America Inc. dba Professional Services of America, Parkersburg, W.Va.; Progressive Data Systems, Inc., Stafford, Va.; Promethean Technical Solutions, LLC, Fredericksburg, Va.; Provideo Management, Inc., Tysons Corner, Va.; QualBlazer, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; QSI, Inc. dba Quality Solutions Consulting Group, INC., Carlsbad, Calif.; QuickFlex Inc., San Antonio, Texas; R Dorsey &amp; Co. dba R.DORSEY+Co., Worthington, Ohio; Ranger Aerofab, LLC dba Ranger Enterprises, Springville, Ind.; Rapier Solutions, Inc. dba Simplified Computing Systems, Matthews, N.C.; RCT Systems, Inc., Linthicum, Md.; Red Tail, LLC, Arlington, Va.; REK Associates, LLC, Chantilly, Va.; RETTEW Associates, Inc., Lancaster, Pa.; Right Sized Solutions, Inc. dba RSSI, Sterling, Va.; RightDirection Technology Solutions, LLC, Baltimore, Md.; Risk Mitigation Consulting, Inc., Destin, Fla.; RLM Communications, Spring Lake, N.C.; Rock Creek Research, Data Management and Analysis LLC dba Rock Creek Data, Alexandria, Va.; RoundTable Defense, LLC, Stafford, Va.; RSL Fibersystems LLC, E. Hartford, Conn.; Sabel Systems Technology Solutions, LLC, Gainesville, Va.; SABRE88, LLC, Newark, N.J.; Saint Security Services, LLC, Springfield, Va.; Sapient Government Services Inc., Arlington, Va.; SAPTA Systems LLC, San Antonio, Texas; SAVID LLC, Saratoga, Calif.; SCI Consulting Services, Inc. dba Software Control International, McLean, Va.; SciTech Services dba SciTech, Havre de Grace, Md.; SDL Federal Solutions Inc., Reston, Va.; Sealund &amp; Associates Corp., St. Petersburg, Fla.; Sektor Solutions, Inc., Arlington, Va.; SEMAC LLC dba SEMAC, Virginia Beach, Va.; SENTAR Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; Shivan Technologies, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; SI Organization, Inc., King of Prussia, Pa.; Silverback7, Inc., Woodbridge, Va.; Six Degrees of Simulation, Inc., Orlando, Fla.; SofTec Solutions, Inc., Englewood, Colo.; Spartan Business &amp; Technology Services Inc. dba Spartan Business&amp; Technology Consulting, Alexandria, Va.; Spectra Tech Inc., Oak Ridge, Tenn.; Spin Systems, Inc., Sterling, Va.; Spinvi Consulting, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Squires Group Inc., Annapolis, Md.; STARA Technologies, Inc., Gilbert, Ariz.; Stauder Consulting, Inc., dba Stauder Technologies, St. Peters, Mo.; SteedPetro LLC, Washington, D.C.; Storage Strategies, Inc. dba SSI, Springfield, Va.; Strata G Solutions Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; Strategic Response Initiatives, LLC , Albany, N.Y.; Strategy and Management Services Inc. dba SAMS, Springfield, Va.; Strike Group LLC, Detroit, Mich.; Strong Castle, Inc., Washington, D.C.; Strongbridge Corp., Sterling, Va.; Succeed to Lead, LLC, Dumfries, Va.; SunMan Engineering, Inc., San Jose, Calif.; Sunrise Beach Corp. dba M2 Services Corp., McKinney, Texas; Synergy Aerospace, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; Syntelligent Analytic Solutions, LLC, Falls Church, Va.; Tactical Micro, Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; Takontrol, LLC, Annandale, Va.; Tanager, Inc., Annapolis Junction, Md.; Tandel Systems, Inc., Oldsmar, Fla.; Tantivy Systems Group Technologies, Inc. dba TSG Technologies, Melbourne, Fla.; Tech Global, Inc., Rockville, Md.; Technical Professional Services, Inc., Wayland, Mich.; Technique Solutions, Inc., Martinsville, Va.; Tellus Solutions, Inc., Santa Clara, Calif.; TENICA and Associates, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Threat Defense LLC dba Threat Defense, New Orleans, La.; Tidewater, Inc., Elkridge, Md.; Tilson Government Services, LLC, Portland, Maine; TIME Systems LLC, Washington, D.C.; TM3 Solutions, Woodbridge, Va.; TMCI - The McVey Co., Inc. dba TMCI, Fairfax, Va.; TMGE LLC, Remington, Va.; Tolliver Group Inc., Winter Park, Fla.; Tompkins Consulting LLC dba TC Defense, Arlington , Va.; Topologe, Burlington, Mass.; TOTE Services, Inc., Moorestown, N.J.; Trace Systems, Inc., McLean, Va.; Trey Software, La Jolla, Calif.; Trimech Services, LLC dba Trimech Services, Glen Allen, Va.; Triple Canopy, Inc., Reston, Va.; Trusted Federal Systems, Inc., Greenbelt, Md.; TSO Armor and Training, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; United Global Group Inc. dba United Global Group, Fredericksburg, Va.; Universal Marine Leasing, Inc. dba Universal Marine, Seaford, Va.; Universal Solutions International, Inc. dba USI, Newport News, Va.; Universal Strategy Group, Inc., Franklin, Tenn.; Unlimited Services Systems Management &amp; Consultants dba USSMC, Glen Allen, Va.; Valytics, LLC, Great Falls, Va.; Varen Technologies, Inc., Columbia, Md.; Varsant, Inc., Waldorf, Md.; Vasto Technologies, Inc., Fairfax Station, Va.; Vector Resources, Inc., Torrance, Calif.; Vectrona, LLC, Virginia Beach, Va.; Venatore LLC, Tampa, Fla.; Vesa Health &amp; Technology, San Antonio, Texas; Vion Corp., Herndon, Va.; Visual Soft, Inc., Vienna, Va.; VLS IT Consulting, Inc., Newark, Del.; VOR Technology, LLC, Columbia, Md.; VPC Solutions, Inc., Dunn Loring, Va.; vTech Solution Inc., Chantilly, Va.; VXD Systems, Inc., Morganville, N.J.; W4 Limited L.P., Fort Worth, Texas; Warrant Technologies LLC, Bloomington, Ind.; Webworld Technologies, Inc., Springfield, Va.; Wellington Federal, LLC, Dumfries, Va.; Westcarb Enterprises, Inc., Springfield, Mass.; Woodbury Technologies, Inc., Clearfield, Utah; WPI Services, LLC dba Worldwide PRCH Ingration Services , Juno Beach, Fla.; XOR Security, LLC, Fairfax, Va.; Xpect Solutions, Inc., Bristow, Va.; YADARI Enterprises, Fairfield, Calif.; Zephyr Media and Communications, Inc., Springfield, Va.; Zurka Interactive LLC, Vienna, Va.; Kongsberg Gallium Ltd, Kanata, Ontario; Haka Inc., Honolulu, Hawaii; Science Applications International, Corp. (SAIC), McLean, Va.; A. Harold and Associates, LLC dba AHA, Jacksonville, Fla.; A2Z, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; A-T Solutions, Fredericksburg, Va.; AAC Inc., Vienna, Va.; AAI Corp., Hunt Valley, Md.; AAMCORE Inc., Leesburg, Va.; Abbott On Call, Inc. dba AOC, Inc., Vienna, Va.; ABSG Consulting Inc., Arlington, Va.; Accenture Federal Services LLC, Arlington, Va.; Acquisition, Research and Logistics, Inc., Oxon Hill, Md.; ACTA, Inc., Torrance, Calif.; Adaptive Methods, Inc., Centreville, Va.; Addx Corp., Alexandria, Va.; Advanced Information Systems Group, Inc., Orlando, Fla.; Advanced Internet Marketing, Inc. dba GBS Group, Virginia Beach, Va.; Advanced Systems Technology and Management, Inc., Vienna, Va.; Advanced Systems Technology, Inc., Lawton, Okla.; Affordable Engineering Services LLC, Coronado, Calif.; Agile Defense, Inc. dba Webster Data Communication, Fairfax, Va.; ALEX-Alternative Experts, LLC, Chantilly, Va.; Alpha Solutions Corp., Virginia Beach, Va.; ALTRON, Inc., Mt. Pleasant, S.C.; AM Pierce &amp; Associates, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; Amee Bay LLC, Anchorage, Alaska; American Electronics, Inc., California, Md.; American Technical Services, Inc., Norco, Calif.; Amron Corp., McLean, Va.; Amyx, Inc., Reston, Va.; Analysis Modeling and Programming Sciences, Inc., Poway, Calif.; Analytic Solutions LLC, Virginia Beach, Va.; Anchor Innovation, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; Andromeda Systems Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; Antech Systems, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; AOC Global Services, LLC, Chantilly, Va.; Apextech, LLC., Arlington, Va.; Apogee Solutions, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; Applied Engineering Management Corp., Herndon, Va.; Applied Logistics Services, Inc., Odon, Ind.; Applied Management Corp. dba AM, Arlington, Va.; Applied Research Associates, Inc., Albuquerque, N.M.; Applied Technical Systems, Inc., Silverdale, Wash.; Applied Technology, Inc., King George, Va.; A-P-T Research, Inc. dba APT Research, Huntsville, Ala.; Arinbe Technologies, Inc., Falls Church, Va.; Artisan Electronics, Inc., Gosport, Ind.; ASM Research, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; AT&amp;T Government Solutions, Inc. dba AT&amp;T, Vienna, Va.; Alliant Techsystems Operations LLC dba  ATK Tactical Propulsion and Control, Rocket Center, W.Va.; Atkinson Aeronautics&amp; Technology, King Geroge, Va.; Atlantic CommTech Corp., Norfolk, Va.; Atlas Executive Consulting, LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; AUSGAR Technologies, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Ausley Associates, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; Automation Precision Technology, LLC dba A P T, Norfolk, Va.; Avaya Government Solutions, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; AVIAN Engineering, LLC, Lexington Park, Md.; Aviation Systems Engineering Co., Inc. dba ASEC, Lexington Park, Md.; Avineon, Inc., McLean, Va.; AVW Technologies Inc., Chesapeake, Va.;  BAI, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Battelle Memorial Institute, Columbus, Ohio; BGI, LLC, Akron, Ohio; BLS Consultants, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; Brandes Associates, Inc., Lone Tree, Colo.; Baum, Romstedt Technology Research Corp. dba BRTRC, Fairfax, Va.; BSC Systems, Inc., Chantilly, Va.; Burr Business Solutions, LLC, Enola, Pa.; CAE USA Inc., Tampa, Fla.; CALNET, Inc., Reston, Va.; Calvert Systems Engineering, Prince Frederick, Md.; Camber Corp., Huntsville, Ala.; Cameron Bell Corp. dba Gov Solutions Group, Daniel Island, S.C.; Capstone Corp., Alexandria, Va.; Cardno EM-Assist, Inc., Folsom, Calif.; Carley Corp., Orlando, Fla.; Carter-Lambert Divisions, LLC, Waldorf, Md.; Celeris Systems, Inc., Anaheim, Calif.; Centerscope Technologies Inc. dba CenterScope, Elkridge, Md.; Centurum Technical Solutions, Inc., Marlton, N.J.; CEXEC, Inc., Reston, Va.; CGI Federal, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; CGW Technologies, Inc., Great Mills, Md.; CJSeto Support Services, LLC, Ventura, Calif.; Client Solution Architects LLC, Mechanicsburg, Pa.; Client/Server Software Solutions, Inc. dba CSSS.NET, Bellevue, Neb.; Coalition Solutions Integrated Inc., California, Md.; CodeLynx, LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; Coherent Technical Services, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; COLE Technology Corp., Fort Worth, Texas; COLSA Corp., Huntsville, Ala.; Command Decisions Systems &amp; Solutions, Inc. dba CDS2, Stafford, Va.; CommIT Enterprises Inc., Hughesville, Md.; Compass Systems, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; Compliance Corp., Lexington Park, Md.; Concurrent Technologies Corp., Johnstown, Pa.; CORTEK, Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; Cruz Associates Inc., Yorktown, Va.; CSSI, Inc., Washington, D.C.; Culmen International, LLC, Alexandria, Va.; Cydecor, Inc., Arlington, Va.; D&amp;L Services, LLC, California, Md.; D&amp;S Consultants Inc. dba DSCI, Eatontown, N.J.; D3 Technologies, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Daniel H Wagner Associates, Inc., Exton, Pa.; DasNet Corp., Bohemia, N.Y.; Data Solutions &amp; Technology Inc., Lanham, Md.; DataSource, Inc., McLean, Va.; Davis Defense Group, Fredericksburg, Va.; Dawnbreaker, Inc., Rochester, N.Y.; Decision Technologies, Inc., Arlington, Va.; Decisive Analytics Corp., Arlington, Va.; Defense Holdings, Inc., Manassas Park, Va.; DEL REY Systems and Technology, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Diamond Data Systems, LLC, Metairie, La.; Diverse Technologies Corp., Upper Marlboro, Md.; DKW Communications, Inc., Washington, D.C.; Domenix Corp., Chantilly, Va.; DRPA Inc., Knoxville, Tenn.; Dyncorp International, LLC, Fort Worth, Texas; E. L. Hamm &amp; Associates, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; Eagle Systems, California, Md.; Eastern Research Group, Inc., Lexington, Mass.; ECS Federal, Inc. dba E C S, Fairfax, Va.; EHS Technologies Corp., Moorestown, N.J.; EMSolutions, Inc. dba EMSolutions, Arlington, Va.; EMW, INC., Herndon, Va.; Engineering Support Personnel Inc. dba ESP, Orlando, Fla.; Enterprise Information Services, Inc. dba ESI, Vienna, Va.; Enterprise Resource Performance, Inc. dba ERPI, Leesburg, Va.; EOIR Technologies, Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; E S H Group Inc., Alexandria, Va.; ESRG Government Services, LLC dba ESRG, Virginia Beach, Va.; Exceptional Software Strategies, Inc., Linthicum Heights, Md.; EXCET, INC., Springfield, Va.; Exelis, Inc., Herndon, Va.; Facchina Global Services, LLC, La Plata, Md.; Falconwood, Arlington, Va.; Flatter&amp; Associates, INC., Stafford, Va.; Forward Slope, San Diego, Calif.; Fulcrum Corp., Arlington, Va.; Fulcrum IT Services, LLC, Centreville, Va.; G2 Software Systems, San Diego, Calif.; Geographic Information Services, Inc. dba GIS, Birmingham, Ala.; Geologics Corp., Alexandria, Va.; George Consulting, Ltd., Daniel Island, S.C.; Georgia Tech Applied Research Corp., Atlanta, Ga.; Global Business Solutions, Inc. dba GBSI, Pensacola, Fla.; Global Services Corp., Fayetteville, N.C.; Global Systems Technologies dba GST, Yardley, Pa.; Global Technology and Management Resources, Inc. dba GTMR, Leonardtown, Md.; Goldbelt Hawk, LLC dba GBHAWK, Newport News, Va.; Gnostech, Inc., Warminster, Pa.; GPA Technologies, Inc., Ventura, Calif.; Greenfield Engineering Corp., Leonardtown, Md.; Greenpak Development, Inc., Parkersburg, W.Va.; Greystones Consulting Group LLC dba Greystones Group, Washington, D.C.; Grove Resource Solutions, Inc. dba GRSI, Frederick, Md.; GSTEK Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; Harlan Lee &amp; Associates, Vienna, Va.; Harmonia Holdings Group LLC, Blacksburg, Va.; Harry Kahn Associates, Inc., Hagerstown, Md.; HART Technologies Inc., Manassas, Va.; HDT Engineering Services, Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; HEBCO, INC., Oklahoma City, Okla.; Herdt Consulting, Inc. dba Herdt, Chelsea, Ala.; HI-TEST Laboratories, Inc., Arvonia, Va.; Holmes-Tucker International, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; Homeland Security Solutions, Inc., Hampton, Va.; Honeywell Technology Solutions dba Honeywell, Columbia, Md.; HP Enterprise Services, LLC, Herndon, Va.; Hughes Associates, Baltimore, Md.; I-Prise Communications, Inc., Oxnard, Calif. ; IBASET, Foothill Ranch, Calif.; II Corps Consultants, Inc. dba II Corps Consultants, Locust Grove, Va.; ICF Inc., L.L.C., Fairfax, Va.; Imagine One Technology and Management LTD, Colonial Beach, Va.; Information Planning Associates, Inc., Falls Church, Va.; Info Soft Systems Inc., Potomac, Md.; InfoReliance Corp., Fairfax, Va.; Information Management Resources, Aliso Viejo, Calif.; Information Research Corp., Bridgeport, W.Va.; InnovaSystems International LLC, San Diego, Calif.; Innovative Aviation Services, Inc., Woodbridge, Va.; Innovative Decisions, Inc., Vienna, Va.; Innovative Logistics Support Services Corp., New Orleans, La.; IMS-Chas, North Charleston, S.C.; Innovative Reasoning LLC, Orlando, Fla.; Integrated Consultants Inc. dba ICI Integrated Consultants, San Diego, Calif.; Integrated Systems Analyst dba ISA, Alexandria, Va.; INTEKRAS, Inc., Sterling, Va.; Intelligent Decision Systems Inc., Centreville, Va.; intelliSolutions, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Intergraph Government Solutions Corp. dba IGS, Madison, Ala.; International Business Machines Corp. dba IBM, Bethesda, Md.; International Systems Management Corp., Boyds, Md.; Interoptek, Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; ISPA Technology, Centreville, Va.; ITA International LLC, Yorktown, Va.; IZ Technologies, Inc., Sterling, Va.; J. M. Waller Associates, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; J.F. Taylor, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; J5 Systems, San Diego, Calif.; Jahn Corp., Lexington Park, Md.; Janus Research Group, Inc., Appling, Ga.; Jardon and Howard Technologies, Orlando, Fla.; JBR Resources, LLC, Carlisle, Pa.; JC3 Global, Inc., La Plata, Md.; Joint Research and Development, Inc., Stafford, Va.; Juno Technologies, Rancho Santa Fe, Calif.; KAEGAN Corp., Orlando, Fla.; Kalman and Co., Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; Kay and Associates, Inc., Buffalo Grove, Ill.; Ki Ho Military Acquisition Consulting, Inc. dba KIHOMAC, Fairfax, Va.; King Technologies, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Klett Consulting Group, Virginia Beach, Va.; KMS Solutions, LLC, Melbourne, Fla.; Knight Networking and Web Design, Inc. dba Knight Networking, Marlton, N.J.; Knowledge Engineers, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; KOAM Engineering Systems, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Kratos Defense &amp; Rocket Support Services, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Liberty Business Associates, LLC, North Charleston, S.C.; LinQuest Corp., Los Angeles, Calif.; Linxx Global Solutions, Inc., dba Linxx Security, Virginia Beach, Va.; Logistics Management Institute dba LMI, McLean, Va.; Logis-Tech, Inc., Manassas, Va.; Logistic Services International, Inc. dba LSI, Jacksonville, Fla.; Logistics Support Inc., Arlington, Va.; Long Wave Inc., Oklahoma City, Okla.; Loyola Enterprises Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; LTM Inc., Havelock, N.C.; M.C. Dean, Inc., Dulles, Va.; M2 Consulting Corp, San Diego, Calif.; MAC Consulting Services, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; MacAulay-Brown Inc., Dayton, Ohio; Main Sail, LLC, Cleveland, Ohio; Maintenance Inspection Services, Inc., Morganton, N.C.; Management &amp; Engineering Technologies International, Inc. dba METI, El Paso, Texas; Management Consulting Inc. dba MANCON, Virginia Beach, Va.; MANDEX Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Manufacturing Engineering System, Inc dba MES, Rockville, Md.; Manufacturing Techniques, Inc. dba M-TEQ, Kilmarnock, Va.; Marine Acoustics, MIddletown, R.I.; Maritime Applied Physics Corp., Baltimore, Md.; MARKON, Inc., Falls Church, Va.; Marlin Alliance Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Marshall Communications Corp., Ashburn, Va.; MCR Federal LLC, McLean, Va.; Merdan Group, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Metamorphosis Group Inc., Vienna, Va.; Metron Inc., Reston, Va.; Metson Marine Services, Inc., Ventura, Calif.; MI Technical Solutions, Chesapeake, Va.; MicroTechnologies, LLC dba Microtech, Vienna, Va.; Mid Atlantic Engineering Technical Services, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; Mikel, Fall River, Mass.; MIL Corp., Bowie, Md.; Millennium Corp., Arlington, Va.; Milli Micro Systems, Inc. dba Mms Tactical, Northridge, Calif.; MILVETS Systems Technology, Orlando, Fla.; Minerva Engineering, Mesa, Ariz.; Modern Technology Solutions, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Momentum Inc., Camp Hill, Pa.; MPR Associates, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; MTG Services, Inc., Lakehurst, N.J.; MTS Technologies, Arlington, Va.; Mutual Telecom Services Inc. dba Black Box Network Services, Needham, Mass.; MYMIC, Portsmouth, Va.; KSH Solutions Inc., San Antonio, Texas; Nakuuruq Solutions LLC, Herndon, Va.; Nathan Kunes, Inc., Coronado, Calif.; National Sourcing, Inc., Tampa, Fla.; Naval Systems, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; NCI Information Systems, Inc., Reston, Va.; Netzer Russell Consulting, LLC, Ridgecrest, Calif.; Next Wave Systems, LLC, Pekin, Ind.; Oak Grove Technologies LLC, Raleigh, N.C.; Object CTalk, King of Prussia, Pa.; Odyssey Systems Consulting Group LTD., Wakefield, Mass.; Oldenburg Group Inc. dba Oldenburg Lakeshore, Kingsford, MI; Omnitech Solutions, Inc., Bethesda, Md.; Opal Soft Inc., Sunnyvale, Calif.; Organizational Strategies Inc. dba OSI, Arlington, Va.; Overlook Systems Technologies, Inc., Vienna, Va.; P3I, Inc., Hopkinton, Mass.; PAL Services, O Fallon, Mo.; Parsons Government Services Inc., Pasadena, Calif.; Patrona Corp. dba Patrona, Arlington, Va.; PCCI Inc., Alexandria, Va.; PC Engineering, Inc., Panama City, Fla.; Penobscot Bay Media LLC dba Pen Bay Media, Rockland, Maine; Phacil. Inc., Arlington, Va.; Phoenix Group Of Virginia, Inc. dba PGV, Chesapeake, Va.; PAL Technologies Inc. dba Pal-Tech, Arlington, Va.; Potomac-Hudson Engineering Inc., Gaithersburg, Md.; Prairie Quest Consulting, Fort Wayne, Ind.; Precise Systems, Lexington Park, Md.; Predicate Logic, San Diego, Calif.; Preferred Systems Solutions, Vienna, Va.; Prism Maritime LLC, Chesapeake, Va.; Professional Solutions1, LLC dba Professional Solutions, Alexandria, Va.; Professional Systems Associates, Inc., Panama City, Fla.; Progeny Systems, Manassas, Va.; Programs Management Analytics &amp; Technologies, Inc. dba PMAT, Norfolk, Va.; Prometheus Co., Lexington Park, Md.; PSI PAX INC., California, Md.; Puritan Research Corp., Vienna, Va.; Quadelta, Arlington, Va.; Quantum Professional Services, San Diego, Calif.; R &amp; D Training and Technical Services, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; R&amp;K Solutions, Inc., Roanoke, Va.; Radiance Technologies, Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; Research Analysis and Engineering, LLC, Arlington, Va.; RAM Laboratories, San Diego, Calif.; RBC, Alexandria, Va.; Regis &amp; Associates, PC, Washington, D.C.; Reliability &amp; Performance Technologies LLC dba RP Technologies, Dublin, Pa.; Reliable Government Solutions Inc., Beltsville, Md.; Renaissance Sciences Corp., Chandler, Ariz.; Rentfrow Inc., Ventura, Calif.; Research and Engineering Development, LLC, Lexington Park, Md.; RGS Associates, Arlington, Va.; RNB Technologies, Inc., Stafford, Va.; ROH Inc., Arlington, Va.; Rohrbach Group, Inc., Poway, Calif.; ROI Consulting LLC, Mullica Hill, N.J.; Rollout Systems, LLC, California, Md.; S4 Inc., Burlington, Mass.; Saalex Corp dba Saalex Solutions, Camarillo, Calif.; Sabre Systems, Inc., Warrington, Pa.; SAM Inc., College Park, Md.; San Diego Community College District dba San Diego City College, San Diego, Calif.; Savvee Consulting, Inc., Chantilly, Va.; Sayres and Associates, Washington, D.C.; SBG Technology Solutions, Stafford, Va.; Schafer Corp. dba WJ Shafer and Associates, Chelmsford, Mass.; SDS International Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; Secure Mission Solutions, LLC. Dba SMS, N. Charleston, S.C.; Sentek Consulting Inc. dba Sentek Global, San Diego, Calif.; Serrano IT Services, Omaha, Neb.; ShadowObjects LLC, Leonardtown, Md.; Sierra Management and Technologies, Inc., California, Md.; Silver Bullet Solutions Inc., Arlington, Va.; Simulation Systems Technologies, Inc. dba SSTI, Voohees, N.J.; SITE, LLC dba Systems Intgrtion Tech Evltion, Arlington, Va.; Smartronix, Inc., Hollywood, Md.; Solution Engineering Associates, Inc. dba SEAI, Lexington Park, Md.; Sotera Defense Solutions Inc., Herndon, Va.; Sound &amp; Sea Technology, Inc. dba Sound &amp; Sea Technology, Lynnwood, Wash.; Southwest Research Institute dba SWRI, San Antonio, Texas; Spalding Consulting, Inc., Lexington Park, Md.; Spatial Integrated Systems Inc. dba SIS, Virginia Beach, Va.; Specialty Systems, Toms River, N.J.; Spectrum Technology Group, Inc., Gaithersburg, Md.; SRI International, Menlo Park, Calif.; Standard Calibrations, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; Stargates Inc., Arlington, Va.; STG Inc., Reston, Va.; STIMULUS Engineering Services, Inc., Loogootee, Ind.; Strategic Analysis, Inc., Arlington, Va.; Strategic Data Systems dba SDS, San Diego, Calif.; Strategic Technology Institute Inc. dba STI, Rockville, Md.; Stratom Inc., Boulder, Colo.; Subsidium, Inc., Luray, Va.; Summit Technical Solutions, LLC, Colorado Springs, Colo.; Sunset Design &amp; Programming Inc. dba Sunset Design, Oxnard, Calif.; Support Systems Associates, Inc., Melbourne, Fla.; Survice Engineering Co., Belcamp, Md.; Symvionics Inc., Arcadia, Calif.; Synergy Software Design, LLC, Washington, D.C.; Systems Documentation, Inc., Piscataway, N.J.; Systems Engineering &amp; Management Co. dba SEMCO, Vista, Calif.; Systems Engineering Support  dba SESCO, San Diego, Calif.; Systems Planning and Analysis, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Systems Plus, Inc., Rockville, Md.; SRA International Inc. dba SRA, Fairfax, Va.; Sysytems Technology Forum, Limited, Fredericksburg, Va.; Tactical Engineering &amp; Analysis, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Target Media Mid Atlantic Inc. dba Target Systems, Mechanicsburg, Pa.; Technical Software Services, Inc.. dba TECHSOFT, Pensacola, Fla.; Tech Wizards, Inc., Newburg, Md.; Technical and Project Engineering, LLC dba TAPE, Alexandria, Va.; Technology and Management International, LLC dba TAMI, Toms River, N.J.; Technology Associates International Corp. dba TAIC, Carlsbad, Calif.; Technology Security Associates Inc., California, Md.; Technomics, Arlington, Va.; Tekla Research Inc., Dumfries, Va.; Teleconsultants Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; TELESIS Corp., Beltsville, Md.; Tetra Tech EMC, Inc. dba Tetra Tech EMC, Camarillo, Calif.; Thornberry Consulting, LLC, Mount Airy, Md.; TIE Today, Inc., Oviedo, Fla.; Technology Program Services Associates, Inc., Whiting, N.J.; Transformation Systems Inc., Arlington, Va.; TRANSTECS Corp., Wichita, Kan.; Tri-Force Consulting Services Inc., Lansdale, Pa.; Triton Services, Inc., Annapolis, Md.; Triumph Enterprises, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Trofholz Technologies, Inc., Rocklin, Calif.; Truston Technologies, Inc., Broussard, La.; T-Solutions, Inc., Chesapeake, Va.; Turner Strategic Technologies, LLC, Norfolk, Va.; TWM Associates, Inc., Falls Church, Va.; Unconventional Concepts, Inc., Mary Esther, Fla.; Unified Industries Inc., Springfield, Va.; Unisys Corp. dba Federal Systems, Reston, Va.; Universal Consulting Services, Inc., Fairfax, Va.; Universal Technical Resource Services, Inc. dba UTRS, Cherry Hill, N.J.; Valkyrie Enterprises, LLC, Virginia Beach, Va.; Vaughn Management &amp; Services, Inc., Camarillo, Calif.; VectorCSP, LLC, Elizabeth City, N.C.; Veteran Enterprise Technology Services, LLC dba VETS, Vienna, Va.; Vision Point Systems, Inc., Blacksburg, Va.; Visual Concepts LLC, Ventura, Calif.; Vox Optima, LLC, Albuquerque, N.M.; VT AEPCO Inc., Alpharetta, Ga.; W R Systems, Ltd., Fairfax, Va.; Washington Technology Group, Inc., Silver Spring, Md.; Web Business Solutions Inc., Fredericksburg, Va.; Whitney, Bradley &amp; Brown Inc., Reston, Va.; WGS Systems LLC, Frederick, Md.; Wyle Laboratories, Inc., Huntsville, Ala.; X-Feds, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Zekiah Technologies, Inc., La Plata, Md.; Zimmerman Associates, Inc. dba ZAI, Fairfax, Va.; Accelerated Development &amp; Support Corp. dba ADS, Arlington, Va.; Applied Computing Technologies, Inc., Alexandria, Va.; Artemis Consulting, LLC, San Diego, Calif.; BTP Systems, LLC, Ludlow, Mass.; Caelum Research Corp., Rockville, Md.; Cape Henry Associates, Inc., Virginia Beach, Va.; Collins Consulting, Inc., Schaumburg, Ill.; Craig Technical Consulting, Inc. dba Craig Technologies, Cape Canaveral, Fla.; Dynamic Analytics and Test, LLC, Arlington, Va.; GCC Technologies, LLC, Oakland, Md.; Global Defense, Inc. dba GDI, Arlington, Va.; J3S, Inc., Georgetown, Texas; KPMG LLP, McLean, Va.; Kros-Wise, San Diego, Calif.; Marine Systems Corp., Boston, Mass.; Monroe Defense Industry Consulting, Inc., Colonial Beach, Va.; Natural SPI Inc., Tucson, Ariz.; Navmar Applied Sciences Corp., Warminster, Pa.; NS Software Services Inc. dba Stiltmart Learning Management Services, Pensacola, Fla.; Ohm Systems, Inc., Horsham, Pa.; Orqid Consulting &amp; Associates, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Pacific Science &amp; Engineering Group, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Quality Innovative Solutions, Inc. dba QI-Solutions, QISI, Oxnard, Calif.; Referentia Systems Inc., Honolulu, Hawaii; S &amp; K Technologies, Inc., Saint Ignatius, Mont.; Sedna Digital Solutions, LLC, Manassas, Va.; Softcomm Inc. dba Softcomm, San Diego, Calif.; Solers, Inc., Arlington, Va.; SOLUTE dba SOLUTE Consulting, San Diego, Calif.; STS International, Inc., Berkeley Springs, W.Va.; System Planning Corp., Arlington, Va.; Systems Technologies, Inc., West Long Branch, N.J.; TechFlow, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Tecolote Research, Inc., Goleta, Calif.; Tek Source USA, Inc., Tampa, Fla.; Wakelight Technologies, Inc., Honolulu, Hawaii; Analysis Group, LLC, Falls Church, Va.; Salient Federal-SGIS, Inc. dba SGIS, San Diego, Calif.; Vector Planning and Services, Inc., San Diego, Calif.; Investment Management Enterprise Inc., Richmond, Va.; iO Technologies, Inc., Dahlgren, Va.; Electromagnetic Compatibility Management Concepts dba EMC Management Concepts, Sterling, Va.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
