<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Weight, Power Issues Vex U.S. Pacific Force Communications</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>December 3, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Asia-Pacific</tag>
    <tag>Battlespace Information Systems</tag>
    <tag>Networks</tag>
    <tag>PACOM</tag>
    <tag>TechNet Asia-Pacific 2013 Coverage</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>An increasing number of missions combined with more diverse settings offer a major challenge to establishing needed communications throughout the Asia-Pacific region. U.S. forces cannot count on having necessary communications links in place with they respond to a new mission, noted a panel of military officers.</abstract>
  <text>An increasing number of missions combined with more diverse settings offer a major challenge to establishing needed communications throughout the Asia-Pacific region. U.S. forces cannot count on having necessary communications links in place with they respond to a new mission, noted a panel of military officers.
	At TechNet Asia-Pacific 2013 in Honolulu, Hawaii, a panel featuring the U.S. Pacific Command’s -6s focused on some of those needs. Col. James Dillon, USMC, assistant chief of staff for G-6, Marine Forces Pacific, noted that most U.S. armed forces have become comfortable falling into forward operating bases with big pipes. While Marines often enter a theater and set up their links, the typhoon relief effort known as Operation Damayan illustrated that the Marines could have used a lightweight communications system that does not require a lot of lift or power.
	“We want a system that provides the same level of communications, data storage and information exchange in a bandwidth challenged environment,” the colonel declared.
	He also called for embedding ways of conserving bandwidth so that forces need not use appliqués for that task. Transmission systems should have built-in bandwidth compression, he offered.
	Capt. Sandra Schiavo, USN, deputy director, N-6, U.S. Pacific Fleet, cited the need for network situational awareness—“our own cyber cop. It seems we’ve been working on that for a long time,” she observed. Col. Michael Finn II, USAF, director of communications and chief information officer, headquarters, U.S. Pacific Air Forces, reiterated an oft-stated point that a communications system must be able to establish a network with coalition partners who can dial in.
	 
 
 
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
