<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Bilateral Network Leads to Coalition Connectivity</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>December 4, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
    <department>International</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Asia-Pacific</tag>
    <tag>Networks</tag>
    <tag>PACOM</tag>
    <tag>TechNet Asia-Pacific 2013 Coverage</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>An evolving mission network connecting U.S. and Australian forces is being expanded to include other trusted allies with an eye toward adding coalition partner nations. The network is built around a risk-managed approach for sensitive information sharing.</abstract>
  <text>An evolving mission network connecting U.S. and Australian forces is being expanded to include other trusted allies with an eye toward adding coalition partner nations. The network is built around a risk-managed approach for sensitive information sharing.
	Known as Pegasus, the network expands on the two nations’ Improved Connectivity Initiative (ICI). Maj. Gen. Mike J. Milford, Australia Military, chief technology officer, Chief Information Officer Group of the Australian Department of Defence, outlined details of the network to the Wednesday breakfast audience at TechNet Asia-Pacific 2013 in Honolulu, Hawaii.
	Describing Pegasus as “the main game” for network connectivity between the two militaries, Gen. Milford explained that it is Australia’s coalition network of choice. Its nation-to-nation capabilities are the way forward for sensitive information sharing among the Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations of Australia, Canada, New Zealand, the United Kingdom and the United States.
	One advantage of Pegasus is a characteristic of shared networks—the ability to reduce the amount of hardware for networks, Gen. Milford offered. In particular, Pegasus provides a reusable set of tools that can be deployed from the desktop instead of building networks for specific activities</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
