<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>U.S. Pacific Fleet Seeks Partnership With Industry</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>December 5, 2013</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Acquisition</tag>
    <tag>Asia-Pacific</tag>
    <tag>Navy Technologies</tag>
    <tag>PACOM</tag>
    <tag>TechNet Asia-Pacific 2013 Coverage</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Partnering with industry is not a new concept for the military. However, with funding limits plunging, the commander of the U.S. Pacific Fleet has extended an invitation to industry to come up with ways of giving the Navy what it needs in economic ways.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Pacific Fleet is feeling the pain of budget cuts, and its commander is looking toward industry to provide it with necessary capabilities under tight budgetary conditions. Adm. Harry B. Harris Jr., USN, commander of the U.S. Pacific Fleet, described the approaches he wants industry to take along with the fleet’s requirements on the final day of TechNet Asia-Pacific 2013 in Honolulu, Hawaii.
	“We’re looking to our partners in industry to develop the new technologies and capabilities we need,” Adm. Harris declared. “And, we have do it in a fiscally constrained environment.”
	The admiral explained that the Navy cannot afford to invest in single mission systems and platforms. That now is a luxury that cannot be afforded, so industry must provide systems and platforms that can accommodate several missions.
	The fleet also needs robust cybersecurity for systems in all security domains. And, it must be able to conduct cross-domain chat between individuals in coalition operations.
	“We evolve and adapt better than anyone in the world,” the admiral maintained. “Our strength comes from leaders in industry who are well aware of the challenges we face around the world, and the men and women who wear the uniform,” he declared.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
