<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Boeing Awarded $750 Million B-1 Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 6, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Boeing</tag>
    <tag>B-1</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Boeing Co., Oklahoma City, Okla., has been awarded a firm-fixed-price, cost-plus-fixed-fee, cost-plus-incentive-fee, time and material, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract (FA8107-14-D-0002), including the base period and four one-year option periods with an estimated ceiling value of $750 million. Contractor will provide integrated engineering services for the B-1 weapon system to include detailed design engineering, maintenance engineering and systems (structure/flight systems, avionics, software and weapons delivery) engineering support, computer network support, technical analysis, drawing and source data maintenance/updates, flight safety analyses, reliability/maintainability analysis, test support, program analysis, cost estimation, schedule development, government furnished property and government furnished material maintenance, accident investigation, engineering feasibility studies, material deficiency report analysis, field problem investigation, and in-flight emergency response support, logistic system design support, evaluation of new capabilities and development of operational guidelines for fleet repairs and for users to employ. Additional requirements include integration management, configuration management, acquisition/sustainment, weapon system enhancement, weapon system development efforts, production, integration management, configuration management, acquisition/sustainment logistics elements, sustaining engineering, studies and analysis, initial spares (investment and expense), provisioning, technical data, support for training due to system upgrades (tech data, source code, etc.), support equipment, technical support and technical order maintenance. Air Force Life Cycle Management Center, Tinker Air Force Base, Okla., is the contracting activity (FA8107-14-D-0002).
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
