<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DARPA Announces Eight Robotics Challenge Trials Winners</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>January 7, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>research and development</tag>
    <tag>Robotics</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) selected eight teams eligible to receive up to $1 million to continue their work following the conclusion of the agency’s Robotics Challenge trials. The robots performed a series of eight simple tasks, such as walking a short distance or cutting a hole in a wall, at the Homestead-Miami Speedway, Homestead, Florida.</abstract>
  <text>The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) selected eight teams eligible to receive up to $1 million to continue their work following the conclusion of the agency’s Robotics Challenge trials. These top teams will now prepare for the finals, which will occur at some point in the next 12-18 months. The robots performed a series of eight simple tasks, such as walking a short distance or cutting a hole in a wall, at the Homestead-Miami Speedway, Homestead, Florida. DARPA designed the tasks to simulate what a future robot might have to do to safely enter and effectively work inside a disaster zone. The tasks tested autonomous perception, autonomous decision-making, mounted and dismounted mobility, dexterity and strength.
	The scores, out of a total of 32 points, were:

		27 points: SCHAFT (SCHAFT Inc., Tokyo)

		20 points: IHMC Robotics (Florida Institute for Human and Machine Cognition, Pensacola, Florida)

		18 points: Tartan Rescue (Carnegie Mellon University, National Robotics Engineering Center, Pittsburgh)

		16 points: Team MIT (Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Boston)

		14 points: RoboSimian (NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory (JPL), Los Angeles)

		11 points: Team TRACLabs (TRACLabs Inc., Webster, Texas)

		11 points: WPI Robotics Engineering C-Squad (Worcester Polytechnic Institute, Worcester, Massachusetts)

		9 points: Team Trooper (Lockheed Martin Advanced Technology Laboratories, Cherry Hill, New Jersey)

	Check out the "DARPA Robotics Challenge Trials Day Two Wrap" video for a closer look:
</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img></img>
    <img></img>
    <img></img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
