<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Sponsored Products</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 15, 2014</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Sponsored Products</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>
	 

	SMi
The 7th annual conference on...
	Mobile Deployable Communications
	6 - 7 February 2014 | Mövenpick City Centre Hotel, Amsterdam
	Sponsored by: Cisco Systems, Harris CapRock, iOra Software, RUAG Schweiz AGwww.mobiledeployable.comJoin US Army, Cisco, Austrian MoD and DE&amp;S at Mobile Deployable Communications conference
	Organised by SMi Group, taking place on the 6th and 7th February 2014, Amsterdam
	Mobile Deployable Communications conference returns for the 7th annual event to bring together key military officials and industry experts to discuss the latest developments and challenges facing the mobile deployable communications industry.
	Key topics to be addressed include a recent update on UK Land Environment Tactical CIS, working towards a global mobile communications system, network centric warfare and examine case studies such as the withdrawal from Afghanistan.
	SMi are delighted to announce Cisco has joined the speaker line-up on day 2 of the conference. Do not miss the chance to hear their presentation on: Transforming Military Mobile Deployed Communications. The presentation will be led by David Lawford Mee, Business Development Manager, Defence - Europe, Middle East, Africa &amp; Russia and Edwin Tromp, Vertical Solutions Architect both from Cisco Systems. Click here for an event update.
	If you would like to find out more on speaking or showcasing a product at the event, please contact Sadia Malick via smalick@smi-online.co.uk or visit the website for more information.Speaker presentation highlights include:
	Michael McCarthy, Director of Operations and Program Manager, US Army
	Breaking the Paradigms: The US Army Mobility Project

		CSDA is changing how soldiers access knowledge, training, data across the Training, Admin and Operational Domains
	
		The Army continues to lead the efforts to bring mobile computing technologies to the soldier at the leading edge of the battlefield.
	
		The Army continues to share Insights and Lessons Learned from the CSDA project across DoD and Agencies and Departments of the Government
Senior representative, BOWMAN and tactical Communication &amp; Information Systems, DE&amp;S
	The future of UK Land Environment Tactical CIS

		The Current state of the UK Tactical CIS in the Land Environment
	
		The short term future of the current solution
	
		The future challenge facing the UKs tactical CIS
	
		The possible future solutions to meeting the demand
Resilient Voice Services for the Tactical Internet
	Robin Edgar Hansen, Team Leader SW design, RUAG

		What is the Tactical Internet and why services need to be resilient and de-centralized
	
		What challenges is a VoIP telephony solution faced with in such environments
	
		Why existing enterprise VoIP solutions are not designed for the Tactical Internet
	
		How RUAG Tactical Telephony TTEL solves the challenges
Click here to download the conference brochure and view the full speaker line-up
	If you would like to register please visit www.mobiledeployable.com
	Alternatively contact James Hitchen on +44(0) 207 827 6054 or email jhitchen@smi-online.co.uk to get more information about the event.
	 

	ViaSat
Secure Mobile Device Technology Delivered to U.S. Marine CorpsTrusted hand-held commercial devices available now for network pilots or trialsCarlsbad, Calif.  – In Fall 2013 the U.S. Marine Corps Systems Command took delivery of off-the-shelf mobile devices with advanced information security engineered by ViaSat Inc. (NASDAQ: VSAT). The USMC is now evaluating this first production delivery of 150 protected mobile devices on a beta service network. This new secure mobile system will be available on any Android device and multiple carriers for pilots.
While this development is for government unclassified and classified use, the ViaSat system is based entirely on commercial technology and is designed to provide secure communication of sensitive information for any government or commercial customer. The technology creates a virtual secure environment on standard android devices, enabling a highly trusted platform for secure enterprise extension to the mobile network.
“We’ve delivered this secure virtualization in a standard android device to enable a highly-trusted platform for the mobile enterprise,” said Jon Korecki, executive director of Secure Network Systems at ViaSat. “Now we’re at work on integrating these protected commercial devices into a variety of carrier networks and managed services.”
ViaSat cyber and information security for commercial off-the-shelf (COTS) smartphones and tablets adds three key protection benefits:

		Secure communications over 3G/4G/LTE cellular and Wi-Fi networks.
	
		Secure storage of sensitive data.
	
		Protection against malware attacks.

	SES Government Solutions

In SES Government Solutions, SES has combined three decades of Americom’s USG experience with the global capabilities and assets of the SES satellite fleet. The result is a new organization, formed in April 2010, created solely to provide bandwidth and hosted payload opportunities to U.S. Government, Intelligence and Civilian agencies.
SES Government Solutions continues Americom’s corporate record of serving the U.S. Government SATCOM market since 1973. As the only operating company within the SES family focused on USG, we back every Government mission with a long-standing record of technical achievement, operational excellence and service commitment.
Bandwidth &amp; Capacity
As part of the premier global satellite operator of satellites, SES Government Solutions expands the communications capabilities of U.S. Government and military missions – no matter where they are.

		Over 50 GEO satellites with an industry leading 99.999% network availability
	
		Broadband service for global, high-quality, secure access
	
		Large fleet capacity for managing new requirements and coverage areas
	
		Highly reliable and secure links
	
		Full or partial transponders
	
		Long term, short term and occasional use
	
		Portability
	
		Multiple protection levels
	
		Opportunities to engage in fleet development and investment process to ensure capacity is available when and where it is needed for future Government missions
Contact Us:
We’re ready to help you in every way we can.
SES Government Solutions Headquarters?
	2010 Corporate Ridge, Suite 550
	?McLean, VA 22102 U.S.A.
www.ses-gs.com
Call: 703-610-1000?
	Fax: 703-610-1030?
	Email: info@ses-gs.com
Send a meeting request by filling out your information here.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
