<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Army Awards $21 Billion for Alternative Energies</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 21, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Army</tag>
    <tag>renewable energy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Ameresco Inc. (W912DY-14-D-0036), Framingham, Mass., and Wheelabrator Technologies Inc. (W912DY-14-D-0041), Hampden, N.H., were awarded a maximum $7,000,000,000 firm-fixed-price, multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for biomass technology. In addition, Ameresco (W912DY-14-D-0031); M. Arthur Gensler, Jr. and Assoc., (W912DY-14-D-0032), Dallas, Texas; and Infigen Energy US Development LLC (W912DY-14-D-0033), Dallas, Texas were awarded a maximum $7,000,000,000 firm-fixed-price, multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for wind technology. And Ameresco (W912DY-14-D-0016); Chevron Energy Solutions Co. (W912DY-14-D-0017), San Francisco, Calif.; Constellation NewEnergy Inc. (W912DY-14-D-0018), Baltimore, Md.; Distributed Sun LLC (W912DY-14-D-0019) Washington, D.C.; Energy Ventures LLC (W912DY-14-D-0020), Rockville, Md.; First Solar Development Inc. (W912DY-14-D-0021) San Francisco, Calif.; FLS Energy (W912DY-14-D-0022), Asheville, N.C.; Linc Government Services, LLC (W912DY-14-D-0023), Hopkinsville, Ky.; RE Independence Co. LLC (W912DY-14-D-0024) San Francisco, Calif.; Sun Edison Government Solutions LLC (W912DY-14-D-0025), Beltsville, Md.; Sun Edison LLC (W912DY-14-D-0026), Beltsville, Md.; SunWize Technologies Inc. (W912DY-14-D-0027), San Jose, Cal.; TransGen Energy Inc. W912DY-14-D-0028) Rockville, Md.; Victory Renewables LLC: W912DY-14-D-0029), Juno Beach, Fla.; and EDF Renewable Energy (W912DY-14-D-0030), San Diego, Calif., were awarded a maximum $7,000,000,000 firm-fixed-price, multiple-award, indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract for solar technology. Army Corps of Engineers, Huntsville, Ala. is the contracting activity on all awards. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
