<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>The Internet Is Shrinking While Giving Birth </title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>March 17, 2014</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>The Bottom Line</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The bottom line is that the Internet today is more like the Wild West than the researchers who gave birth to it envisioned, but its inherent dangers have inspired techno-creativity to an extent that they also could not have anticipated. That’s probably something the bad guys also never predicted.</abstract>
  <text>In 1966, when the Advanced Research Projects Agency hosted the precursor to today’s Internet, the scientists and engineers at academic institutions could not have foreseen the impact their work would have around the globe. For the digital natives out there, yes, there was a time when finding the definition of a word meant hauling out a huge dictionary, and the words “I wonder…” weren’t followed by pulling out a cellphone to find the answer online.
	In the nearly five decades since several universities participated in the Resource Sharing Computer Networks program, access to the Internet has become faster, more diverse and nearly indispensable. Just ask anyone who’s waiting an entire minute for a file to download or unable to connect while away from the office … or home for that matter.
	The military quickly recognized the power of networking and began taking advantage of it. But with expansion came more opportunities for unsavory characters to use this tool for criminal acts. Whether stealing someone’s identity, breaking into online bank systems or simply defacing a website, it didn’t take long for individuals as well as nation states to figure out that the capability to access information easily could be used as a weapon.
	It also didn’t take long for new words and definitions to be added to everyone’s dictionaries: firewall, password, computer virus, malware, Trojan horse and worm were just a few. Almost at the speed of light, the term cybersecurity became as hot as those first fast computers did in mere minutes.
	The result? Today, the Internet is shrinking. No longer just an easy way to send or receive information quickly, the Internet has mutated as cybersecurity issues caused many organizations to prevent their employees from accessing certain websites. Email recipients double check with senders—even if they’ve been friends for dozens of years—to ensure that a message is indeed from them and an attachment is safe to open. Information theft is running so rampant that the well-publicized Target incident during the 2013 holiday season recently led to the resignation of Chief Information Officer Beth Jacob..
	But the illicit activity that has raised restrictions on Internet activity has given birth to another phenomenon that those original researchers could have never predicted: baby networks for specific groups. One example is milSuite.com, which is larger than an intranet, smaller than the World Wide Web and caters to a distinct audience, the military. With the requirement to sign in with credentials, it enables service members to access information and discussions that fall into the “for their eyes-only” category. While no network can ever be 100 percent secure, milSuite is one example of how people who need the ability to network do not let cybermonsters get in their way.
	The bottom line is that the Internet today is more like the Wild West than the researchers who gave birth to it envisioned, but its inherent dangers have inspired techno-creativity to an extent that they also could not have anticipated. That’s probably something the bad guys also never predicted.In your experience, how has the Internet changed since you began using it? Share your answer in the comments section or email mlawlor@afcea.org.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
