<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Air Force Awards Potential $5.7 Billion under NETCENTS-2 Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 28, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>NETCENTS-2</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Centech Group Inc., Falls Church, Va.,( FA8732-14-D-0010); Epsilon Systems Solutions Inc., San Diego, Calif., (FA8732-14-D-0011); Smartronix Inc., Hollywood, Md., (FA8732-14-D-0012); SMS Data Products Group Inc., McLean, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0013); Indus Corp., Vienna, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0014); Technica Corp., Sterling, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0015); Telos Corp., Ashburn, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0016); Sumaria Systems Inc., Danvers, Mass., (FA8732-14-D-0017); BTAS Inc., Beavercreek, Ohio, (FA8732-14-D-0018); American Systems Corp., Chantilly, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0019); STG, Inc., Reston, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0020) and MicroTechnologies LLC, Vienna, Va., (FA8732-14-D-0021) have been awarded a maximum $5,790,000,000 multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity (ID/IQ) contract for Network-Centric Solutions-2 (NETCENTS-2) network operations and infrastructure solutions. This contract vehicle will provide solutions to support network operations, core enterprise services and infrastructure development and operations, includes network management/defense, services oriented architecture infrastructure, enterprise level security/management and implementation/operations, telephony infrastructure and services. This contract vehicle is the mandatory source for all Air Force units purchasing services that fall under the scope of the contract, and it is available for use by Army, Navy, other department of defense and federal agencies. The contracting activity is Air Force Life Cycle Management Center, Maxwell Air Force Base-Gunter Annex, Ala.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
