<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>STEM Students' Innovations Impress Army</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>April 8, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>U.S. Army leaders of the Brigade Modernization Command (BMC) at Fort Bliss, Texas, supported middle and high school students vying for top spots in the fields of science and technology during a recent competition. Brig. Gen. John W. Charlton, USA, commanding general of the BMC, lent support by providing soldiers from his command to help judge the first 5-STAR Innovation Cup science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) competition.</abstract>
  <text>U.S. Army leaders of the Brigade Modernization Command (BMC) at Fort Bliss, Texas, supported middle and high school students vying for top spots in the fields of science and technology during a recent competition. Brig. Gen. John W. Charlton, USA, commanding general of the BMC, lent support by providing soldiers from his command to help judge the first 5-STAR Innovation Cup science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) competition.
	The challenge took place late March, and organizers hope it might become an annual event. The competition gives students a chance to design, build and present products to tackle issues in the STEM fields.
	“We’re surrounded by technology every day, so we’re really happy to be co-sponsors of this science, technology, engineering and math effort,” Gen. Charlton says. “This event is going to showcase some of the best minds in the middle and high schools across the El Paso community. So we’re real excited about that.
	“[These] … students brought some of their equipment to see how it compares to ours,” Gen. Charlton says. “I’m pretty impressed.”
	The BMC analyzes new technologies and provides improved capabilities to soldiers.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img></img>
    <img></img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
