<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Air Force Awards $900 Million for Technical Area Tasks</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 16, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>WMD</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Va. (FA8075-14-D-0002); Battelle Memorial Institute, Columbus, Ohio (FA8075-14-D-0003); Jacobs Technology Inc., Tullahoma, Tenn. (FA8075-14-D-0004); MacAulay-Brown Inc., Dayton, Ohio (FA8075-14-D-0005); MRI Global, Kansas City, Mo. (FA8075-14-D-0006); National Security Information Associates, Chantilly, Va. (FA8075-14-D-0007); Strategic Analysis Inc., Arlington, Va. (FA8075-14-D-0008); Leidos Inc., Reston, Va. (FA8075-14-D-0009); Scitor Corp., Colorado Springs, Colo. (FA8075-14-D-0010); TASC Inc., Andover, Md. (FA8014-14-D-0011); URS Federal Services Inc., Germantown, Md. (FA8075-14-D-0012); and Wyle Laboratories Inc., Houston, Texas (FA8075-14-D-0013) have been awarded a maximum $900 million cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price, multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for homeland defense and decurity technical area tasks (HD TATs). The HD TATs multiple-award IDIQ contracts will provide research, development, test and evaluation, and advisory and assistance services related to research and development efforts for TATs within the chemical, biological, radiological and nuclear defense, homeland defense and security, critical infrastructure protection, weapons of mass destruction, biometrics, medical, cultural studies and alternative energy focus areas. Individual task orders, obligating fiscal 2014 research and development funds, will be issued against the basic contracts, in order to meet the minimum order guarantee. The Air Force Installation Contracting Agency, Offutt Air Force Base, Neb., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
