<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Basic Research Receives Funding Boost</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>April 17, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>research and development</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Defense Department will award $167 million in research funding to academic institutions as part of the department’s Multidisciplinary University Research Initiative (MURI). During the next five years, 24 awards will be issued through the program to support multidisciplinary basic research, which will be conducted by teams of investigators that intersect more than one traditional science and engineering discipline.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Defense Department will award $167 million in research funding to academic institutions as part of the department’s Multidisciplinary University Research Initiative (MURI). During the next five years, 24 awards will be issued through the program to support multidisciplinary basic research, which will be conducted by teams of investigators that intersect more than one traditional science and engineering discipline. More than 60 academic institutions are expected to participate in the 24 research efforts.
	The Army Research Office, the Air Force Office of Scientific Research and the Office of Naval Research received more than 360 white papers in response to a solicitation for proposals in 24 research areas that are important to the Defense Department and the military services. The final award winners were selected based on a merit review by a panel of experts and are subject to successful negotiation between the institution and the department.
	Examples of technologies advanced through the MURI program include laser frequency combs and atomic and molecular self-assembly projects that complement nanomanufacturing. The list of projects selected for fiscal 2014 funding is available online.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
