<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Evaluates Color-Coded Explosive Detection Kits</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>May 9, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Acquisition</tag>
    <tag>IED</tag>
    <tag>Law Enforcement Technologies</tag>
    <tag>Navy Technologies</tag>
    <tag>research and development</tag>
    <tag>sensors</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Navy has evaluated color-coded chemical detection technology known as colorimetric explosive detection kits, the service recently announced.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Navy has evaluated color-coded chemical detection technology known as colorimetric explosive detection kits, the service recently announced. Colorimetric detection technology is based upon a series of chemical reactions that produce a visual response, most often in the form of a color change dependent upon the molecular structure of the compounds being tested. 
	The main goal of the weeklong evaluation was to collect data on performance, usability, type of users and type of mission suitable for the kits. The event included a variety of military explosive ordnance detection technicians, entry control point personnel, forensic specialists and law enforcement personnel who could potentially use the kits in the field. The group included representatives from the Transportation Security Administration, FBI, Department of Homeland Security, the U.S. Marshals and all four military services. The six companies providing demonstration products were ChemSpectra, DetectaChem, Field Forensics, Lindon Defense, Mistral Security and Morphix Technologies.
	The Naval Surface Warfare Center Indian Head Explosive Ordnance Disposal Technology Division conducted the evaluation at U.S. Army Blossom Point Research Facility. The Joint Improvised Explosive Device Defeat Organization sponsors the program.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
