<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Small Businesses Awarded Telecommunications Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 15, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>telecommunications</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Long Wave Incorporated, Oklahoma City (N39430-14-D-1422); SiteMaster Incorporated, Tulsa, Oklahoma (N39430-14-D-1423); and Shape Construction Incorporated, Bremerton, Washington (N39430-14-D-1424), are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity multiple award contract for construction services for specialized antennas, towers, and communication facilities at Navy installations worldwide. The maximum dollar value including the base period and two option periods for all three contracts combined is $45,000,000. The work to be performed provides for the maintenance, repair, or new construction of telecommunication towers and supporting communications and electrical equipment for Navy telecommunication towers. These requirements may include project development, concept development, design, engineering analysis, preparation of plans, writing of specifications, estimation of construction costs, fabrication, construction, and controlling quality, troubleshooting, overhauling old equipment, procuring new components, equipment installation and testing. SiteMaster Incorporated is being awarded task order 0001 at $669,794 for the extension of top-load radials at the Naval Radio Transmitting Facility, Aguada, Puerto Rico. Work for this task order is expected to be completed by November 2014. All work on this contract will be performed at various Navy installations worldwide. The term of the contract is not to exceed 36 months, with an expected completion date of May 2017. The Naval Facilities Engineering and Expeditionary Warfare Center, Port Hueneme, California, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
