<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Jacobs Supports Information Assurance in Multiple Countries</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 16, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
    <department>International</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Jacobs Technology</tag>
    <tag>Information Assurance</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Jacobs Technology Incorporated, Bedford, Massachusetts, has been awarded a $23,547,235 cost-plus-fixed-fee and cost-reimbursable contract (FA8721-14-C-0016) to provide engineering and technology acquisition support services, which consist of disciplined systems/specialty engineering and technical/information assurance services, support, and products using established government, contractor, and industry processes. Work will be performed at Hanscom Air Force Base (AFB), Massachusetts, Lackland AFB, Texas, Schreiver AFB, Colorado, Eglin AFB, Florida, and Wright-Patterson AFB, Ohio, and is expected to be complete by Nov. 30, 2015. This award is the result of a sole source acquisition. Fiscal 2012, 2013 and 2014 procurement, aircraft procurement, missile procurement, and foreign military sales (for Oman and Taiwan) funds in the amount of $2,826,951 will be obligated at time of award. The company also was awarded $60,430,781 contract (FA8721-14-C-0018) to provide the same services to Hanscom Air Force Base, Peterson AFB, Colorado, Langley AFB, Virginia, Tinker AFB, Oklahoma, and Seattle, Washington. Fiscal year 2013 and 2014 research and development, procurement, operations and maintenance and foreign military sales (Saudi Arabia, Iraq, Jordan, Australia and Taiwan) funds in the amount of $39,988,406 will be obligated at time of award. Air Force Life Cycle Management Center, Hanscom AFB, Massachusetts, is the contracting activity for both awards.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
