<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Air Force Awards $3 Billion for Research and Development</title>
  <author/>
  <date>June 6, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Alion Science and Technology, Burr Ridge, Illinois (FA8075-14-D-0014); Battelle Memorial Institute, Columbus, Ohio (FA8075-14-D-0015); Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Virginia (FA8075-14-D-0016); EOIR Technologies Inc., Fredericksburg, Virginia (FA8075-14-D-0017); Georgia Tech Research Institute, Atlanta, Georgia (FA8075-14-D-0018); MacAulay-Brown Inc., Dayton, Ohio (FA8075-14-D-0019); Mantech TSG-2 Joint Venture, Fairfax, Virginia (FA8075-14-D-0020); Prescient Edge Corporation, McLean, Virginia (FA8075-14-D-0021); Strategic Analysis Inc., Arlington, Virginia (FA8075-14-D-0022); TASC Inc., Andover, Maryland (FA8075-14-D-0023); URS Federal Services Inc., Germantown, Maryland (FA8075-14-D-0024); and Wyle Laboratories Inc., Huntsville, Alabama (FA8075-14-D-0025) have been awarded a maximum $3 billion cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price, multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for Defense Systems Technical Area Tasks (DS TATs). The DS TATs contracts will provide research, development, test and evaluation, and advisory and assistance services related to research and development efforts for technical area tasks within the Advanced Materials; Autonomous Systems; Directed Energy; Energetics; Military Sensing; Non-Lethal Weapons and Information Operations; Reliability, Maintainability, Quality, Supportability, and Interoperability; Survivability and Vulnerability; and Weapons Systems focus areas. Generally, work will be performed at government facilities, and the period of performance is five years. The ordering period is a one-year basic period with four one-year option periods with work expected to be completed by June 2019 if all option periods are exercised. The Air Force Installation Contracting Agency, Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
