<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cyber Operations Centers of Academic Excellence List Expands</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>July 14, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
    <department>Intelligence</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>homeland defense</tag>
    <tag>information operations</tag>
    <tag>Security</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The National Security Agency has added five schools to the National Centers of Academic Excellence in Cyber Operations Program.</abstract>
  <text>The National Security Agency (NSA) has selected five more schools for the National Centers of Academic Excellence (CAE) in Cyber Operations Program, which is designed to cultivate more U.S. cyber professionals. These schools are now designated as Cyber Operations CAEs for the 2014-2019 academic years:

		New York University, New York;
	
		Towson University, Maryland;
	
		United States Military Academy, New York;
	
		University of Cincinnati, Ohio; and
	
		University of New Orleans, Louisiana
The program, which now has a total of 13 schools, complements the more than 100 existing centers of academic excellence in information assurance research and education jointly overseen by the NSA and the Department of Homeland Security. An outgrowth of the president’s National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education, the CAE in Cyber Operations Program identifies institutions that have a deeply technical, interdisciplinary curriculum centered on fields such as computer science, computer engineering and electrical engineering.
	In addition, the Cyber Operations Program offers participants opportunities to apply their learning or enhance their teaching in a summer internship program at the NSA. Participating students and faculty members do not engage in actual U.S. government intelligence activities.
	Applications to become a designated CAE in Cyber Operations are evaluated annually and are due by January 15 each year. Designations are for five years and all schools across the country can compete to join.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
