<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Air Force Awards Nearly $500 Million to Host Space Payloads</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 11, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>space</tag>
    <tag>Satellites</tag>
    <tag>Hosted Payloads</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Astrium Services Government Incorporated, Rockville, Maryland (FA8814-14-D-0001); Harris Corporation Government Communications Systems Business Unit, Palm Bay, Florida (FA8814-14-D-0002); Space Systems/Loral LLC, Palo Alto, California (FA8814-14-D-0003); Millennium Engineering &amp; Integration Company, Arlington, Virginia (FA8814-14-D-0004); Surrey Satellite Technology, Englewood, Colorado (FA8814-14-D-0005); Orbital Sciences Corporation, Dulles, Virginia (FA8814-14-D-0006); The Boeing Company, El Segundo, California (FA8814-14-D-0007); Exoterra Resource, Littleton, Colorado (FA8814-14-D-0008); Lockheed Martin Corporation., Littleton, Colorado (FA8814-14-D-0009); Merging Excellence and Innovation Tech Incorporated, Houston, Texas (FA8814-14-D-0010); ViviSat LLC, Beltsville, Maryland (FA8814-14-D-0011); Intelsat General Corp., Bethesda, Maryland (FA8814-14-D-0012); SES Government Solutions, McLean, Virginia (FA8814-14-D-0013); and Eutelsat America Corporation, Washington, District of Columbia (FA8814-14-D-0014), have each been awarded a $494,900,000 maximum firm-fixed-price, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity (IDIQ) contract under the Hosted Payload Solutions (HoPS) program. The purpose of the multiple awarded HoPS IDIQ contract is to provide a rapid and flexible means for the government to acquire commercial hosting capabilities for government payloads. The contract is designed to create a pool of qualified vendors to meet the government's needs for various hosted payload missions. The HoPS IDIQ scope includes procurement of hosted payload missions and procurement of hosted payload studies. Procurement of hosted payload missions includes a fully-functioning on-orbit hosted payload space and ground system for government-furnished payloads on commercial platforms. In addition to the space and ground systems, the HoPS mission will also include related on-orbit support for data transfer from the hosted payload to the government end-user(s). The HoPS studies include those study activities related to enabling hosted payloads. The contract has a five-year ordering period from the date of award. The Space and Missile Systems Center Contracting Directorate, El Segundo, California, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
