<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Veterans Affairs Awards Contract to Help Veterans in Rural Areas Access Services</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>July 21, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>business</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Department of Veterans Affairs hired a contractor to help veterans who live in rural areas learn to acccess and navigate technical programs that will give them better access to their medical records.</abstract>
  <text>The Department of Veterans Affairs’ (VA) Office of Information and Technology awarded its fourth and final contract for its Transformation Twenty-One Total Technology (T4) contract to help veterans navigate technical access to health care services.
	Creative Computing Solutions Incorporated (CCSi) will provide on-site rural health community coordinators at each of the VA’s 55 rural medical centers and help staffers and veterans optimize use of available and emerging technologies and access such programs as the virtual lifetime electronic record (VLER) health program, direct secure messaging and the blue button download, a tool to make patient medical records easily available for patients to download and share with health care professionals.
	“Veterans living in rural areas often are challenged in terms of readily available access to an array of online services provided by the VA,” says Maggie Bauer, senior vice president for health services at CCSi.
	Last week, CCSi received a contract to provide the VA with two teams of experts to improve processes and manage the technical management support services for the Health Products Support (HPS) system increased workload and operational tempo. CCSi is a provider of health services, program management, cybersecurity and enterprise systems engineering to the federal government.
	To provide the services to rural veterans, CCSi teamed with Grant Thornton, Armed Forces Services Corporation, a service-disabled veteran-owned business and Atlas Research, a service-disabled veteran-owned small business.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
