<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Active Duty Service Members Eligible for Expedited TSA PreCheck Program</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>August 27, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Service members can get expedited travel screening at TSA PreCheck airports using their Defense Department identification number when booking flight reservations. The security approach is available to all members of the U.S. armed forces, including the reserves, the National Guard and the U.S. Coast Guard.</abstract>
  <text>Service members can get expedited travel screening at Transportation Security Administration (TSA) PreCheck airports using their Defense Department identification number when booking flight reservations. The security approach is available to all members of the U.S. armed forces, including the reserves, the National Guard and the U.S. Coast Guard.

The expedited screening service also is available to Defense Department and Coast Guard civilian employees and for children 12 and younger who accompany active duty travelers who have the TSA’s PreCheck indicator already on their boarding passes. Civilians first must register and select the one-time, opt-in option of the PreCheck program by visiting the “milConnect” website, selecting “My Profile” and the “CIV”menu tab. Active duty members already are eligible and do not need to opt in.

When making a flight reservation, active duty travelers must use the 10-digit Defense Department ID number printed on the back of the common access card, which also will serve as the "known traveler number." The expedited service is available to members and civilians  traveling on both personal and official travel.

All other travelers who wish to enroll in the TSA’s PreCheck program can do so at 302 enrollment centers throughout the nation. They first need to pre-enroll online, then make an appointment to complete the process, which includes fingerprinting and verification of identification documents.

Additionally, the U.S. Customs and Border Protection launched an app for Apple devices that expedites entry process for U.S. citizens and Canadian visitors.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
