<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Army Awards More Than $7 Billion in Intelligence and Information Operations Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 15, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Army</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>BAE Systems Information Solutions Inc., McLean, Virginia (W91W4-14-D-0001); Booz Allen Hamilton Inc., McLean, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0002); CACI Technologies Inc., Manassas, Virginia (W911(W4-14-D-0003); DynCorp International LLC, McLean, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0004); Invertix Corp., McLean, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0005); Lockheed Martin Integrated Systems Inc., Bethesda, Maryland (W911W4-14-D-0006); ManTech Mission, Cyber and Technology Solutions Inc., Falls Church, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0007); Northrop Grumman Systems Corp., Cyber Solutions Division Inc., Chantilly, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0008); Six3 Intelligence Solutions Inc., McLean, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0009); Sotera Defense Solutions Inc., Herndon, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0010); and SRA International Inc., Fairfax, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0011), were collectively awarded a ceiling $5,040,000,000 hybrid, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for global intelligence support services acquisition.

In addition, small business firms Absolute Business Corp., Herndon, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0012); Archimedes Global, Wesley Chapel, Florida (W911W4-14-D-0013); Calhoun International LLC, Tampa, Florida (W911W4-14-D-0014); Circinus LLC, Fredericksburg, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0015); Charles F. Day &amp; Associates, Stafford, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0016); E&amp;M Technologies Inc., Laurel, Maryland (W911W4-14-D-0017); Integral Consulting Services, Gaithersburg, Maryland (W911W4-14-D-0018); K-3 Enterprises Inc., Fayetteville, North Carolina (W911W4-14-D-0019); Pluribus International Corp., Alexandria, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0020); and The Buffalo Group, Reston, Virginia (W911W4-14-D-0021), were collectively awarded a $2,160,000,000 hybrid, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for global intelligence support services acquisition. This acquisition is designed to acquire flexible, comprehensive, cost effective services to support the Army's need for fully integrated intelligence, security, information operations and related support. Funding and work location will be determined with each order, with an estimated completion date of Sept. 11, 2019. Each contractor will compete for task orders, and receive a minimum guarantee of $5,000. Bids were solicited via the Internet, with 17 received. Army Intelligence and Security Command, Fort Belvoir, Virginia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
