<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>NGI Rolls Out, FBI Exploring More Biometrics</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>September 16, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>FBI</tag>
    <tag>biometrics</tag>
    <tag>Global Identity Summit</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The FBI’s Next Generation Identification system went live last week, replacing the Integrated Automated Fingerprint Identification System and improving accuracy.</abstract>
  <text>The FBI’s Next Generation Identification (NGI) system went live last week, replacing the Integrated Automated Fingerprint Identification System and improving accuracy. According to experts, the new system offers 99.6 percent correct identification versus 92 percent with the former. The NGI enables automation of 93 percent of searches. Other upgrades include connections with the National Palm Print System, an iris-modality repository and capabilities for more mobile detections.

More advancements in biometrics identification are underway. Amy Hess, executive assistant director, Science and Technology Branch, FBI, told the Global Identity Summit in Tampa today that her organization is collaborating with the departments of Homeland Security and Defense on requirements for collection of rapid DNA. The bureau also is exploring video analytics in more depth, as the proliferation of video and imagery has skyrocketed in recent years.

The government is working to link many systems that record legal violations from a variety of sources such as the battlefield, border points and detention centers. Repeated criminal behavior remains a major concern for law enforcement. Technology has advanced to identify fugitives while in custody and link them to other crimes they may have committed. Though criminal activity has dropped significantly in the last decade, 10.2 million violent and property crimes were perpetrated in 2012, the last year for which numbers are available, and the FBI wants to further reduce that amount. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
