<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Firms Awarded Counter-IED Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 17, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
    <department>International</department>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>counter-IED</tag>
    <tag>Robotics</tag>
    <tag>Army</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Advanced Reconnaissance Corporation, Fishkill, New York (W911QX-14-D-0007); Applied Research Associates Incorporated, Albuquerque, New Mexico (W911QX-14-D-0008); A-T Solutions Incorporated, Fredericksburg, Virginia (W911QX-14-D-0009); CyPhy Works Incorporated, Danvers, Massachusetts (W911QX-14-D-0010); EFW Incorporated, Ft. Worth, Texas (W911QX-14-D-0011); L-3 Communications Corporation, Camden, New Jersey (W911QX-14-D-0012); NIITEK Incorporated, Dulles, Virginia (W911QX-14-D-0013); Primal Innovation LLC, Sanford, Florida (W911QX-14-D-0014); QinetiQ Incorporated, Centreville, Virginia (W911QX-14-D-0015); Robo-Team NA Incorporated, Bethesda, Maryland (W911QX-14-D-0016); Advanced Technology Systems Company Incorporated (of Virginia), McLean, Virginia (W911QX-14-D-0017); Applied Research Associates Incorporated, Albuquerque, New Mexico (W911QX-14-D-0018); iRobot Corporation, Bedford, Massachusetts (W911QX-14-D-0019); K2 Solutions Incorporated, Southern Pines, North Carolina (W911QX-14-D-0020); Lockheed Martin Procerus Technologies L.C., Orem, Utah (W911QX-14-D-0021); QinetiQ Incorporated, Centreville, Virginia (W911QX-14-D-0023); Robo-Team NA Incorporated, Bethesda, Maryland (W911QX-14-D-0024); Stolar Research Corporation, Rio Rancho, New Mexico (W911QX-14-D-0026); Science and Engineering Services LLC, Columbia, Maryland (W911QX-14-D-0025); and Pearson Engineering Ltd., Newcastle Upon Tyne, Great Britain (W911QX-14-D-0022), were collectively awarded a ceiling $49,497,158 indefinite- delivery/indefinite-quantity, multi-year contract for the Army Research Lab/Joint Improvised Explosive Device Defeat Organization Culvert Denial Challenge program. The contract covers the initial task order challenge event through possible future testing, development and deployment. The Army Contracting Command, Adelphi, Maryland, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
