<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Government, Industry Conduct Vital Intelligence Research </title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>September 19, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Intelligence Summit 2014</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Rather than devote valuable resources pursuing every possible technology solution, the intelligence community complements similar efforts in the commercial sector.</abstract>
  <text>Government is targeting intelligence technology research to maximize its return while relying on industry to provide complementary development, according to a group of government intelligence technologists. This approach aims to address budget constraints amid increased investments by other nations.

Some of the community’s research practices were outlined by a panel at the AFCEA/INSA Intelligence and National Security Summit 2014, being held September 18-19 in Washington, D.C. Peter Highnam, director of the Intelligence Advanced Research Projects Agency (IARPA), noted that IARPA does not fund basic research. Instead, it builds on t?he research done by industry.

Highnam explained that everything IARPA does is of limited duration, including an enforced personnel rotation cycle of three to five years. This also prevents research from becoming bogged down over the long term. The agency also tracks other research developments institutionally, and it has an automated system that monitors technical journals worldwide. Some IARPA programs seek to forecast real-world events, Highnam noted, adding that they are doing well.

Allan Sonsteby, director, Applied Research Labs, Pennsylvania State University, reported that the percentage of funds committed to research and development by other nations is increasing. Globally, $1.435 trillion is spend on research and development, with 66 percent of that being spent by Asia and North America. The United States spends the most of any country, but China has more capacity to put a greater amount of resources into research.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
