<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>High-Tech Toys for Expeditionary Forces Showcased at Modern Day Marine Expo</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>September 25, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Marine Corps</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Massive tents housed booths with roughly 400 companies pitching the up-and-coming technology to approximately 8,000 attendees at the 2014 Modern Day Marine event held at U.S. Marine Corps Base Quantico in Virginia. Much of the technology focused on equipping expeditionary forces.</abstract>
  <text>Whether calling for close air support from an armed A-10, an unmanned aerial vehicle or a Howitzer artillery piece miles away, U.S. joint terminal attack controllers now are field testing a ruggedized, chest-mounted computer that provides optimal situational awareness.

The Forward Air Control Utility Suite (FAC-US) by Black Diamond was among the latest in military technology, particularly for expeditionary forces, showcased by the roughly 400 exhibiting companies at the 2014 Modern Day Marine exposition held at U.S. Marine Corps Base Quantico, Virginia.

Massive tents housed booths with companies pitching the up-and-coming technology, from renewable energy products that cut down on the forces’ need for fuel, which is both costly and often a convoy target, to high-tech toys such as driverless vehicles, robots, laser weapons and rapidly deployable communications systems that can be set up for trusted cellular connections. Attendees who meandered through the tents could visit booths that also showcased some not so high-tech, but perhaps equally imperative, products such as knives, boots and even boot insoles.

While the three-day exposition ended Thursday, organizers already have scheduled next year’s events. Marine West takes place at Camp Pendleton, California, on January 28 and 29. Marine South takes place at Camp Lejeune, North Carolina, on April 22 and 23. Next year’s Modern Day Marine, again at Quantico, is set for September 22 through 24.

The expo, sponsored by the Marine Corps League and hosted by Marine Corps Base Quantico, drew an estimated 8,000 attendees.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>The Forward Air Control Utility Suite (FAC-US) by Black Diamond gives joint terminal attack controllers better situational awareness when calling for close air support. It was among 400 exhibits at the 2014 Modern Day Marine exhibition.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
