<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>NAVMAR to Support ISR in Afghanistan</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 30, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
    <department>International</department>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Afghanistan</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>NAVMAR Applied Sciences Corporation, Warminster, Pennsylvania, is being awarded $12,296,784 for delivery order 0015 against a previously issued basic ordering agreement (N68335-10-G-0026) for work associated with a Phase III Small Business Innovation Research effort under Topics N92-170: Laser Radar Laser Detection and Ranging Identification Demonstration; N94-178: Air-Deployable Expendable Multi-Parameter Environmental Probe; and AF083-006: Low Cost Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance, Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV). Efforts include the assessment, procurement and deployment of intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance systems; communication systems; unmanned systems; noise reduction technology; improved aircraft aerodynamics to include increased lift and decreased drag; unmanned air vehicle weatherization; improved endurance; support of at sea Navy operations; and related support hardware. Work will be performed in Yuma, Arizona (30 percent); Patuxent River, Maryland (20 percent); Afghanistan (20 percent); China Lake, California (15 percent); and Point Mugu, California (15 percent), and is expected to be completed in September 2015.

In addition, the company is being awarded $8,597,356 for delivery order 0001 against a previously issued basic ordering agreement (N68335-14-G-0040) for work associated with a Phase III Small Business Innovation Research effort under topics N08-023: Precision High Altitude Sonobuoy Emplacement; N94-178: Air-Deployable Expendable Multi-Parameter Environmental Probe; and AF083-006: Low Cost Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance, Unmanned Aerial Vehicle. Efforts are associated with the advancements in command, control, communications, computer, intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance technologies to enhance communication techniques between the sensors and/or platforms and interfaces; analyze the fusion and exploitation of multi-source sensor data; and develop any other technique to advance capabilities. The Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Lakehurst, New Jersey, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
