<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>JIEDDO Holds Competition for New Counter-IED Systems</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>October 8, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>bomb detector</tag>
    <tag>JIEDDO</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Military experts and defense contractors are testing technologies in Georgia to thwart the preponderance of roadside bombs that hamper U.S. military and coalition forces' combat and resupply missions. Participating defense contractors are competing for an existing $49.5 million contract.</abstract>
  <text>Military experts and defense contractors are testing technologies to thwart the preponderance of roadside bombs that hamper U.S. military and coalition forces' combat and resupply missions. Participating defense contractors are competing for an existing $49.5 million contract.

The Joint Improvised Explosive Device Defeat Organization (JIEDDO) has partnered with the U.S. Army Research Lab and the Maneuver Battle Lab to host at Fort Benning, Georgia, a 10-day “Culvert Denial Challenge” that ends October 10.

Ten teams are doing what has been classified as a surveillance challenge, in which they will use unmanned systems, microradar technologies, seismic sensors and hyperspectral imaging, or imaging collected from across the electromagnetic spectrum. Ten other teams are doing an inspection challenge.

“Once we’ve secured a culvert, we wanted technology that can maintain security over that area,” says Matthew Way, a JIEDDO program integrator. “The competition really focuses on their ability to distinguish, per the solicitation, between nefarious activity and something that is benign—just regular patterns of life.”

Vendors in the inspection challenge are supposed to demonstrate potential solutions using quadcopter (four rotor helicopter) ground robots, canines and electromagnetic sensors. “We are really measuring how quickly they can get into a culvert area and tell me if it's clear or not clear,” Way says. “The second component that we are scoring them on is, once they’ve done that, how accurately can they identify particular items that may be threats in the region.”

Officials hope new technology might provide better detection and thus protection against the threat of roadside bombs.

JIEDDO officials are expected to declare winners roughly 30 days after the competition. The surveillance teams are: Advanced Recon Corp, Applied Research Associates, A-T Solutions, CyPhy Works, EFW (Elbit), L-3 Communications, Niitek, Primal Innovation, QinetiQ and Roboteam. The inspection teams are: Applied Research Associates, ATSC (Inuktun), iRobot, K2 Solutions, Lockheed Martin, Pearson Engineering, QinetiQ, Roboteam, Science and Engineering Services, and Stolar Research.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>A U.S. soldier with the 65th Engineer Battalion installs culvert denial systems in Helmand province, Afghanistan. The system can detect disturbances from vibrations to heat and initiate a camera to record attempts of tampering.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
