<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DARPA Seeks Technology to Detect, ID Substances from Great Distances </title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>October 9, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DARPA</tag>
    <tag>biological agent detection</tag>
    <tag>chemical agent detectors</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) put a call out for technology that can detect and identify from great distances dangerous biological and chemical substances. </abstract>
  <text>The Defense Department's premier research agency put a call out for technology that can detect and identify from great distances dangerous biological and chemical substances. 

The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) issued a broad agency announcement for the development of the small devices for the new Spectral Combs from UV to THz (SCOUT) program, according to the agency.

“In laboratory settings we’ve seen proof of principle that it’s possible to identify and quantify multiple substances at a distance of 2 kilometers or more, but no portable sensors exist today that can detect and distinguish among multiple chemical or biological agents in gas or liquid form at even half that distance,” Prem Kumar, DARPA program manager, says in a statement. “The challenge DARPA is addressing is to develop portable, microchip-size optical frequency combs that display a high degree of sensitivity and specificity across the electromagnetic spectrum, even in a cluttered frequency environment.”

Officials seek devices that can harness optical frequency comb (OFC) technology, which experts liken to the creation of a hair comb with extremely fine teeth using thousands of lasers at the same time. The technology would allow for high sensitivity and wide spectral coverage that can detect biological and chemical substances from several hundred yards away.

The response deadline is November 25. Details will be available on an October 15 proposers' day webcast.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
