<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>CDC Apps Provide Easy Access to Health Information</title>
  <author>Rachel Lilly</author>
  <date>October 21, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>With the Ebola outbreak dominating headlines and flu season looming, it's difficult to know where to turn for fast, reliable health information. That's where the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention comes in, offering a variety of apps to help you protect yourself.</abstract>
  <text>With the Ebola outbreak dominating headlines and flu season looming, it's difficult to know where to turn for fast, reliable health information. That's where the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) comes in, offering a variety of apps to help you protect yourself.

Want health information at your fingertips 24/7? The CDC's main app offers timely health articles, a "Disease of the Week" topic with key facts and prevention tips, details on current outbreaks and press releases from the CDC newsroom, among other features. Access videos, podcasts, blogs and social media, and share interesting content with friends.

Concerned about the spread of the flu? The FluView app tracks influenza-like illness activity levels across the United States and identifies trends. Data comes from more than 3,000 health care providers in all 50 states. Plus, get access to state health department websites for local surveillance information.

Want to learn more about diseases in an engaging way? Check out the Solve the Outbreak app, which highlights how the CDC's disease detectives save lives around the world. You'll be on a mission to analyze data and solve an outbreak. Figure out how the outbreak started before it spreads further, and earn honors by solving new and more challenging scenarios.

Check out a full list of the CDC's mobile apps.

These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
