<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Marine Corps Procures Four G/ATORs</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 24, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>G/ATOR</tag>
    <tag>Marine Corps</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Northrop Grumman Corp. Electronic Systems, Linthicum Heights, Maryland, is being awarded a $207,291,682 modification to a previously awarded contract (M67854-07-C-2072) for procurement of four Ground/Air Task-Oriented Radar (G/ATOR) low-rate initial production systems, including operating spares, contractor engineering services and support, developmental and operational test support, and transition to production. G/ATOR is an expeditionary, three-dimensional, short-to-medium-range multi-role radar system designed to detect low-observable, low-radar cross section targets such as rockets, artillery, mortars, cruise missiles, and unmanned aircraft systems. G/ATOR is being developed and fielded in three blocks and will be employed by the Marine Air Ground Task Force across the range of military operations.

Work will be performed in Linthicum Heights, Maryland (55 percent); East Syracuse, New York (24 percent); Stafford Springs, Connecticut (5 percent); San Diego, California (5 percent); Big Lake, Minnesota (3 percent); Londonderry, New Hampshire (2 percent); High Point, North Carolina (2 percent); Wallingford Center, Connecticut (2 percent); Camarillo, California (1 percent); and Woodbridge, Illinois (1 percent), and is expected to be completed by October 2017. Fiscal 2013 procurement (Marine Corps) funds in the amount of $81,934,362; fiscal 2014 procurement (Marine Corps) funds in the amount of $80,869,885; and fiscal 2014 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $12,735,865, will be obligated at the time of award. Contract funds in the amount of $94,670,227 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Marine Corps Systems Command, Quantico, Virginia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
