<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Personalized Training App Challenges Your Brain</title>
  <author>Rachel Lilly</author>
  <date>November 4, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>You might hit the gym or stay active for your health, but do you exercise your brain? The scientifically designed program Lumosity provides personalized training to help you improve memory, attention and a wide variety of other cognitive skills.</abstract>
  <text>You might hit the gym or stay active for your health, but do you exercise your brain? The scientifically designed program Lumosity provides personalized training to help you improve memory, attention and a wide variety of other cognitive skills. The program, based on extensive research in the field of neuroplasticity, currently boasts more than 50 million members in more than 180 countries. Lumosity's in-house research and development team collaborates with researchers from 36 top universities around the world, including Harvard, Stanford and UC Berkeley, to transform common neuropsychological tasks into fun, challenging games.

To begin, you identify which aspects of memory, attention, speed, flexibility and problem solving you hope to challenge, including associating names with faces, dividing your attention between multiple tasks, ignoring distractions, making decisions quickly in time-sensitive situations and calculating figures in your head, among many others. Lumosity then creates simple daily workouts with exercises that reflect your choices. Play online or on the go.

Analysis of the program database shows just 10-15 minutes of Lumosity training per day can lead to improvements in cognitive skills.

Basic Lumosity membership is free, and unsubscribed members have access to a limited amount of games and features. Subscribers have full access, including all games, training and progress monitoring tools. Prices range from $4.99 per month to $14.95 per month depending on the length of the commitment.

Download the free app from the iTunes App Store or Google Play.

These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img></img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
