<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>New TSA PreCheck Program Enrolls Travelers at Participating Work, School Locations</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>November 25, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>TSA</tag>
    <tag>travel</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The contractor that facilitates enrollment in the U.S. Transportation Security Administration’s PreCheck program developed an enrollment option to let employees of participating organizations sign up at their offices, saving them the trip to an airport or off-site enrollment center.</abstract>
  <text>The contractor that facilitates enrollment in the U.S. Transportation Security Administration’s PreCheck program developed an enrollment option to let employees of participating organizations sign up at their offices, saving them the trip to an airport or off-site enrollment center.

MorphoTrust USA’s rollout adds to previous efforts to provide faster and more efficient screening at participating U.S. airport checkpoints for domestic and international travelers. The firm already provides enrollment services for travelers at more than 300 locations, including major airports and at off-airport IdentoGO centers. The program is available at more than 120 airports nationwide.

The mobile enrollment program is available to a number of organizations, including universities, trade associations, sports teams and travel companies.

A company enrollment services team will partner with organizations to schedule enrollment days. Then, trained agents will set up secure workstations in conference rooms or other common spaces to record travelers' biographic data and fingerprints, which is sent to the TSA for processing. Once approved, travelers receive a “known traveler number,” which is printed on their boarding passes and gives them access to the TSA PreCheck lines. TSA charges an $85 application fee, and enrollment is valid for five years.

Military members, eligible family and federal civilian employees can get expedited travel screening at TSA PreCheck airports using their Defense Department identification number when booking flight reservations. PreCheck travelers need to pre-enroll online. U.S. Customs and Border Protection also has an app that expedites the entry process for U.S. citizens and Canadian visitors.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
