<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Army Pacific Improves via Industry Innovation</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>December 10, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>TechNet Asia-Pacific 2014</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Army Pacific has a plan—coordinated with an overall Army modernization effort—to incorporate commercial innovation into its force to overcome many of the challenges it faces in the vast Asia-Pacific region.</abstract>
  <text>An emerging capabilities coordination cell (EC3) is the mechanism by which the U.S. Army Pacific (USARPAC) seeks to incorporate commercial innovation to meet its mission needs. The EC3 approach is integrated with overall Army plans to upgrade the force over the next 11 years.

Speaking in a science and technology panel on day two of TechNet Asia-Pacific 2014, being held in Honolulu December 9-11, Col. Charles Heimann, USA, assistant chief of staff G-6, U.S. Army Pacific, explained how the EC3 will improve USARPAC. The command has the goal of leveraging what industry brings to the table so that it can push mission command to the farthest and most western portion of its area of operation—and with interoperability.

USARPAC will combine its existing capabilities with those of industry through 2020. Then, it will move toward the 2025 expeditionary Army goals—mission command on the move; counter weapons of mass destruction; cyberspace; deploying operationally significant forces; sustainment; and balanced lethality, mobility and protection.

EC3 will have four phases. The first will encompass capability gap determination and system nomination; the second will establish requirements for equipment; the third will have units training and using the equipment in the area of operation; and the fourth will generate reporting on their results.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
