<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Receives Global Broadcast Service Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 22, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Global Broadcast Service</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Intelligence, Information and Services, Sterling, Virginia, is being awarded a $6,678,321 firm-fixed-price contract for the production, integration, test and delivery of the global broadcast service (GBS) below deck terminals. The GBS is a key component of the Joint Military Satellite Communications program, which provides high-speed information flow of high volume data to users both afloat, ashore and for Special Forces. The GBS provides the capability to receive, process and quickly disseminate live video and large files to support operating forces, training exercises, weapons targeting, intelligence and reconnaissance. This contract includes options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to an estimated $42,572,992. Work will be performed in Sterling, Virginia (56 percent); Norfolk, Virginia, (26 percent); and Dulles, Virginia (18 percent), and is expected to be completed by October 2015. If all options are exercised, work could continue until October 2019. Fiscal 2014 other procurement (Navy) and fiscal 2012, 2013 and 2014 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) funds in the amount of $6,678,321 will be placed on contract and obligated at the time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via the Commerce Business Daily’s Federal Business Opportunities website, and the SPAWAR e-Commerce Central website, with one offer received. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, is the contracting activity (N00039-15-C-0002).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
