<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Northrop Grumman to Provide Airborne Laser Detection Systems</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 29, 2014</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Airborne Laser Mine Detection System</tag>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Northrop Grumman Systems Corp., Melbourne, Florida is being awarded a $35,514,955 firm-fixed price contract for the fabrication, integration, test and production of airborne laser mine detection systems (ALMDS) and delivery of peculiar support equipment and engineering services to support those systems. This contract is in support of the Program Executive Office Littoral Combat Ships (LCS). ALMDS is a laser-based system, which uses streak tube imaging light detection and ranging to detect, classify, and localize surface and near-surface moored sea mines. The system is mounted on the MH-60S helicopter and will be deployed from the LCS. ALMDS provides a revolutionary, high area coverage rate capability that is organic to the Expeditionary and Carrier Strike Groups. 

This contract includes options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to $163,572,967. Work will be performed in Melbourne, Florida (41 percent); Tucson, Arizona (31 percent); St. Charles, Missouri (11 percent); Irvine, California (7 percent); Santa Clarita, California (6 percent); and Brentwood, New York (4 percent), and is expected to be completed by February 2021. Fiscal 2013 and 2014 other procurement (Navy) funding in the amount of $$33,822,775 will be obligated at time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured with one proposal and one offer received via Federal Business Opportunities. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity (N00024-15-C-6318).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
