<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Educational Activities: AFCEA Offers Scholarships, Awards and Grants</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 1, 2015</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The AFCEA Educational Foundation is a 501(c)(3) nonprofit international organization dedicated to providing educational incentives, opportunities and assistance for people engaged in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM).</abstract>
  <text>The AFCEA Educational Foundation is a 501(c)(3) nonprofit international organization dedicated to providing educational incentives, opportunities and assistance for people engaged in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM). Disciplines include information technology, cybersecurity, telecommunications and electronics that support the defense, homeland security and intelligence communities.

AFCEA and its chapters offer more than $2 million in scholarships to military veterans, ROTC cadets and students majoring in STEM fields or secondary education for the purpose of teaching STEM subjects in U.S. middle/intermediate and high schools.
Scholarships, awards and grants are offered to the following:

STEM Majors 
Scholarships ranging from $2,000 to $5,000 are awarded to full-time students actively pursuing an undergraduate or a graduate degree in STEM subjects directly related to the mission of AFCEA, such as cybersecurity, intelligence studies, computer science, biometrics, information technology or electronics engineering.

Minorities
Scholarships ranging from $3,000 to $5,000 are awarded to full-time minority students and women actively pursuing an undergraduate degree at historically black colleges and universities (HBCUs) or a graduate degree at any college or university in the United States in a STEM subject directly related to the mission of AFCEA.

War Veterans 
Scholarships of $2,500 are awarded to active-duty service members and honorably discharged U.S. military veterans (including reservists and National Guard personnel) from Operations Enduring Freedom and Iraqi Freedom who are enrolled part time or full time majoring in subjects directly related to the mission of AFCEA, such as computer science, computer engineering, systems engineering, information technology, electronics engineering or mathematics.

ROTC Cadets
ROTC scholarships ranging from $2,000 to $5,000 are awarded to ROTC students enrolled full time in a C4I-related major. ROTC Medal of Honor scholarships recognize the top ROTC undergraduate students of the Air Force, Army, Navy and Marine Corps who demonstrate leadership performance and potential and strong commitment to serve in the U.S. armed forces.  

Future and Current STEM Teachers 
Scholarships of $5,000 are awarded to students pursuing teaching degrees in a STEM discipline who are planning to teach at a U.S. middle/intermediate or high school upon completion of their degree.

In addition, the Gravely Teacher Tool Grant program is a partnership with AFCEA chapters and the Educational Foundation to award STEM teachers at middle/intermediate or high schools grants to assist with the cost of STEM-related activities for their students, such as robotics and cybersecurity clubs as well as STEM-focused equipment. These grants range from $500 to $1,000.

Students at Military Institutions
The AFCEA Educational Foundation presents approximately 150 awards for academic excellence in more than 30 educational institutions and training commands of the uniformed services each year.
 Step Up for STEM
Thanks to the generous contributions of corporate sponsors, chapters and individual donors, the AFCEA Educational Foundation is able to award scholarships and grants to these deserving students. 

AFCEA relies on donor support to build a strong future for the AFCEA Educational Foundation.

Every tax-deductible gift is important and demonstrates your confidence in the AFCEA Educational Foundation and its future.

Annual gifts may be made by check or credit card. Interested in doubling your donation? Participate in a matching gift program.

Many companies offer matching gift programs, so check with your company today.

For more information on making a tax-deductible gift, please visit http://link.afcea.org/give2STEM, or contact Tanika Coates at (703) 631-6149 or tcoates@afcea.org.

Regardless of size, your gift shows your AFCEA pride!</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Christopher Piazza (c) is presented the AFCEA STEM Major scholarship award.</img>
    <img>Pfc. Donald Ilobinso, USAR, receives the AFCEA Diversity scholarship award.</img>
    <img>Master Sgt. Aaron Kaplan, USAF (c), is awarded the AFCEA War Veteran scholarship. </img>
    <img>Cadet Robert Crumley (l) is presented the AFCEA Air Force ROTC scholarship award. </img>
    <img>Surrounded by his students, Jeremy Jonas, chemistry and biology teacher at Tucson High Magnet School, receives his grant.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
