<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Adds Two CANES Contractors</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 12, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>CANES</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>CGI Federal Incorporated, Fairfax, Virginia (N00039-15-D-0001), and DRS Laurel Technologies, Johnstown, Pennsylvania (N00039-15-D-0002), are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, firm-fixed-price, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for Consolidated Afloat Networks and Enterprise Services (CANES) production units. This contract has an eight-year ordering period up to the contract award amount. There are no options. The CGI Federal and DRS Laurel Technologies contracts are an addition to the five CANES production contracts awarded on August 20, 2014. The estimated cumulative value of the multiple award CANES contract is $2,529,500,000. CANES serves as the bridge to the future of Navy afloat networks, consolidating existing legacy and standalone networks and providing the necessary infrastructure for applications, systems and services to operate in the tactical domain. CANES delivers its capabilities within a single complete system, establishing the necessary infrastructure that will enable timely and interoperable information exchange among tactical, support and non-tactical or administrative users, applications and information technology platforms. Work will be performed in Charleston, South Carolina, and Jonestown, Pennsylvania, as delivery orders determine. Work is expected to be completed by August 2022. No funds will be obligated at the time of award. Funds will be obligated as individual delivery orders are issued. The multiple award contracts were competitively procured by full and open competition bids via the SPAWAR e-Commerce Central and the Federal Business Opportunities websites, with seven offers received. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
