<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>ROTC Scholarships Honor AFCEA Leaders</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 1, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The legacy of five prominent AFCEA leaders continues on through ROTC scholarships named in their honor. Lt. Gen. James Rockwell, USA; Vice Adm. Jon L. Boyes, USN; Lt. Gen. Ron Iverson, USAF; Lt. Gen. John Dubia, USA; and Mort Marks have made significant contributions in developing, promoting and fostering the concepts, aims and goals of the AFCEA Educational Foundation.</abstract>
  <text>The legacy of five prominent AFCEA leaders continues on through ROTC scholarships named in their honor. Lt. Gen. James Rockwell, USA; Vice Adm. Jon L. Boyes, USN; Lt. Gen. Ron Iverson, USAF; Lt. Gen. John Dubia, USA; and Mort Marks have made significant contributions in developing, promoting and fostering the concepts, aims and goals of the AFCEA Educational Foundation. The scholarships that bear their names are presented annually to deserving sophomore or junior cadets of the Army, Navy and Air Force ROTC programs. ROTC cadets who earn such recognition are selected based on exemplifying the dedication, persistence, patriotism and selfless service of these honored AFCEA leaders.

Established in 1990 with an endowment from Advanced Technology Incorporated and administered by the AFCEA Educational Foundation, a scholarship named in honor of the late Gen. Rockwell recognizes an Army ROTC cadet majoring in a telecommunications engineering degree program. Gen. Rockwell served on both the AFCEA International and Educational Foundation boards of directors.

The Vice Adm. (Dr.) Jon L. Boyes Memorial Scholarship was established in 1993 to honor the memory and accomplishments of AFCEA International’s longest-serving president (10 years), during which time he established the AFCEA Educational Foundation. The scholarship recognizes a Navy ROTC midshipman or naval officer candidate majoring in electrical engineering.

The AFCEA Mort Marks Memorial Scholarship was established in 2010 by the AFCEA Montgomery Chapter through the AFCEA Educational Foundation in memory of Marks, a member of the chapter who made many significant contributions to further its Education Foundation. Marks, a graduate of the U.S. Naval Academy and U.S. Navy veteran, was a longtime Air Force civil service employee. During his 35-year career, he attained the civil service rank of Senior Executive Service, Level IV. 

The AFCEA Lt. Gen. Ronald W. Iverson Scholarship was established in 2012 by a generous contribution to the AFCEA Educational Foundation from LGS Innovations on the occasion of Gen. Iverson’s retirement as CEO of LGS. The scholarship is presented to a deserving sophomore or junior cadet of the Air Force ROTC program. Gen. Iverson served on the AFCEA Educational Foundation’s board of directors from 2007 to 2014.

The Lt. Gen. John A. Dubia Scholarship was established in 2014 to honor his longtime service and many significant contributions as executive vice president of AFCEA International. After retiring from the U.S. Army, Gen. Dubia served 14 years in this role, retiring from AFCEA in September 2013. The scholarship is awarded to Army ROTC sophomore or junior cadets.

For additional information on AFCEA ROTC scholarship programs, please visit www.afcea.org/scholarships/rotc.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Lt. Gen. John A. Dubia, USA (Ret.), former executive vice president of AFCEA International, presents Kimberly Nicole Denny of Jacksonville, Florida, the first AFCEA Lt. Gen. John A. Dubia, USA (Ret.), Scholarship in November 2014. Cadet Denny is a junior at Mary Baldwin College in Staunton, Virginia, and participates in the ROTC program at nearby Virginia Military Institute, Lexington, Virginia.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
