<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Naval Defensive Capabilities Increase in Importance</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>February 10, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>West 2015</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>New defensive technologies have risen in importance as the U.S. Navy confronts a host of new and diverse threats to its surface ships.</abstract>
  <text>New defensive technologies have risen in importance as the U.S. Navy confronts a host of new and diverse threats to its surface ships. These technologies range from upgrades to existing capabilities to exotic systems that would change the nature of naval warfare.

Some of these technologies were described by Vice Adm. Thomas S. Rowden, USN, commander, Naval Surface Forces and Naval Surface Force, U.S. Pacific Fleet. Speaking in a panel discussion at West 2015, being held in San Diego, February 10-12, Adm. Rowden said getting these new defensive technologies out to the ship will be a big help to the fleet. “It’s about changing the rules of the game in the middle of the game,” he declared.

For the short term, new upgrades will improve the Navy’s minehunting capability “significantly better than we have in the Avenger class,” the admiral offered. This additional capability also can be folded into littoral combat ships through spiral development, he added.

Longer-term advances include lasers and railguns, and they could have a significant effect on how battles are fought. “When the interceptor you’re using costs more than the missile being shot at you, you’re on the wrong side of the equation,” he said of the current situation facing the U.S. Navy. “We can’t get that laser, and the other weapons, out there fast enough.”

Vice Adm. Michael J. Connor, USN, commander, Naval Submarine Forces, commander, Submarine Forces-U.S. Atlantic Feet, and commander, Allied Submarine Command, called for torpedoes with a range at least 100 miles greater than currently in use. He also wants to add unmanned underwater combat vehicles for even greater range and introduce advances into the submarine force faster.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
