<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Commercial, Military Technologies Will Decide Defense Supremacy</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>February 10, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>West 2015</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lasers, railguns and unmanned underwater vehicles are just a few of the new capabilities the U.S. Defense Department is counting on to overcome advances pursued by potential adversaries.</abstract>
  <text>Lasers, railguns and unmanned underwater vehicles are just a few of the new capabilities the U.S. Defense Department is counting on to overcome advances pursued by potential adversaries. Both short- and long-term capabilities likely will feature a blend of commercial and military technologies, according to a senior Defense Department official.

Robert O. Work, deputy secretary of defense, described some of these technologies to the Tuesday morning audience at West 2015, being held in San Diego, February 10-12. Work stated that the military will see many potentially game-changing technologies over the long term.

For the short term, the administration is adding funding into several areas: countering anti-access/area denial efforts by others; missile defense; protecting space assets—Work described the U.S. space constellation as being “under more threat now than at any time”; and cyber operations.

He said that, in the past, the development of new military technologies was relatively easy. The single adversary was well known, and government provided the necessary technologies. However, with the multitude of changing threats, planning will be difficult. And, commercial systems both confound and offer opportunity.

"Commercial adaptation is causing all of us to scratch our heads and say, ‘Where are we headed?’” Work said. “Government must ensure that we are exploiting all of the advances they are pursuing.”</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
