<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Military Networks Must Reach Down, Reach Up</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>February 11, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>West 2015</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The advantages offered by defense network advances need to be sped to both the warfighter and the decision maker, according to a panel of service communicators. Improvements from security to data storage offer vital capabilities that vary among the different ranks in the military.</abstract>
  <text>The advantages offered by defense network advances need to be sped to both the warfighter and the decision maker, according to a panel of service communicators. Improvements from security to data storage offer vital capabilities that vary among the different ranks in the military.

Speaking at West 2015, being held in San Diego, February 10-12, Vice Adm. Ted N. Branch, USN, deputy chief of naval operations for information dominance, N-2/N-6, and director of naval intelligence, cited the advantages brought by the Consolidated Afloat Networks and Enterprise Services (CANES) program. Describing CANES as the network to the tactical edge, Adm. Branch noted that the endeavor “is a journey, and we won’t be done with that journey for a while.” The Navy needs the tactical cloud with reachback as well as maritime tactical command and control for a fused operational picture that will give the commander vital decision aids.

Rear Adm. Marshall B. Lytle, USCG, assistant commandant, command, control, communications, computers and information technology and commander, U.S. Coast Guard Cyber Command, noted that a commander does not yet have awareness of operational risk in cyber, which is needed. He also noted that, for port security, the Coast Guard must be able to network with state and local governments and industry, including international firms. This networking will require a partnership among all these entities.

When asked what he would do if he were able, Adm. Branch said he would make more investments in cybersecurity for networks. Adm. Lytle offered that he would strive to get to the promise and goals of the Joint Information Environment as quickly as possible in a secure environment.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
