<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Get Your Bot On: DARPA Challenges High School Students With Robotics Video Challenge </title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>February 11, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DARPA</tag>
    <tag>Robotics</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) is going back to high school—sort of. The research arm of the Defense Department launched a challenge for all high school students called Robots4Us, a video contest on societal implications of robotics.</abstract>
  <text>The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) is going back to high school—sort of. The research arm of the Defense Department launched a challenge for all high school students called Robots4Us, a video contest on societal implications of robotics.

Students are to focus on how robots could make a difference for society in the future. Students are to make a two- to three-minute video that shows the kind of robot-assisted society they would like to see.

The contest opened today, February 11, and the video entry deadline is April 1, no fooling.

DARPA’s challenge is open only to high school students grades 9 to 12 or home-schooled in the United States and U.S. territories. They can form teams of up to three students, or go it solo.

“Videos should consider both current and anticipated advances in robotics technologies and address the implications of those advances for individuals, workplaces and communities, as well as for national security and the ideals upon which American society is built,” reads the announcement. “In particular they should address the choices we will face as the nation and the world strive to reap the benefits of the robotics revolution while minimizing the potential for harm.”

Five winners will be selected to attend the DARPA Robotics Challenge Finals held June 5 and 6 in Pomona, California, (and yes, an adult must accompany each of the winners. For that, there’s no going it alone.) </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Aaron Nicely, of RE2, manipulates the High Dexterity Robot to retrieve candy from a bag at the Naval Future Force Science and Technology Expo.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
