<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Missile Defense Agency Modifies C2BMC Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 25, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Ballistic Missile Defense System</tag>
    <tag>Missile Defense Agency</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lockheed Martin has been awarded a contract modification for the continued engineering, development, test, integration, fielding and on-site operations and sustainment support for the Command and Control, Battle Management and Communications (C2BMC) system located worldwide for the Ballistic Missile Defense System.</abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Corp., Gaithersburg, Maryland, has been awarded a maximum $129,000,000 modification (P00034) to previously awarded HQ0147-12-D-0003 for the continued engineering, development, test, integration, fielding and on-site operations and sustainment support for the Command and Control, Battle Management and Communications (C2BMC) system located worldwide for the Ballistic Missile Defense System. This is a hybrid cost-plus-fixed-fee, cost-plus-incentive-fee, cost-plus-award-fee, fixed-price incentive, firm-fixed-price indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract. The modification brings the total cumulative face value of the contract to $1,203,500,000 from $1,074,500,000. Locations of performance are Arlington, Virginia, Huntsville, Alabama, and Colorado Springs, Colorado, with an expected completion date of Jan. 26, 2018. Fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation funds will be obligated incrementally against the task orders. The Missile Defense Agency, Huntsville, Alabama, is the buying activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>The guided-missile destroyer USS Fitzgerald (DDG 62) launches a Standard Missile-3 (SM-3) as apart of a joint ballistic missile defense exercise. The Missile Defense Agency has awarded Lockheed Martin a $129 million contract modification for work on the Command and Control, Battle Management and Communications system.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
