<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Leverage and Monetize Your Conference Investment</title>
  <author>Joyce Bosc</author>
  <date>March 3, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Event Coverage</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Guest Blogs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Guest blogger Joyce Bosc, from Boscobel Marketing Communications, outlines some steps companies can use to get the most out of exhibiting at a conference.  </abstract>
  <text>With fewer government workers and contractors attending conferences and events, companies that do decide to exhibit at a conference need to maximize their investments. Here are some tips to take advantage of, and capitalize on, the lead generation and thought leadership opportunities that exhibiting provides.

Social Media
Government currently drives the use of social media. Federal workers constantly turn to it to get information. So use an inbound marketing approach and announce your presence at an event. To make it worthwhile for attendees, offer an informative giveaway, such as an ebook or white paper, to those who stop by your booth.

Then, use social media to share what you’re learning at the conference. Photos always help, but make sure to use the appropriate hashtags. An event should make the hashtag readily available via social media activities and on event signage.

Pick a Persona
Determine the type of person who attends the shows. Are they technologists? Are they acquisition staff? Are they decisions makers? Make sure your content, signage and other materials speak directly to them so your message resonates.

Make a Splash, ahem, Announcement
First, look inward to determine if the conference is the appropriate place to make an announcement. Sometimes, an announcement’s scope and theme will dictate this decision. If heavily attended by the market, then the press most likely will attend. Therefore, it is a good idea to issue a substantive news release to establish (or build) your thought leadership in that community.

Measure ROI
How will you know whether an event is worth attending again? Plan ahead and set goals so you can measure the return on investment. Track things such as the prospect capture rate and partnership development, both during and after the show. Remember, most of the tangible results of a show happen post-tradeshow. Have a good follow-up strategy, and you’ll get a better sense of how to budget for future events.

Share the Knowledge
A good conference will give you the opportunity to collaborate and share information with current and prospective customers and partners. It will also provide forums and panel discussions that will inform and educate. Take what you learn and figure out the best way to share it. No matter if it’s a white paper, infographic or blog, you have plenty of avenues to establish your thought leadership. Take advantage of them.

With the AFCEA Homeland Security Conference right around the corner, it’s important to have tactics in place to help you get the most ROI out of your investment and drive home your thought leadership expertise.

Joyce Bosc is president and CEO of Boscobel Marketing Communications Incorporated, founded in 1978. She currently provides a full range of marketing and digital communications for government contractors, high-tech companies, associations, federal, state and local governments, real estate and utility companies.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
