<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Two Firms Awarded Interoperability Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 25, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lafayette Group Inc., Vienna, Virginia, is being awarded a potential $92,739,725 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee multiple award contract (N66001-15-D-0028) to provide technical assistance as well as research and development for the advancement of interoperable communications to federal, state, local, tribal and non-governmental entities, and to support other command, control, communications, computers and intelligence efforts. Science Applications International Corporation (SAIC), McLean, Virginia, is being awarded a potential $83,818,576 contract (N66001-15-D-0029). Each awardee will have the opportunity to compete for task orders during the ordering period. This five-year contract includes no options periods. Work will be performed in Vienna (50 percent), and at government facilities throughout the United States and its territories (50 percent). Work is expected to be completed March 22, 2019. No funds will be obligated at the time of award. Funding will be obligated via task orders as they are issued. The types of funding to be obligated include operation and maintenance (Navy) and interagency agreements through federal agencies such as the Department of Homeland Security and the Department of Commerce. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via Request for Proposal N66001-13-R-0006 published on the Federal Business Opportunities website, and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website, with two offers received. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
