<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Boeing to Support International Multiplex Systems Program</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 25, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Boeing Company, Huntington Beach, California, is being awarded a $12,878,533 cost-plus-incentive-fee contract to provide design agent and technical engineering services in support of the AN/USQ-82(V) Gigabit Ethernet Data Multiplex Systems (GEDMS) program. GEDMS is a third-generation shipboard network used for DDG 51 class destroyers. The GEDMS transfers inputs and/or outputs for the machinery control systems, damage control system, steering control system, AEGIS combat system, navigation displays and interior communications alarms and indicators. This contract includes options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to $39,991,521.This contract combines purchases for the Navy (91 percent) and the governments of Australia (3 percent), Korea (3 percent) and Japan (3 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales Program. The work will be performed in Huntington Beach, (72 percent); Arlington, Virginia (11 percent); Bath, Maine (9 percent); Pascagoula, Mississippi (3 percent); Georgetown in Washington, D.C. (3 percent); Richardson, Texas (1 percent); and Fairfax, Virginia (1 percent), and is expected to be completed by March 2016. Fiscal 2014 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) funding in the amount of $3,179,520 will be obligated at time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured in accordance with authority FAR 6.302-1(a)(2)(iii)–only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements. The Naval Surface Warfare Center, Dahlgren Division, Dahlgren, Virginia, is the contracting activity (N00178-15-C-2016).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
