<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Three Firms Provide Tactical Data Link Support</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 27, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>data link systems</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Tactical Engineering &amp; Analysis Inc., San Diego, is being awarded a potential $19,651,998 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract (N66001-15-D-0073) to provide tactical data link systems support to include research; systems engineering; software engineering; configuration management; human factors engineering for software design; system level hardware and software integration; test analysis and reporting; and quality assurance support. Computer Sciences Corp., San Diego, is being awarded a potential $17,844,438 contract (N66001-15-D-0072), and Odyssey Systems Consulting Group, Wakefield, Massachusetts, is being awarded a potential $16,023,035 contract (N66001-15-D-0074). Each awardee will have the opportunity to compete for task orders during the ordering period. The three-year contracts include one two-year options periods, which if exercised, would bring the total contract values to $33,275,314, $30,136,398 and $27,128,654 respectively. 

No funding will be obligated at the time of award. Funding will be obligated via task orders are issued. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The types of funding to be obligated include research, development, test and evaluation, foreign military sales, and operations and maintenance (Navy). This contract was competitively procured via full and open solicitation via publication on the Federal Business Opportunities website and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website, with four proposals received and three were selected for award. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
