<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon to Support Aegis Modernization</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 30, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Aegis weapon system</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Integrated Defense Systems, Sudbury, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $16,663,927 firm-fixed-price delivery order under previously awarded basic ordering agreement (N00024-14-G-5105) for fiscal 2015 Aegis modernization production requirements. This delivery order covers the production of Multi-Mission Signal Processor Ordnance Alteration (ORDALT) kits, kill assessment system ORDALT kits and spares, radio frequency coherent combiner kits, high voltage power supply sidewall capacitors, traveling waves tube monitoring circuits, and stabilized master oscillator ORDALT kits, as well as test and installation efforts, in support of the Aegis Modernization (AMOD) program. The AMOD program fields combat system upgrades that will enhance the anti-air warfare and Ballistic Missile Defense capabilities of Aegis-equipped Arleigh Burke-class destroyers and Ticonderoga-class cruisers.

This delivery order includes options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this delivery order to $24,821,438. Work will be performed in Norfolk, Virginia (42 percent); Andover, Massachusetts (38 percent); Burlington, Massachusetts (12 percent); and Sudbury, Massachusetts (8 percent), and is expected to be completed by May 2017. Fiscal 2015 other procurement (Navy); fiscal 2015 Defense-wide procurement and fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation funding in the amount of $16,663,927 will be obligated at the time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity.? 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
