<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Supports Dual Band Radar</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 2, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Wallops Island</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Integrated Defense Systems, Tewksbury, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $26,917,593 cost-plus-fixed-fee design agent contract to provide level-of-effort support for the development environment infrastructure that supports the complete development, verification and support of the CVN 78 Dual Band Radar (DBR) and support of testing to be accomplished at Wallops Island Engineering Test Center Land Based Test Site. This radar suite is a single, integrated radar system combining the AN/SPY-3 Multi-Function Radar at X-Band and AN/SPY-4 Volume Search Radar at S-Band. This radar suite is a state of the art, high performance radar system with self-defense anti-aircraft warfare mission. The design agent contract described is intended to provide the engineering services necessary to fully mitigate numerous system integration schedule risks that are being tracked by the DBR program. This contract will provide services necessary to conduct follow on software interface development efforts to resolve software trouble reports discovered during land based and at-sea testing. This contract includes options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to $50,821,247.  

Work will be performed in Sudbury, Massachusetts (86 percent); Moorestown, New Jersey (9 percent); and Burlington, Massachusetts (5 percent), and is expected to be completed by December 2015. Fiscal 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) and fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation funding in the amount of $11,602,288 will be obligated at the time of contract award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year.  This contract was not competitively procured in accordance with authority FAR 6.302-1(a)(2)(iii) - only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity (N00024-15-C-5335).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
