<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Companies to Support ISR Research and Development</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 15, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Alion Science and Technology, Rome, New York (N00164-15-D-JT04); BAE Systems Inc., Rockville, Maryland (N00164-15-D-JT05); Charles Stark Draper Laboratory, Cambridge, Massachusetts (N00164-15-D-JT06); DigitalGlobe Inc., Herndon, Virginia (N00164-15-D-JT03); Exelis Inc., Clifton, New Jersey (N00164-15-D-JT01); G3 Technologies, Columbia, Maryland (N00164-15-D-JT02); Herrick Technology Laboratory, Germantown, Maryland (N00164-15-D-JT97); The HumanGeo Group LLC, Arlington, Virginia (N00164-15-D-JT95); LEIDOS, Reston, Virginia (N00164-15-D-JT94); NAL Research Corp., Manassas, Virginia (N00164-15-D-JT96); Northrop Grumman Xetron, Cincinnati, Ohio (N00164-15-D-JT81); Scientific Research Corp., North Charleston, South Carolina (N00164-15-D-JT99); and Southwest Research Institute, San Antonio, Texas (N00164-15-D-JT98), are each being awarded a combined aggregate not-to-exceed $49,000,000 fixed-price, cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity multiple award contract to support research and development of special intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance components and systems.

Each of the 13 contractors will have the opportunity to bid on individual delivery orders as they are issued. Work will be performed in Rome, New York; Rockville, Maryland; Cambridge, Massachusetts; Herndon, Virginia; Clifton, New Jersey; Columbia, Maryland; Germantown, Maryland; Arlington, Virginia; Reston, Virginia; Manassas, Virginia; Cincinnati, Ohio; North Charleston, South Carolina; and San Antonio, Texas. Work is expected to be completed April 2020. Working capital funds in the amount of $1,300 will be obligated at the time of award, with each contractor receiving $100 at time of award. Contract funding will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via the Federal Business Opportunities website, with 15 offers received. The Naval Surface Warfare Center Crane, Crane, Indiana, is the contracting activity.
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
