<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>3E Technologies Awarded Critical Infrastructure Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 17, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>3E Technologies International Inc., Rockville, Maryland, is being awarded a $9,995,697 modification to previously awarded contract (N00174-10-D-0021) for work on Navy-wide Critical Infrastructure Control and Monitoring System (CICMS) interface to Navy Virtual Perimeter Monitoring System for a Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase III project. This increase provides for the implementation of the CICMS at Navy facilities beyond the originally identified Naval District Washington's boundaries. This increase supports the Navy Region Southeast and Navy Region Hawaii for integration on shore-based facilities. This contract modification is being issued under 10 U.S.C. 2304(b)(2), as implemented by FAR 6.302-5 Authorized or Required by Statute. The statutory authority for this SBIR Phase III increase in ceiling is 15 U.S.C. 638(r). Work will be performed in Hawaii (50 percent); Dahlgren, Virginia (8.34 percent); San Diego (8.34 percent); Indian Head, Maryland (8.33 percent); Annapolis, Maryland (8.33 percent); Patuxent River, Maryland (8.33 percent); and Washington, D.C. (8.33 percent). The work is expected to be completed by September 2015. Fiscal 2015 operations and maintenance (Navy) and fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation funding in the amount of $2,900,746 will be obligated at the time of award. Contract funds in the amount of $2,774,670 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Surface Warfare Center, Indian Head Explosive Ordnance Disposal Technology Division, Indian Head, Maryland, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
