<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Avaya Government Solutions Funds AFCEA STEM Scholarships</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 1, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>STEM Education</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Avaya Government Solutions is committed to helping the next generation of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) professionals with a $25,000 gift to the AFCEA Educational Foundation’s STEM scholarships and grants programs for 2015.</abstract>
  <text>Avaya Government Solutions is committed to helping the next generation of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) professionals with a $25,000 gift to the AFCEA Educational Foundation’s STEM scholarships and grants programs for 2015.

Five STEM Majors scholarships will be awarded to deserving undergraduate and graduate students majoring in fields related to the mission of AFCEA Educational Foundation. In addition to STEM Majors scholarships, one War Veterans Scholarship will be awarded to an active-duty or honorably discharged veteran of the Enduring Freedom-Afghanistan and/or Iraqi Freedom operations pursuing a STEM-related undergraduate degree.

Avaya also is supporting STEM teachers, providing two Gravely Grants for two STEM teachers in the Washington, D.C., metropolitan area to help promote STEM innovation in the classrooms. The Gravely Grants will help augment the budget for student programs such as robotics clubs, cyber clubs and other activities that promote STEM to students.

“Our Avaya Government Solutions team knows the importance of developing future leaders, which makes our support of AFCEA an especially great fit,” says Susan Pompliano Keys, vice president, Avaya Government Solutions Sales. “During its more than 30-year history, the AFCEA Educational Foundation has helped hundreds of deserving individuals earn degrees in fields that are vital to our defense, intelligence and homeland security communities. We are delighted to make an investment in our nation’s future by helping deserving students further their education and learn critical new skills.”

“The AFCEA Educational Foundation is very grateful for the generous donation from Avaya Government Solutions in support of STEM education,” says Dr. Vincent Patton, the foundation’s executive director. “With the continued support of AFCEA members like Avaya Government Solutions, the foundation will be able to provide opportunities and assistance to students interested in cybersecurity, intelligence and other fields that support the mission of AFCEA and the AFCEA Educational Foundation.”

Avaya Government Solutions is a long-time member and supporter of AFCEA, known for communication and networking solutions that help the U.S. Defense Department and other federal government agencies work more efficiently and effectively.

Avaya-funded scholarships will support students majoring in telecommunications and engineering; network engineering; information technology; network security; information science; computer systems; and cybersecurity.
The AFCEA Educational Foundation scholarships are awarded annually in the spring and the fall. To learn more about AFCEA Educational Foundation scholarship and grant opportunities, visit www.afcea.org/education.

About Avaya Government Solutions
Avaya Government Solutions is a leading global provider of next-generation collaboration and communications solutions that engage people across multiple channels and devices. Avaya Government Solutions offers communication and engagement solutions to support citizens, government employees and warfighters. With Avaya’s technology and professional services team, agencies can bring the right people together with the right information at the right time. For more information, visit www.avayagov.com.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
