<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Commerce Department to Lead Cybersecurity Trade Delegation</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>May 1, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>International</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Cybersecurity</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Twenty companies will participate in a trade mission with Romania and Poland.</abstract>
  <text>U.S. Deputy Secretary of Commerce Bruce Andrews announced today he will lead a delegation of 20 American companies on a Cybersecurity Trade Mission to Bucharest, Romania, and Warsaw, Poland, May 11-15. Assistant Secretary for Industry and Analysis Marcus Jadotte also will participate in the mission.

The trade mission is designed to help U.S. companies launch or increase their business operations in Central and Southeast Europe, specifically connecting them with businesses and government leaders in Romania and Poland. It also will introduce or expand the market presence of U.S. cybersecurity companies.

“This trade mission is part of our commitment to combatting the growing threat of cyberthreats and protecting critical infrastructure in the U.S. and among our European allies,” said Deputy Secretary Andrews in a written statement. “U.S. cybersecurity firms are world leaders, providing cutting-edge technologies, products and services all over the globe. Through this trade mission, we will have the opportunity to share best practices and collaborate to combat and protect against cyber attacks, while strengthening bilateral ties with Romania and Poland, two strategic and economic U.S. partners in the region.”

The following companies will join the trade mission: Cask LLC, San Diego;  Cisco Systems, Washington, D.C.; Creative Information Technology Inc. (CITI) and CSC, both in Falls Church, Virginia; CyberPoint International LLC, Baltimore; DataLocker, Overland Park, Kansas; F5 Networks, Seattle; Fidelis Cybersecurity, Waltham, Massachusetts; FireEye, Reston, Virginia; General Dynamics Information Technology, Fairfax, Virginia; Glimmerglass Cyber Solutions, Hayward, California; Hewlett Packard, Palo Alto, California; IBM, Armonk, New York; Information Unlimited, Washington, D.C.; Lockheed Martin, Oakton, Virginia; Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington; Oracle, Redwood Shores, California; Palo Alto Networks, Santa Clara, California; Raytheon IIS, Dulles, Virginia; and WhiteHat Security Ltd., Santa Clara, California.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
