<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>The Complexity of Things (CoT)</title>
  <author>David E. Meadows</author>
  <date>May 19, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Technology</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Internet of Things</tag>
    <tag>artificial intelligence</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>As the Internet of Things takes shape, it will generate a new phenomenon—the Complexity of Things.</abstract>
  <text>In my earlier blog about artificial intelligence, I touched on the growing interconnectivity of the Internet of Things (IoT) and how it provides a pathway for connecting technology. The IoT concept envisions all technology in the information technology enterprise being connected on a global scale. Unfortunately, such a complex architecture will affect the individual components of technology and how information is protected. Extrapolated, it means that protecting information is unattainable.

Think about how rapidly information technology requires the user—or even information technology products—to react to a changing technological environment. Then think of your Global Positioning System (GPS). The GPS in your car works great, because even in an area with lots of road construction, it is not really worth the effort or cost to change the software. Why? Because change associated with a brick and mortar road map is accomplished within a stasis timeline where humans live and are able to manage.

But that is not necessarily so for the IoT. Your information technology road map will never achieve such stasis. It always will be in transition and change. Also, human interface will be through technology. And, some of those changes, as we enter the quantum technology age, will move at near-speed of light … simultaneously.

In Louis L’Amour’s 1984 book, “The Walking Drum,” the protagonist Mathurin Kerbouchard commented during a philosophical argument that “... The one law of the universe seems to be change. Everything is in a state of flux, and it is better so.” By the way, didn’t George Orwell write a book titled “1984” in 1948? What is this about the numbers 4 and 8, or 8 and 4?

The IoT brings with it a Complexity of Things (CoT). This CoT is created by millions and millions of disparate information technologies riding the IoT network. The IoT is basically a lineal growth pattern architecture. Technology is connected to it with the IoT attempting to adjust accordingly. Unfortunately, the IoT is powered by a world of oscillating CoTs caused by technology that is changing exponentially within timelines of varying degrees of flux.

Another way of thinking of this is using the universe. The CoT can be thought of as the power that exploded the universe, while the IoT represents the celestial bodies that are riding the expansion forever amidst change and flux. Wherever we look, we are seeing something that already has happened.

Software, hardware, policies, doctrines and work force skills are a few basics that will convolute the ever-increasing pace that the IoT brings with it. This ever-growing bow wave of information technology innovation, connectivity and scientific discoveries will increase the CoT further regardless of what steps are taken to reduce it.

Regarding statistics: do you remember that ancient art of management theories? The story is there are three ways of avoiding the truth: lies, half-truths and statistics. A total of 68 percent of statistics are made up on the spot—such as this one.

But statistically, in the IoT world, constant change and an oscillating information technology flux of CoT bring with it a never-ending challenge of protecting information. The more complex the information technology backbone upon which technology resides and rides is an ever-evolving range stretching along the IoT dotted with a multitude of overlapping security issues. Cybersecurity never can be obtained within the technological world of the IoT because of the CoT.     

Some may say that quantum technology will be the answer to cybersecurity, but when quantum technology becomes readily available it too will connect to the IoT enwrapped by the CoT. And sitting in the wings, rubbing its hands together, waiting, is the threat of artificial intelligence.

Risk management highlighted in Department of Defense Instruction (DODI) 8500.01 titled “Cybersecurity” and dated March 14, 2014 appears to be a well-written operational concept. It provides for protecting critical information/technologies through managing risk, which hopefully will assure survivability of the essential elements of national security. But, DODI 8500.01 has too many cooks in the kitchen.

To win, you have got to get ahead of change.

David E. Meadows, MBA, MS, is the author of “The Sixth Fleet.”</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
