<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>ViaSat Awarded More Than $478 Million for JTRS Terminals </title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 29, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Joint Tactical Radio System</tag>
    <tag>Multifunctional Information Distribution System</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>ViaSat Inc., Carlsbad, California, is being awarded a maximum potential $478,600,000 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract (N00039-15-D-0008) for the production, development and sustainment of the Multifunctional Information Distribution System (MIDS) Joint Tactical Radio Systems (JTRS) terminals. The MIDS JTRS terminal is a four-channel software defined radio that delivers existing Link 16 with concurrent multi-netting-4 and tactical air navigation functionality, as well as three channels for future growth, including JTRS advanced networking waveforms such as tactical targeting network technology, multifunction advanced data link, intra-flight data link and other advanced networking waveforms. The MIDS JTRS terminal is a line-of-sight radio system for collecting and transmitting broadband, jam-resistant, secure data and voice across a variety of air, sea and ground platforms. The MIDS program office mission is to develop, field and support interoperable, affordable and secure MIDS tactical data link and programmable networking technologies and capabilities for the joint, coalition and international warfighter. Work will be performed in Carlsbad, California, and work is expected to be completed May 27, 2020. Fiscal 2015 operations and maintenance funds in the amount of $1,000,000 will be placed on contract and obligated on the first task order concurrent with contract award, which will meet the minimum order requirement. Funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract is expected to combine purchases for the Navy and potentially other U.S. armed services (99 percent) and various other governments—Austria, Chile, Finland, Israel, Jordan, Japan, Kuwait, Malaysia, Morocco, Oman, Pakistan, Qatar, South Korea, Saudi Arabia, Singapore, Sweden, Switzerland, Taiwan, Thailand, United Arab Emirates, Australia, Canada, New Zealand, United Kingdom, NATO and all NATO nations (1 percent), under the Foreign Military Sales program. This contract was not competitively procured because it is a follow-on, sole-source, multiple-award procurement in accordance with 10 U.S.C. 2304(c)(1)—only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements, as implemented by FAR Subpart 6.302-1. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, is the contracting activity (N00039-15-D-0008).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
