<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Engility to Support Multiple Nations</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 29, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Engility Corp., Chantilly, Virginia, is being awarded a $23,939,937 modification to a previously awarded cost-plus-fixed-fee contract (N00421-14-C-0021) for additional systems engineering and technical services. This modification includes systems integration and software development, platform simulation, integration and laboratory engineering, and software engineering. These services are in support of the U.S. Navy and governments of Thailand, Taiwan, Norway, Australia, United Kingdom, Brazil, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Japan, Pakistan and South Korea. Work will be performed in Patuxent River, Maryland (84 percent); China Lake, California (5 percent); Point Mugu, California (5 percent); Jacksonville, Florida (2.5 percent); Orlando, Florida ( 2.5 percent); various locations within the continental U.S. (0.5 percent) and various locations outside the continental U.S. (0.5 percent), and is expected to be completed in February 2016. Fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy), fiscal 2015 aircraft procurement (Navy), fiscal 2015 working capital (Navy), and fiscal 2015 operations and maintenance (Navy) funds, as well as Foreign Military Sales funds in the amount of $9,404,152 are being obligated on this award, $1,217,466 of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract combines purchases for the Navy ($23,124,684; 96.5 percent); and the governments of Taiwan ($359,099; 1.5 percent); Thailand ($239,399; 1 percent); Norway ($108,378, 0.46 percent); Australia ($15,483, 0.06 percent); United Kingdom ($30,965, 0.14 percent); Brazil ($8,847, 0.05 percent); Canada ($8,847, 0.05 percent); Denmark ($8,847, 0.05 percent); Germany ($8,847, 0.05 percent); Japan ($8,847, 0.05 percent); Pakistan ($8,847, 0.05 percent); and South Korea ($8,847, 0.05 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales program. The Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Patuxent River, Maryland, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
