<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>The Bottom Line: Three Excellent Reasons to Go on Vacation</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>June 9, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>productivity</tag>
    <tag>The Bottom Line</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Technology is a wonderful way to stay in touch, but it’s summer and time to put gadgets away for a bit. Whether you live in a region with year-round sunshine or brutal winters, taking those paid vacation days benefits not just you and your family but also the economy.</abstract>
  <text>Technology is a wonderful way to stay in touch, but it’s summer and time to put gadgets away for a bit. Whether you live in a region with year-round sunshine or brutal winters, taking those paid vacation days benefits not just you and your family but also the economy.

Do it for your health. An annual vacation can reduce the risk of having a heart attack by 50 percent. Vacationers also report getting three times more deep sleep after returning home. Getting away from the office decreases stress and increases recuperative powers, reducing the number of sick days used annually.

Increase your productivity. According to Elizabeth Scott, stress management expert, workers who take regular time off are less likely to experience burnout. As a result, they are more creative than their overworked counterparts. In addition, vacations increase quality of life, which leads to better quality of performance on the job.

Boost the economy. Whether you choose a vacation or a staycation, chances are you’ll spend a bit more money than while working. Perhaps you’ll purchase the supplies you need for that project you never seem to have time or energy to tackle. Or you may go out on the town and dine at restaurants, stay at a hotel or shop at boutiques. Your vacation dollars support every layer of the economy—from farmers to waitstaff to businesses large and small.

Afraid taking time off will make you appear less industrious than other staff members? Think a vacation could affect your chances of getting a raise or bonus this year? Think again. According to a study Oxford Economics conducted last year, employees who forfeit paid time off do not receive raises or bonuses at a faster rate than those who take all of their vacation time.

The bottom line is that getting away from the office, factory or highway offers only benefits for both you and your employer. Don’t put it off. You both deserve the best.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
