<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Sum Will Be Greater Than the Parts</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>June 9, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Technology</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>science and technology</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Sandia National Laboratories and the Georgia Institute of Technology signed a five-year memorandum of understanding that enables them to collaboratively solve science and technology problems of national importance.</abstract>
  <text>Sandia National Laboratories and the Georgia Institute of Technology signed a five-year memorandum of understanding (MOU) that enables them to collaboratively solve science and technology problems of national importance. Among the goals of the partnering agreement are to solve major national problems; to engage talented researchers to work on practical, complex problems early in their academic careers; and to introduce new ideas and technologies into the marketplace through jointly developed intellectual property. 

G.P. “Bud” Peterson, Georgia Tech’s president, says the MOU furthers his institution’s research strategy, which focuses on pursuing transformative research, strengthening collaborative relationships and maximizing the economic and societal impact of its research.

Sandia and Georgia Tech researchers are interested in energy and grid security, advanced manufacturing and computer science and data analytics, among other topics. The two institutions have been collaborating for many years. Most recently, their scientists have focused on advanced computer architectures, energy systems, manufacturing and materials science.

Georgia Tech, known for its ability to break down traditional academic barriers and assemble interdisciplinary teams, combined with Sandia’s scientific research and systems engineering approach will enable both organizations to take multidisciplinary approaches to solving problems and developing new technologies.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Sandia researchers work with new imaging techniques to view cell-level activity with unprecedented detail. (By Randy Montoya) </img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
