<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Contracts</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>January 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Robots for the ArmyThe U.S. Army can order up to 3,000 military robots, spare parts, training and repair services over the next five years under a new agreement. In the past, the Army has deployed robots in combat in limited numbers and only to explosive ordnance device specialists. Now the service is broadening the deployment of robots to general infantry forces for a variety of critical missions. The first 101 robots are being delivered for urgent deployment. The robots, PackBot 510 with FasTac Kit, are smaller and lighter than the original PackBot 510, with a robust gripper and an observation mast equipped with a low-light-capable zoom camera. iRobot Corporation received the $286 million indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract from the U.S. Army Program Executive Office for Simulation, Training and Instrumentation on behalf of the Robotic Systems Joint Project Office at Redstone Arsenal, Alabama.Communications for Navy in CaliforniaMultiple radio frequency and satellite communications programs and projects will be provided through In-Service Engineering Agent support. The work includes assistance in the areas of management, engineering, technical, logistics, fabrication and installation for integrated and nonintegrated shipboard installations of super high frequency, extremely high frequency and ultrahigh frequency radio and satellite communications. Centurum Incorporated won the indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract worth up to $84 million to provide the services to the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center in San Diego. The award has one base year with four option years. The contract was procured competitively with proposals solicited on an unrestricted basis via the Federal Business Opportunities Web site and the Space and Naval Warfare e-Commerce Central Web site. System Will Know Status of Army AssetsA new enterprise system that is capable of providing the current status of all U.S. Army equipment and assets is being implemented. The technology will enable soldiers to best anticipate, allocate and manage the flow of available resources. Work on the project includes re-engineering current tactical logistics Standard Army Management Information Systems. When fully fielded, the system will support U.S. Army, National Guard and reserve component troops worldwide. It is a key element of the Army’s larger vision of integrating major logistics processes and systems and will be crucial to managing logistical assets of future programs such as the Joint Light Tactical Vehicle. Northrop Grumman is the prime contractor on the Global Combat Support System–Army (Field/Tactical) program. The company received $10 million in initial funding on the cost-plus-fixed-fee task order, which is valued at up to $600 million over seven years. The task order was issued through the Information Technology Enterprise Solutions–2 Services indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract. Teamed with Northrop Grumman are IBM Global Services, Bethesda, Maryland; Computer Sciences Corporation, El Segundo, California; Joint Logistics Managers Incorporated, Prince George, Virginia; and SAP America, Newton Square, Pennsylvania. NASA Awards Data ContractsFour contracts for advanced data acquisition and analysis systems for a variety of satellite, rocket and aviation testing applications have been awarded. As part of the agreements, the data acquisition product Piranha III will be delivered to the following NASA locations: The NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory has ordered a 64-channel Piranha III system to augment work in shock and vibration testing of satellites and space vehicles. The NASA Langley Research Center will take delivery of a 288-channel system with integrated signal conditioning for environmental testing of rockets and wind tunnel testing of aircraft components. The NASA Glenn Research Center will receive a 640-channel system for advanced spaceflight systems applications. Finally, the NASA Marshall Space Flight Center will acquire a 224-channel system for space shuttle and space station testing. DSPCon Incorporated will supply the Piranhas IIIs, the company’s flagship data acquisition product, for an undisclosed amount. WIN-T Equipment Ordered Under CHS-3Military hardware and software, including computers and network equipment, have been ordered for the U.S. Army’s Warfighter Information Network–Tactical (WIN-T) program. The order is on the Common Hardware/Software 3 (CHS-3) contract vehicle that enables U.S. military and government agencies to access the latest commercial computer and networking advancements in an effort to establish common hardware and software computing platforms and networks throughout the battlefield. CHS-3 is an indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract with a potential value of $2 billion over the contract’s 10-year life. The CHS-3 product line includes rugged local area networks, server platforms, communication gateways, routers, laptops, faxes and various ancillary equipment including vehicle mounts, cables and operational transit cases. Also available are extensive system integration, product-testing services, end-user support and program management. CHS-3 prime contractor General Dynamics C4 Systems received the recent WIN-T order, which is valued at $75 million. The Army Communications–Electronics Life Cycle Management Command is the lead contract authority for CHS-3. NATO Surveillance in AfghanistanNATO forces in Afghanistan will have better protection with a new tower-based, elevated persistent surveillance capability. Enhanced surveillance systems equipment and all logistics support services required to keep the systems operational will be provided. The technology has similarities to Rapid Aerostat Initial Deployment (RAID) systems currently deployed by the U.S. Army in Iraq and Afghanistan. RAID consists of infrared and other sensor systems, elevated on a stationary platform, capable of detecting hostile troop and equipment movement from great distances. The capability enables U.S. and coalition forces to respond rapidly to threats. Raytheon Company won the $5.3 million contract awarded by the NATO Maintenance and Supply Agency. Raytheon will perform the work at its Integrated Defense Systems’ IntegratedAirDefenseCenter, Andover, Massachusetts, and at Raytheon's WarfighterProtectionCenter, Huntsville, Alabama.CREW System DevelopmentDesign, development and delivery of seven development models for Spiral 3.1 dismounted and seven development models for Spiral 3.2 Mounted Counter Radio-Controlled Improvised Explosive Device (RCIED) Electronic Warfare (CREW) systems is underway, including engineering support services, training, maintenance and repair. The mounted CREW systems are two elements of the U.S. Defense Department’s Joint Counter RCIED Electronic Warfare program. Spiral 3.1 CREW systems are dismounted electronic jammers designed to prevent the initiation of RCIEDs. Spiral 3.2 CREW systems have the same purpose but are mounted. This work will advance CREW technology and bridge the capability gap between current systems and future systems. Northrop Grumman Space and Mission Systems Corporation, Network Communications Division, San Diego, won the $16 million cost-plus-award-fee, firm-fixed-price and cost-only contract. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington Navy Yard, D.C., is the contracting activity. Work should be completed by June 2009.Submit information about contract awards to signalnews@afcea.org.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
