<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Analytic Sciences to Provide Radar Support for Four Countries</title>
  <author/>
  <date>June 29, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Taiwan</tag>
    <tag>Poland</tag>
    <tag>Korea</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Analytic Sciences Corp. Inc., Andover, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $35,445,651 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for radar engineering and logistics services in support of Naval Surface Warfare Center, Port Hueneme Division, Ship Defense and Expeditionary Warfare Department, Virginia Beach Detachment. The services include in-service engineering and acquisition engineering; integrated logistics support; software support; installation services, support, and coordination; programmatic and project management support; and staging facility support. This contract includes options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to $53,151,290. This contract combines purchases for the Navy (99 percent), and the governments of Taiwan, Poland and Korea (1 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales program. Work will be performed in Virginia Beach, Virginia (60 percent); San Diego (10 percent); Bremerton, Washington (10 percent), Honolulu (10 percent); Newport, Rhode Island (9 percent); and ports outside of the U.S. (1 percent), and is expected to be completed by April 2016. Fiscal 2015 other procurement (Navy); fiscal 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy), fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation; and fiscal 2015 operations and maintenance (Navy) funding in the amount of $3,555,777 will be obligated at time of award, and funds in the amount of $282,000 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured in accordance with Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-1(a)(2)(iii)(B). The Naval Surface Warfare Center-Port Hueneme Division, Port Hueneme, California, is the contracting activity (N63394-15-C-0012).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
