<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Educational Foundation</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>January 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>
	Foundation Works Behind the Scenes in Preparation for West
One of the highlights of West 2008 in San Diego, which will take place February 5-7, and is co-sponsored by the U.S. Naval Institute (USNI) and AFCEA, is the recognition of outstanding and deserving individuals during the event. The Educational Foundation plays a part in this process by supporting the selection process for the Copernicus Award winners and the Enlisted Superior Performer award recipients. 
The late Vice Adm. Art Cebrowski, USN, who was the Navy N6 in 1997, conceived of the Copernicus Award. The name for the award came from the Copernicus Architecture used as the blueprint for the future C4I structure of the Navy. Recipients are selected based on a major accomplishment in a C4I/information technology-related job. Each year, U.S. naval personnel review applications from the Department of the Navy and the U.S. Coast Guard, including active duty and civilians, and select the award winners. The Educational Foundation works with a representative from the Office of the Chief of Naval Operations to ensure timely nominations and then coordinates official notifications to the award recipients. This year, Lt. Cmdr. Erik G. Pittman, USN, a member of Vice Adm. Mark Edwards' N6 staff, played this pivotal role in the Copernicus Award process.
Winners are invited to attend West along with their commanding officers and their respective spouse or special guest. Copernicus winners receive their awards and are recognized during a special awards ceremony prior to the Awards Reception and Dinner held this year on February 5. The U.S. Naval Institute and AFCEA are honored to recognize individuals who continue to demonstrate in operations that Copernicus remains relevant today. 
The West Enlisted Superior Performer (ESP) awards recognize the service of members of the military who have been selected by their commands for particularly superior service during the past year. Award recipients along with their commanding officers and/or senior representatives are invited to attend a luncheon during West. 
Winners of the Copernicus and ESP awards receive a one-year membership in USNI and in AFCEA. Information and a list of previous winners are available on the Educational Foundation Web site. 
 

	PDC Courses Offered at West 2008
The AFCEAProfessionalDevelopmentCenter will offer three courses at West 2008:

		DoD Architecture Framework Implementation, February 4-8, 2008
		This is a major revision of the contents of the course to prepare participants in developing architectures conformant to DODAF 1.5.Course Coordinator: Dr. Alex Levis
	
		Military Satellite Communications in a Net-Centric Environment, February 5-7 &amp; 8, 2008This course is divided into two sessions: Unclassified February 5-7 and Secret February 8.The unclassified session is a prerequisite for the classified course.Course Coordinator: James A. Mazzei
	
		Government Contracting: Workshop for Engineers, Project Managers, Technical Representatives, Procurement Specialists, Contract Administrators, February 5-7, 2008The course is oriented to industry and government engineers and project managers, but also is beneficial to contracts administrators.Course Coordinator: Bill C. Giallourakis
 

	Education News
For the latest issue of the AFCEA Educational Foundation newsletter that features information about chapter activities as well as educational news and deadline information, visit www.afcea.org/education/scholarships/news.asp.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
