<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Assurance Technology to Develop Software Definable Radio Technology</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 20, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Naval Research Laboratory</tag>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Assurance Technology Corp., Carlisle, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $24,663,970 cost-plus-fixed-fee task order under the One Acquisition Solution for Integrated Services (OASIS) multiple award contract (N00173-15-F-6201) for research, development, and integration as it relates to software to develop software definable/reconfigurable systems (SDS) that respond to Navy, Defense Department, and national mission requirements with improved performance, capability, reliability, efficiency and life cycle cost. Specifically, this effort involves systems development, support and integration for SDS design tasking required in support of the Space Systems Development Department technology advancements, system requirements definition, architecture development, and the system and unit design, development and transition to operational use. Recent and current Naval Research Laboratory SDS programs include the Software Reconfigurable Payload and the Operationally Responsive Space Technology Demonstrator. These programs represent a core technology for the creation of radio transceivers/software defined payloads that are smaller, lighter and more flexible tactical systems. Advanced waveform development and porting advanced receiver design and implementation, as well as communications security and information assurance functions are required.

Work will be performed in Washington, D.C. (93 percent); and Carlisle, Massachusetts (7 percent), and work is expected to be completed July 13, 2020. Fiscal 2015 defense working capital funds in the amount of $2,035,641 are being obligated at the time of award. Funds in the amount of $110,000 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The contract was competitively procured in accordance with the Fair Opportunity Procedures at 16-505(b)(1)(iv) under RFP NOOJ73-15-R-SE02 via General Services Administration OASIS-Small Business. The Naval Research Laboratory Contracting Division issued this solicitation to Pool 4 of the GSA OASIS small contractors, which consists of 42 vendors. One offer was received. The Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity.? 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
