<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Foster the Next Generation of Innovators</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 1, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>STEM Education</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Each year, the AFCEA Educational Foundation and AFCEA International chapters provide more than $2 million in grants and scholarships to deserving undergraduate and graduate students in 24 various STEM-related degree programs in computer science, cybersecurity, information technology, telecommunications engineering, mathematics and other similar academic areas.</abstract>
  <text>As dependence on technology grows, the need for experts in the fields of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) increases. Equally important are ongoing discussions on whether academic institutions in the United States are turning out enough qualified graduates in the STEM disciplines. According to the most recent report from the U.S. Department of Commerce Economic and Statistics Administration, STEM workers drive innovation and competitiveness by generating new ideas, companies and industries. However, U.S. businesses continually voice concerns about the quality and availability of STEM workers.

This is where AFCEA International steps in to help cultivate tomorrow’s great thinkers. Each year, the AFCEA Educational Foundation and AFCEA International chapters provide more than $2 million in grants and scholarships to deserving undergraduate and graduate students in 24 various STEM-related degree programs in computer science, cybersecurity, information technology, telecommunications engineering, mathematics and other similar academic areas.

In fiscal year 2014, the AFCEA Educational Foundation alone awarded more than $75,000 in grants to science and mathematics teachers in grades six and above to support their classroom studies. The foundation, a Section 501(c)(3) charitable organization, wants to emphasize efforts at increasing these classroom grants in the future.

Promoting education is a long-standing tradition for AFCEA, dating back to its establishment in 1946, when founder Brig. Gen. David Sarnoff, USA, stated, “Our preparation for future innovation in technology begins with planting the seed of knowledge to those who want to experience the challenge of success.” The AFCEA Educational Foundation strives to continue his legacy through its mission of providing educational incentives and opportunities for people engaged in the STEM disciplines. These disciplines are focused on AFCEA’s core areas: information technology, cybersecurity, communications and electronics that support the defense, homeland security and intelligence communities. Maintaining focus on this important and valued mission requires strong support throughout the AFCEA family.

AFCEA International members are encouraged to make a financial contribution to help support the foundation’s mission of promoting STEM educational incentives. Member support will help the foundation raise the visibility of AFCEA’s overall mission across the globe. Consider becoming a member of the AFCEA Educational Foundation’s Leadership Society by making an annual contribution at one of the levels below:

Sarnoff    $5,000-plus
Boyes    $2,500 to $4,999
Gravely    $1,500 to $2,499
Renzi    $1,000 to $1,499

Give at www.afcea.org/education/donate, or send a check made out to AFCEA Educational Foundation to:

AFCEA Educational Foundation
4400 Fair Lakes Court
Fairfax, VA 22033

Donations also can be made through the United Way. The designation code for the AFCEA Educational Foundation is 9604. For Combined Federal Campaign donations, the designation code is 78176.

Each tax-deductible, unrestricted donation will greatly support the foundation’s efforts to continue its proactive work in STEM education programs. Invest today to ensure that tomorrow’s work force is strong and highly competitive and capable of handling the demands of future technology and innovation.

Contact the foundation directly at edfoundation@afcea.org or 703-631-6147 with any questions.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Students from Central Hardin High School in Cecilia, Kentucky, prepare their robotics entry for a Project Lead the Way (PLTW) competition. An AFCEA scholarship funded teacher training for PLTW—a leading provider of K-12 STEM programs—at the University</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
