<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Three Companies to Support Air Traffic Control</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 29, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>air traffic control</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Booz Allen Hamilton Engineering Services LLC, Linthicum, Maryland (N65236-15-D-4804); CSSI Inc., Washington, District of Columbia (N65236-15-D-4805); and SERCO Inc., Reston, Virginia (N65236-15-D-4806), are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, with provisions for firm-fixed-price task orders, performance-based multiple award contract. 

The cumulative, estimated ceiling value of the base year is $38,028,800. The contracts are for the procurement of air traffic control (ATC) engineering and technical support services including specialized ATC engineering, specialized ATC technical and integration support, configuration data management and systems maintenance for a broad range of complex ATC, meteorology and oceanography and aviation command, control, communications, computers, combat, intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance systems. 

These contracts include options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative ceiling value of these contracts to an estimated $199,901,400. Work will be performed at multiple locations in the continental U.S., Southwest Asia, Southeast Asia and Africa. Work is expected to be completed by July 2016. If all options are exercised, work could continue until July 2020. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command Systems Center Atlantic Navy working capital funds in the amount of $25,000 will be obligated at the time of award as the minimum guarantee and will be split among the three awardees; these funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. 

This contract action establishes a potential ceiling value in which funds are obligated on individual task orders. The multiple award contracts were competitively procured by full and open competition via the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center e-Commerce Central website and the Federal Business Opportunities website, with six offers received. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, South Carolina, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
