<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Small Businesses Awarded C4I Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 30, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>C4I</tag>
    <tag>SPAWAR</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>C4 Planning Solutions LLC, Blythe, Georgia (N00039-15-D-0036); Cambridge International Systems Inc., Arlington, Virginia (N00039-15-D-0037); Envistacom LLC, Atlanta (N00039-15-D-0038); Forward Slope Inc., San Diego (N00039-15-D-0039); and SOLUTE Consulting, San Diego (N00039-15-D-0040) are being awarded a $232,068,059 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, hybrid, cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price, cost-reimbursable-type, multiple-award contract for command, control, communications, computers, and intelligence (C4I) systems integration and engineering services in support of authorized and approved U.S. security assistance and security cooperation programs. Foreign military sale funds in the amount of $5,000 per contract awardee (for a total of $25,000) will be placed on contract and obligated at the time of award via a delivery order to each awardee. This contract involves utilizing foreign military sales to various security cooperation partners to be identified as individual delivery orders are issued. Work will be performed in various overseas locations based on the requirement for each individual delivery order placed. The ordering period is three years for the base period up to the contract award amount. The base ordering period expires July 2018. The multiple-award contract was competitively procured with small business proposals solicited and 22 offers received via the Commerce Business Daily’s Federal Business Opportunities and the SPAWAR e-Commerce Central websites. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
