<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Shopping App Offers Quick, Curated Deals</title>
  <author>Rachel Lilly</author>
  <date>August 4, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The new mobile shopping app snach.it aims to combine the deep discounts of Groupon with the instant gratification of Snapchat. It simplifies the shopping experience by offering curated daily deals from top brands, but you only have 30 seconds to purchase, or the offer is gone.</abstract>
  <text>The new mobile shopping app snach.it aims to combine the deep discounts of Groupon with the instant gratification of Snapchat. It simplifies the shopping experience by offering curated daily deals from top brands, but you only have 30 seconds to purchase, or the offer is gone.

“I believe it only takes 30 seconds to make a good first impression,” explains Angela Ramirez, snach.it founder and former merchandise manager for Overstock.com. And that’s all the time you’ll have to take advantage of the snach.it deals. Each morning, users will find three to four new products selected from more than 20 brands such as Ray-Ban, Michael Kors, Nike and Under Armour. Once the clock runs out, the deal is over. Need more time? Users earn 5 seconds of extra time for each friend who downloads the app.

The app targets shoppers who are short on time and seeking specific, relevant and on-trend items. “I have two kids, I’m always on the go. I work, and I never stop,” Ramirez says. Mornings became her only time to slow down and catch up online. Unsatisfied with the quality of the discounts she found and frustrated with the slow shopping process, the idea for snach.it was born.

Ramirez, who moved to the United States from Colombia 15 years ago, uses her experience from her time as a merchandising executive to carefully curate the products—everything from tablets to running shoes, handbags and sunglasses. And unlike shopping on many websites, purchasing is instant. “Within two to three clicks, you’re done,” notes Ramirez. All communication with users will be through the mobile platform. “The first time you register, that will be the only email you get from snach.it.”

Ramirez anticipates final app approval from Apple this week, at which point it will go into a two-week friends and family launch followed by a beta. Interested in testing it out? Sign up on the snach.it website.

Do you use mobile apps for shopping? Could you make a purchase decision in 30 seconds or less?</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
