<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Lockheed Martin to Support P-3 Aircraft for Multiple Countries</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 5, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>NOAA</tag>
    <tag>NASA</tag>
    <tag>P-3</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lockheed Martin receives a contract with a five-year ordering period for engineering services for the P-3 Fatigue Life Management Program.</abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Corp., Marietta, Georgia, is being awarded a $32,289,173 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract with a five-year ordering period for engineering services for the P-3 Fatigue Life Management Program in support of the Navy; other government agencies, including the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA), and the U.S. Customs Border Protection (CBP); and the governments of Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Norway and Germany. Work will be performed in Marietta, Georgia, and is expected to be completed in August 2020.

This contract combines purchases for the Navy ($4,197,592; 13.1 percent); NOAA ($430,522.30; 1.3 percent); NASA ($430,522.30; 1.3 percent); CBP ($430,522.30; 1.3 percent); and the governments of Canada ($5,360,003; 16.6 percent), Australia ($5,360,003; 16.6 percent), New Zealand ($5,360,003; 16.6 percent), Norway ($5,360,003; 16.6 percent), and Germany ($5,360,003; 16.6 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales program. Fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation funds (Navy) and foreign military sales funds in the amount of $463,260 are being obligated at time of award, none of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured pursuant to FAR 6.302-1, Only One Responsible Source. The Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Lakehurst, New Jersey, is the contracting activity (N68335-15-D-0002).
 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Lockheed Martin Corporation is being awarded a $32,289,173 contract for engineering services in support of the P-3 Fatigue Life Management Program for the U.S. Navy; other government agencies, including the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, NASA, and the U.S. Customs Border Protection; and multiple countries.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
