<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Three Major Contractors Awarded JSTARS Delivery Orders</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 10, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Boeing</tag>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Corp., King of Prussia, Pennsylvania, has been awarded an $11,495,833 firm-fixed-price delivery order (FA8730-15-F0054) against a previously awarded General Services Administration Schedule (GS-23F-0150S) for pre-engineering and manufacturing development efforts intended for the Joint Surveillance Target Attack Radar System recapitalization program. Contractor activities will help assess maturity of subsystem technology, reduce weapon system integration risk and lower life cycle cost by virtue of design. Work will be performed in King of Prussia and is expected to be complete by July 31, 2016. Fiscal 2015 research and development funds in the amount of $11,495,833 are being obligated at the time of award.? 

Northrop Grumman Systems Corp. Aerospace Systems, Melbourne, Florida, has been awarded a $10 million firm-fixed-price delivery order (FA8730-15-F0053) against a previously awarded General Services Administration Schedule (GS-23F-0058K). Work will be performed in Melbourne and is expected to be complete by July 31, 2016. Fiscal 2015 research and development funds in the amount of $10 million are being obligated at the time of award.

Boeing Service Co., Richardson, Texas, has been awarded a $9,945,179 firm-fixed-price delivery order (FA8730-15-F0052) against a previously awarded General Services Administration Schedule (GS-23F-0183K). Work will be performed in Seattle and is expected to be complete by July 31, 2016. Fiscal 2015 research and development funds in the amount of $9,945,179 are being obligated at the time of award.

These awards are the result of a competitive acquisition with four offers received. The Air Force Life Cycle Management Center, Hanscom Air Force Base, Massachusetts, is the contracting activity. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
