<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Centerra-Parsons Pacific to Support Base Operations</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 12, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Centerra-Parsons Pacific LLC, Palm Beach Gardens, Florida, is being awarded a $62,113,029 modification under previously awarded indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract N62742-12-D-3601 to exercise option three for base operations support services at Navy Support Facility, Diego Garcia. The work to be performed provides for general management and administration services; command and staff (information technology services, information technology support and management, telephone services, telecommunication services, antenna maintenance); public safety (fire protection and emergency services); air operations (ground electronics, airfield facilities, and passenger terminal and cargo handling); port operations; supply (supply services and petroleum, oil and lubricant management and operations, and ship's store service activities); morale, welfare and recreation support; galley; bachelor quarters; facilities support (facility management, facility investment sustainment, restoration and modernization, custodial, pest control, integrated solid waste management, grounds maintenance, and pavement clearance); utilities (electrical, compressed gases, wastewater, steam, hot water and demineralized water, and potable water); base support vehicles and equipment; and environmental to provide integrated base operating services. After award of this option, the total cumulative contract value will be $237,884,839. 

Work will be performed in Diego Garcia, British Indian Ocean Territory, and is expected to be completed for this option period August 2016. No funds will be obligated at time of award. Fiscal 2015 operation and maintenance (Navy); fiscal 2015 operation and maintenance (Air Force); and fiscal 2016 non-appropriated funds in the amount of $44,417,849 for recurring work will be obligated on individual task orders issued during the option period, of which $23,180,878 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year and $21,236,971 is subject to the availability of funds for the next fiscal year. The Naval Facilities Engineering Command Pacific, Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
