<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Companies to Provide Training Systems Under Nearly $21 Billion Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 12, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>AAI Corp., Goose Greek, South Carolina (FA8621-15-D-6265); The Boeing Co., St. Louis, Missouri (FA8621-15-D-6266); CAE USA Inc., Tampa, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6267); Camber Corp., Huntsville, Alabama (FA8621-15-D-6268); Computer Science Corp., Norco, California (FA8621-15-D-6269); Cubic Defense Applications Inc., San Diego, California (FA8621-15-D-6270); Flight Safety Services Corp., Centennial, Colorado (FA8621-15-D-6272); L3 Communications Corp., Arlington, Texas (FA8621-15-D-6273); LB&amp;B Associates Inc., Columbia, Maryland (FA8621-15-D-6274); Lockheed Martin MST, Orlando, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6276); Northrop Grumman Technical Services Inc., Herndon, Virginia (FA8621-15-D-6278); Raytheon Technical Services Company LLC, Dulles, Virginia (FA8621-15-D-6279); Aero Simulation Inc.,* Tampa, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6252); Aerospace Training Systems Partners JV,* Oklahoma City, Oklahoma (FA8621-15-D-6253); Aviation Training Consulting LLC,* Altus, Oklahoma (FA8621-15-D-6254); Bowhead Systems Management LLC,* Alexandria, Virginia (FA8621-15-D-6255); CTE Joint Venture LLC,* Orlando, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6256); CymSTAR LLC,* Broken Arrow, Oklahoma (FA8621-15-D-6257); Delaware Resource Group,* Oklahoma LLC, Oklahoma City, Oklahoma (FA8621-15-D-6258); DL PI JV, * Clover, South Carolina (FA8621-15-D-6259); Fidelity Technologies Corp.,* Reading, Pennsylvania (FA8621-15-D-6260); Logistics Services International Inc.,* Jacksonville, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6261); Nakuuruq Solutions LLC,* Herndon, Virginia (FA8621-15-D-6262); Nova Technologies,* Panama City, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6263); and Quadrant Training Solutions LLC,* Oviedo, Florida (FA8621-15-D-6264), have been awarded a ceiling $20,900,000,000 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for the Training Systems Acquisition III partial small business set-aside, multiple-award contract. 

Contractors will provide for the analysis, design, development, production, installation, integration, test, and sustainment for Air Force training systems encompassing complex aircrew, maintenance, and system-specific training systems in support of warfighter training at operating locations worldwide. TSA III has a 10-year ordering period through August 2025. This award is the result of a competitive acquisition and 20 large business and 21 small business offers were received. Fiscal 2015 operations and maintenance funds in the amount of $1,000 are being obligated to each company at the time of award. Additional funding will be obligated on individual task orders. Air Force Lifecycle Management Center, Simulators Division, Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio, is the contracting activity.

*Small business

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
