<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Two Firms Awarded C4ISR Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 17, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Honeywell</tag>
    <tag>M.C. Dean Inc.</tag>
    <tag>C4ISR</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>M.C. Dean Inc., Sterling, Virginia, is being awarded an $853,777,308 costs-plus-incentive-fee, fixed-price-incentive (firm target), firm-fixed-price, and cost-plus-fixed-fee multiple award contract (N00039-15-D-0035). Task orders under this multiple award contract will achieve the successful installation and operational certification of command, control, communications, computers, intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance (C4ISR) systems by the program executive office for C4I, Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, and other prospective U.S. government and foreign military sales customers. The C4ISR systems are produced under various production contracts (separate from this contract) and are delivered as government furnished equipment to this contract for installation onboard surface ships, submarines and shore stations located worldwide. Work will be performed aboard Navy platforms on the East and West Coasts, as well as locations worldwide, and is expected to be completed by February 2019. Honeywell Technology Solutions Inc., Columbia, Maryland, is being awarded an $805,170,296 costs-plus-incentive-fee, fixed-price-incentive (firm target), firm-fixed-price and cost-plus-fixed-fee multiple award contract (N00039-15-D-0034).

Fiscal 2015 operations and maintenance (Navy) funds in the amount of the minimum guarantee, which is $5,000, will be placed on contract and obligated at the time of award. The contract funds will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured with full and open competition via the Commerce Business Daily's Federal Business Opportunities website and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website, with two offers received. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity.? 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
