<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Sikorsky Awarded ALIAS Funds</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 19, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Sikorsky</tag>
    <tag>DARPA</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Sikorsky Aircraft Corp., Stratford, Connecticut, has been awarded a $9,787,539 agreement modification (P00002) to exercise the phase II option of previously awarded other transaction HR0011-15-9-0004 for the Aircrew Labor In-Cockpit Automation System (ALIAS) program. Phase II will involve ALIAS requirements update and concept evolution, ALIAS ACES V2.0 technology development and verification, ALIAS system integration, and Phase II capability demonstrations. During Phase II, Sikorsky will conduct UH-60L based flight demonstration of the Autonomous Crew Enhancement System (ACES) cargo-resupply mission and full demonstration of ACES system on a representative fixed-wing aircraft. The primary objectives of the Phase II option effort are to enhance and mature the Phase I system to support flight tests, enhance the usability and robustness of the human interface, and demonstrate system portability on the ground, including demonstration of the knowledge acquisition approach. The addition of the ALIAS Phase II program brings the total cumulative face value of the agreement from $8,066,058 to $22,746,633. Total Sikorsky cost share is $7,581,453 and the total estimated government funding of the agreement is $15,165,180. Fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $9,787,539 are being obligated at time of award. Work will be performed in Stratford, Connecticut (61 percent); Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (10 percent); East Hartford, Connecticut (18 percent); and Alpharetta, Georgia (11 percent), with an estimated completion date of January 2017. The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, Arlington, Virginia, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
