<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Army Awards Oshkosh $6.7 Billion Vehicle Contract</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>August 26, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Oshkosh Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Army</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Army has awarded a $6.7 billion firm fixed price production contract for the Joint Light Tactical Vehicle (JLTV) to Oshkosh Defense LLC, part of Oshkosh Corporation. The Army and the U.S. Marine Corps are expected to replace the bulk of their high-mobility, multipurpose wheeled vehicles (HMMWVs) with 17,000 JLTVs beginning in 2016. The vehicle is designed to combine versatility and protection. It features enhanced ballistic protection, underbody protection similar to that of a mine-resistant ambush protected vehicle (MRAP) and high-speed off-road mobility.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Army has awarded a $6.7 billion firm fixed price production contract for the Joint Light Tactical Vehicle (JLTV) to Oshkosh Defense LLC, part of Oshkosh Corporation. The Army and the U.S. Marine Corps are expected to replace the bulk of their high-mobility, multipurpose wheeled vehicles (HMMWVs) with 17,000 JLTVs beginning in 2016.

The vehicle is designed to combine versatility and protection. It features enhanced ballistic protection, underbody protection similar to that of a mine-resistant ambush protected vehicle (MRAP) and high-speed off-road mobility. It will be produced in two variants: a two-seater and a four-seater. The two-seater is a utility vehicle, while the four-seater has two base platforms for general purpose and a close combat weapons carrier.

The production contract includes eight option years, with three years low-rate initial production and five years of full rate production.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>The U.S. Army has awarded a $6.7 billion firm fixed price production contract for the Joint Light Tactical Vehicle to Oshkosh Defense LLC.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
