<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Joint Venture to Develop Submarine Antennas</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 2, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>submarine</tag>
    <tag>antenna</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Sippican/GSM Submarine Antenna JV, Marion, Massachusetts, is being awarded a not-to-exceed $30,890,543 cost-plus-incentive-fee, cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price letter contract for the development of an OE-538B antenna upgrade and procurement of OE-538 and OE-538A antennas, provisioning items and engineering services. The contract provides for existing and upgraded capabilities to the OE-538 antenna system. The OE-538 antenna system is a single-service (submarine-unique), mast-mounted, multi-function antenna system that provides a radio frequency communication capability in the very low frequency to ultra high frequency; and identification, friend or foe and Global Positioning System (GPS) capabilities for all submarine classes. The OE-538A antenna system is a modified OE-538 antenna system with added capabilities to support Mobile Users Objective Systems Tactical Data Link via Link 16 and iridium capabilities. The OE-538B antenna system will be a modified OE-538A antenna system with added capabilities to support the requirements for anti-jam and GPS military-coded capabilities.  

This contract includes options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative not-to-exceed value of this contract to an estimated $68,900,772.  Work will be performed in Marion, Massachusetts, and is expected to be completed by Aug. 30, 2018. If all options are exercised, work could continue until December 2020.  Fiscal 2014 and 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy); and fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $9,082,879 will be placed on the contract and obligated at the time of award.  The contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year.  This contract was not competitively procured in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1) - only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements (Federal Acquisition Regulation Subpart 6.302-1). The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity (N00039-15-C-0225).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
