<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Contracts</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>February 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Support for Various Systems and U2Advisory and assistance services support has been contracted for the 560th Aircraft Sustainment Group. Technical, analytical and travel support will be provided to improve policy development, management and sustainability to the operation of systems applicable to the U2 aircraft and associated sensors, systems and datalinks; the Global Hawk and Predator aircraft; the Distributed Common Ground System; the Joint Surveillance Target Attack Radar System; measurement and signature intelligence/special projects; the Multi-Platform Common Data Link; the Multi-Platform Radar Technology Insertion program; Intelligence Information, Command and Control, Equipment and Enhancements, or ICE2; and other stations such as the U.S. Army, Air National Guard and National Security Agency. Spectrum Communications Incorporated has received the indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity requirements acquisition contract worth $74.5 million. An estimated $8 million has been obligated. Warner Robins Air Logistics Center is the contracting authority for the five-year contract. Electronic SystemsCenter Receives Range of Technical SupportEngineering and Technology Acquisition Support Services (ETASS) will be carried out at Hanscom Air Force Base, Massachusetts. Other work also will be performed at several locations nationwide. Under the new contract, a broad range of engineering and technical support provisioning and logistics support, modeling and simulation, configuration and data management, architectural support, test and evaluation, security engineering and certification, and technical-related advisory assistance will be conducted for the Electronic Systems Center (ESC). The ESC has supplied command and control and information systems to the Air Force for more than 40 years. Jacobs Engineering Group Incorporated received the ETASS contract, which covers a three-year time period and has a maximum potential value of $480 million. Operations and Maintenance, Logistics for Space WingOperations and maintenance as well as logistics support incorporating an array of services has been contracted by the Air Force Space Command’s 50th Space Wing. The work includes configuration management, electrical power systems management, database applications support, 24-hour maintenance management, industrial safety, communications security, information management, communications network control center operations, communications circuit management, satellite control center support, computer operations support, communications-computer systems maintenance and operations and maintenance for the Defense Satellite Communications System, Secure Communication System and Milstar. The network and space operations and maintenance contract also calls for operations, maintenance, logistics and training support for the Air Force Satellite Control Network at remote tracking stations around the world. In addition, maintenance and logistics support will be provided for global positioning system ground antennas and monitoring stations, software analysis and support for the global positioning system, orbital analysis of military satellites in orbit in support of military satellite controllers, and security forces at New Boston Air Force Station, New Hampshire. Harris Technical Services Corporation received the $31 million contract from the 50th Contracting Squadron, Schriever Air Force Base, Colorado.Continued Efforts on C-17 Weapon SystemSustained efforts associated with the analysis, study, plan, design, development and qualification/test and kit prototype of enhancements and improvements to the C-17 weapon system are planned. The first delivery order is for efforts that support Air Mobility Command requirements to participate in planning, provisioning, conducting, analyzing and documenting an integrated follow-on flight test program. For the initial order, $13.6 million has been obligated. McDonnell Douglas Corporation, a wholly owned subsidiary of the Boeing Company, was awarded the indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract for $1.3 billion. The contract has a five-year ordering period, and funding will be identified on individual delivery orders. The award is a follow-on to the producibility enhancement/performance improvement contract awarded in 2001. The 516 AESG/PKP at Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio, is the contracting activity. Mid-Range Munition DevelopmentDevelopment is scheduled for the XM 1111 Mid-Range Munition for the Future Combat Systems’ Mounted Combat System. The XM 1111 Mid-Range Munition is a precision-guided, 120-millimeter, gun-fired smart munition that will provide a dual-mode, beyond-line-of-sight capability. It incorporates proven technology using a dual-mode seeker suite comprising an imaging infrared sensor and a digital semi-active laser seeker. The seeker was developed and demonstrated in the course of a two-year, U.S. Army-managed science and technology program. A multipurpose chemical energy warhead was selected for the munition because developers believe the warhead’s proven lethality against the primary target of threat armor is the best solution. It also works better against the secondary targets of buildings, fortifications and light armor than less versatile kinetic energy penetrators. The team of Raytheon Company and General Dynamics Ordnance and Tactical Systems received the contract from the Army. The award is valued at $232.3 million and covers 63 months of design and development.  Night Vision for Helmets and Small VehiclesNext-generation night vision sensor technology for helmet-mounted and micro-vehicle applications will be developed. The work includes engineering and initial prototypes of highly sensitive lightweight cameras based on commercially successful shortwave infrared (SWIR) sensors. SWIR technology detects reflected light at wavelengths that the human eye cannot perceive. It operates in wavelength bands between visible and thermal cameras, an area that current night vision technology cannot see. The effort will involve developing indium gallium arsenide night vision SWIR sensors into a 640 x 512 pixel resolution camera weighing less than 10 grams and intended for hand-launched unmanned aerial vehicles. A 1,280 x 1,024 pixel head-mounted monocular also will be delivered. The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA) awarded Goodrich Corporation a three-year contract, which was released under DARPA’s MicroSensors for Imaging program. Goodrich uses advanced material and circuitry that enable its technology to run without requiring cooling, making it smaller and lighter than other night vision technologies.  Support for Worldwide Information Technology RequirementsInfrastructure, application and management services to support the integrated information technology solution requirements of U.S. federal government agencies worldwide have been contracted. The agreement calls for support of both domestic and international programs, as well as the Federal Enterprise Architecture and U.S. Defense Department architecture models. The information technology services will be provided under a 10-year, multiple award indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract with a $50 billion ceiling for all awardees. The agreement includes a five-year base period and one five-year option. The U.S. General Services Administration awarded the Alliant Government-wide Acquisition Contract to Stanley Incorporated. The Alliant contract replaces the Millennia and Applications and Support for Widely diverse End-User Requirements contracts. It provides all Defense Department and federal civilian agencies with more streamlined access to a broad range of management and technical support services for integrated IT solutions.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
