<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>SAIC Wins Navy Tactical Networking Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 16, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>?Science Applications International Corp., McLean, Virginia, is being awarded a $79,973,350 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract to provide integrated afloat and ashore tactical networks in-service engineering agent sustainment support. The networks include the Integrated Shipboard Networks System, Automated Digital Network System, Combined Enterprise Regional Information Exchange System Maritime, Submarine Local Area Networks, Sensitive Compartment Information Networks, and Consolidated Afloat Networks Enterprise Services. Support includes the requirement to respond to official casualty reports, significant incidents, and remedy tickets from the SSC Pacific C4I Navy help desk. Support will also include the following areas: engineering, technical and integrated logistics support, and configuration management. This is a three-year contract with no option periods. 

Work will be performed at the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, California (60 percent); globally aboard Navy ships; shore facilities providing ship access, and various Department of Defense/military installations and facilities outside the U.S. (25 percent); the contractor’s facilities in San Diego, California (10 percent); and Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, South Carolina (5 percent). The period of performance is from Sept. 26, 2015, through Sept. 25, 2018.  No funds will be obligated at the time of award. This contract will be funded with the following fiscal 2015 funding: operations and maintenance (Navy); other procurement (Navy); research, development, testing and evaluation; and shipbuilding and conversations (Navy). This contract was competitively procured via the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce and the Federal Business Opportunities websites, with three offers received, with one selected for award.  Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity (N66001-15-D-0341).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
