<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Army Awards $800 Million for R&amp;D to Counter Asymmetric Threats</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 21, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>research and development</tag>
    <tag>asymmetric threats</tag>
    <tag>Army</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>BAE Systems Technology Solutions &amp; Services Inc., Rockville, Maryland (W911NF-15-D-0001); Battelle Memorial Institute, Columbus, Ohio (W911NF-15-D-0002); Booz Allen Hamilton Inc., McLean, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0003); Bowhead System Management LLC,* Alexandria, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0004); ByLight, Professional IT Services Inc., Arlington, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0005); Charles Stark Draper Laboratory Inc., Cambridge, Massachusetts (W911NF-15-D-0006); Envistacom LLC,* Atlanta, Georgia (W911NF-15-D-0007); Exelis Inc., Herndon, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0008); Georgia Tech Applied Research Corp., Atlanta, Georgia (W911NF-15-D-0009); Hickory Ground Solutions LLC,* Heathsville, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0010); Ideal Innovations Inc.,* Arlington, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0011); Janus Research Group Inc.,* Appling, Georgia (W911NF-15-D-0012); K2 Solutions Inc.,* Southern Pines, North Carolina (W911NF-15-D-0013); Leidos Inc., Reston, Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0014); STS International Inc.,* Berkeley Springs, West Virginia (W911NF-15-D-0015); and WinTec Arrowmaker Inc.,* Fort Washington, Maryland (W911NF-15-D-0016), were awarded an $800 million cost-plus-fixed-fee multiple award task order contract with options for research and development to counteract asymmetrical threats, with an estimated completion date of Sept. 17, 2020. Bids were solicited via the Internet with 16 received. Funding and work location will be determined with each order. Army Contracting Command, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, is the contracting activity.

*Small business</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
