<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>BAE Awarded LiDAR Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 18, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>BAE Systems</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>BAE Systems Spectral Solutions LLC, Honolulu, is being awarded an $8,897,938 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for an effort titled Passive Electro-Optics/Infrared and Light Detection and Ranging (LiDAR) Environment for In-stride Classification and Neutralization. The contractor proposes to develop and demonstrate a multi-sensor suite and an onboard processor to detect, classify, and localize moored and drifting sea mines from an airborne vehicle. The sensor suite will consist of a visible-to-near-infrared (VNIR) multi-spectral imaging (MSI) sensor, a broadband long-wave infrared sensor, and a 2D light detection and ranging LiDAR sensor. The prototype demonstration system built and tested under this effort will consist of two identical pods, each housing a VNIR MSI sensor, a broadband LWIR sensor, a 2D LiDAR sensor, a commercial off the shelf laser, and associated control, storage, and processing electronics. The pods will be demonstrated at a Navy test range location on an MH-60 or Fire Scout provided by the Naval Air Systems Command. This contract contains options, which if exercised, will bring the contract value to $12,322,559. Work will be performed in Honolulu (89 percent); Hudson, New Hampshire (6 percent); Greenlawn, New York (3 percent); and Manassas, Virginia (2 percent), and work is expected to be completed September 15, 2017. Exercised options will run concurrent and will be completed the same date. Fiscal 2014 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $2 million are being obligated at the time of award, and will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured under Office of Naval Research long-range broad agency announcement (BAA) 15-001, dated September 29, 2014. Since proposals will be received throughout the year under the long range BAA, the number of proposals received in response to the solicitation is unknown. The Office of Naval Research, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity (N00014-15-C-5073).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
