<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>FLIR to Provide Combatant Craft Imaging System</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 21, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>FLIR Systems Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>FLIR Surveillance Inc. is being awarded a $49,900,000 firm-fixed-price, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for Combatant Craft Forward Looking Infrared variant 2 (CCFLIR2).</abstract>
  <text>FLIR Surveillance Inc., North Billerica, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $49,900,000 firm-fixed-price, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for Combatant Craft Forward Looking Infrared variant 2 (CCFLIR2). The CCFLIR2 is a day/night and infrared imaging system that provides operators the capability to detect visible light or infrared radiation reflected or emitted by surface targets at tactically significant ranges in all operational environments. CCFLIR2 provides increased detection, recognition and identification ranges in all conditions; constant interrogation of targets across the spectrum of operations; and greater situational awareness with high-definition imaging and zoom capability. CCFLIR2 incorporates improved optics and image processing that allows the user to see the same target in multiple wavelengths, highlighting the target features and discriminators. CCFLIR2 integrates with embedded navigational systems and other shipboard systems to provide target and way-point geolocation and tracking functionality. CCFLIR2 is part of a collection of intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance systems available for use on Special Operations Force maritime craft. 

Work will be performed in North Billerica, Massachusetts, and is expected to be completed by September 2025. Fiscal 2014 and 2015 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $2,845,444 will be obligated at time of award. Contract funds will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured and solicited via the Federal Business Opportunities website, with one offer received. The Naval Surface Warfare Center, Crane, Indiana, is the contracting activity (N00164-15-D-JQ76). 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Special warfare combatant-craft crewmen transit the Salt River in northern Kentucky on the Special Operations Craft-Riverine during pre-deployment, live-fire training. FLIR Surveillance Inc. was awarded a contract for Combatant Craft Forward Looking Infrared variant 2.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
