<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Sierra Nevada to Provide Prototype Technology to Support Intelligence Community</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 23, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Sierra Nevada Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Intelligence Community</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Sierra Nevada Corp., Sparks, Nevada, has been awarded a $9,516,004 cost-plus-fixed-fee completion contract for enterprise engine software and hardware prototype system. Contractor will provide design and develop the technology and operational prototypes to satisfy the undersecretary of defense for intelligence goals of optimizing information sharing within the intelligence community (IC), and to enable decision making while maximizing IC capabilities to discover, access, retain, store, share, and exploit information. This will be accomplished by designing, developing, testing, and evaluating technology for an enterprise engine, using model driven development methods and techniques that enable agile software adaptation to situational awareness and decision making. 

Additionally, there will be development and demonstration of prototype adaptations to support National Geospatial-Intelligence Agency and service-oriented tasks in the areas of mission analysis, agile mission processing, and mission knowledge-based situational assessments. Lastly, information assurance and cyber security methods and techniques will be tailored for prototype adaptations. 

Work will be performed at Sparks, Nevada, and is expected to be complete by Sept. 22, 2017. This award is the result of a competitive acquisition with two offers received. Fiscal 2015 research, development, test, and evaluation funds in the amount of $2,791,392 are being obligated at the time of award. Air Force Research Laboratory, Rome, New York, is the contracting activity (FA8750-15-C-0163).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
