<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>United States and China Reach Cyber Espionage Agreement</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>September 25, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>China</tag>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The presidents of the United States and China reach a historic agreement aimed at limiting cyber crime.</abstract>
  <text>U.S. President Barack Obama and Chinese President Xi Jinping have agreed that neither country will “support cyber-enabled theft of intellectual property, including trade secrets or other confidential business information, with the intent of providing competitive advantages to companies or commercial sectors,” according to a White House announcement released today.

The two countries also agree that timely responses should be provided to requests for information and assistance concerning malicious cyber activities, and they have committed to cooperate, as much as each nation’s laws allow, with requests to investigate cyber crimes, collect electronic evidence and mitigate malicious activity emanating from their respective territories.

Additionally, they agreed to establish a joint dialogue on fighting cyber crime and related issues. China will designate an official at the ministerial level to be the lead, and the Ministry of Public Security, Ministry of State Security, Ministry of Justice and the State Internet and Information Office will participate in the dialogue. For the United States, the U.S. secretary of homeland security and the U.S. attorney general will co-chair the dialogue, with participation from representatives from the FBI, intelligence community and other agencies. The first meeting of this dialogue will be held by the end of 2015 and will occur twice per year thereafter.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>President Barack Obama and President Xi Jinping of China hold a press conference at the Great Hall of the People in Beijing, China, last year. Today, the two announced a historic agreement designed to curb cyber aggression.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
