<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Adds $120 Million to Submarine Imaging System Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 28, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>Integrated Submarine Imaging System</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Mission Systems and Training, Manassas, Virginia, is being awarded a $120,400,598 cost-plus-incentive-fee and cost reimbursement modification to previously awarded contract N00024-09-C-6247 to exercise an option for engineering services and support of the AN/BVY-1 Integrated Submarine Imaging System (ISIS). Services will include design, development, testing, reverse engineering, technology insertion/refreshment, engineering services, field engineering services, and system support. The ISIS provides mission critical, all-weather, visual, and electronic search, digital image management, indication, warning, and platform architecture interface capabilities for attack submarine (nuclear propulsion) (SSN) - SSN688 (Los Angeles class); SSN 21 (Seawolf class); submersible, ship, guided, nuclear (SSGN Ohio class); and SSN 774 (Virginia class) submarines with potential for ship, submersible, ballistic, nuclear (SSBN) (Trident class) and potentially other submarines. ISIS rolls-up existing components and near-term capabilities, and provides a robust architecture for efficiently inserting future capabilities as they become available, including items leveraged from the SSN 774 (Virginia) class photonics program. 

Work will be performed in Manassas, Virginia (72 percent); Virginia Beach, Virginia (9.8 percent); Northampton, Massachusetts (7.5 percent); Arlington, Virginia (4.6 percent); Fairfax, Virginia (4.6 percent); and Newport, Rhode Island (1.5 percent), and is expected to be completed by September 2016.  Fiscal 2014 and 2015 other procurement (Navy); and fiscal 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, and 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) funding in the amount of $6,738,308 will be obligated at time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington Navy Yard, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
