<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Awarded Nearly $265 Million for AIM-9X Improvement</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 28, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>AIM-9X</tag>
    <tag>Foreign Military Sales</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Missile Systems, Tucson, Arizona, is being awarded a $264,805,607 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for an AIM-9X system improvement program to provide additional capability and resolve obsolescence issues for the Navy, Air Force, and the governments of Korea, Singapore, Malaysia, Belgium, Netherlands and Turkey under the Foreign Military Sales program. The effort includes engineering services required to incorporate new AIM-9X missile components and associated software updates into the Lot 17 and Lot 19 production programs. This effort will also provide development, integration, and flight test support for AIM-9X Block II hardware and software. Work will be performed in Tucson, Arizona (95.5 percent); Andover, Massachusetts (2.3 percent); Baltimore, Maryland (1.5 percent); and other various continental U.S. locations (0.7 percent), and is expected to be completed in September 2020. Fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy and Air Force), and foreign military sales funds, in the amount of $46,424,785 will be obligated at time of award, none of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. 

This contract combines purchases for the Air Force ($24,783,835; 53.35 percent); Navy ($10,746,165; 23.15 percent); and the governments of Turkey ($3,340,868; 7.2 percent); Netherlands ($1,900,000; 4.6 percent); Belgium ($2,098,917; 4.5 percent); Singapore ($1,960,000; 4.3 percent); Malaysia ($1,310,000; 2.8 percent); and Korea ($285,000; .1 percent). This contract was not competitively procured pursuant to Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-1. The Naval Air Systems Command, Patuxent River, Maryland, is the contracting activity (N00019-15-C-0121).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
