<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Logos to Provide Sensor Package for Small Tactical Unmanned Aircraft</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 30, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Logos</tag>
    <tag>Office of Naval Research</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>?Logos Technologies, Fairfax, Virginia, is being awarded an $18,245,842 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract. The contract is for the spectral wide area airborne surveillance, inspection and fusion technology. The contractor will develop and integrate four significant sensing capabilities (electoral optical, wide area imager, short wave infrared hyper spectral imager and inspection sensor) into one payload that conforms to the size, weight and power limitations of the small tactical unmanned aircraft system platform. The resulting payload will have a wide area sensing capability to enable situational understanding across wide across wide areas; a wide area spectral information collection capability based on a novel multi-slit interferometer design; and a higher resolution inspection sensor for object of interest confirmation. The contractor will develop a payload management system that can control and point the individual sensors and enable the movement and storage of as much as a gigabyte of data per second. The contractor will also adapt and mature a wide range of processing algorithms including scene rendering, geo-location, real time spectral processing, moving object signature extraction, object tracking and condition of interest recognition. Work will be performed in Fairfax, Virginia, and is expected to be completed March 27, 2020. Fiscal 2014 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $251,891; and fiscal 2015 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $2,020,648 are being obligated at this time. Funds in the amount of $251,891 will expire at end of current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured under broad agency announcement 13- 018, entitled "Spectral and Reconnaissance Imagery for Tactical Exploitation," and dated June 28, 2013. Ten proposals were received in response to the solicitation. The Office of Naval Research, Arlington, Virginia, is the contracting activity (N00014-15-C- 0120). </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
