<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Six Companies to Share $5 Billion Technology Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 9, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Cybersecurity</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Barbaricum LLC, Washington, D.C. (FA8075-16-D-0011); Baum, Romstedt Technology Research Corp., Vienna, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0012); Data Systems Analysts Inc., Fairfax, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0013); Professional Project Services Inc. (Pro2Serve), Oak Ridge, Tennessee (FA8075-16-D-0014); SMS Data Products Group Inc., McLean, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0015); and Solers Inc., Arlington, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0016), have been awarded a partial small business set-aside competition for cybersecurity and information systems technical area tasks, and will compete for all orders with an estimated value of $3,500,000 and below. These companies will share the maximum $5 billion cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price, multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract with a not- yet-awarded multi-award full and open competition pool. This contract provides research, development, test and evaluation efforts for technical area tasks within the software analysis, information assurance, knowledge management and information sharing, and modeling and simulation focus areas. Location of performance will be cited on individual task orders. Work is expected to be completed by November 30, 2020. No funds are being obligated on the basic contract, however, a task order to fulfill management reporting requirements will be issued to each contractor to satisfy the minimum order guarantee. This multiple contract award was competitively procured by a partial small business set-aside acquisition via the Federal Business Opportunities website with 14 offers received. The Air Force Installation Contracting Agency, Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
