<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy's CANES Program Cleared for Full Deployment</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>October 22, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>CANES</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Frank Kendall, undersecretary of defense for acquisition, technology and logistics, recently approved the Consolidated Afloat Networks and Enterprise Services (CANES) for full deployment, U.S. Navy officials have announced.</abstract>
  <text>Frank Kendall, undersecretary of defense for acquisition, technology and logistics, recently approved the Consolidated Afloat Networks and Enterprise Services (CANES) for full deployment, U.S. Navy officials have announced. The program puts in place a robust and secure networking environment across ships and submarines that can fulfill the Navy's vision of information dominance. 
The program modernizes the fleet's computing environment, provides common technologies across platforms, upgrades command, control, communications, computers and intelligence (C4I) and streamlines logistics. By consolidating five networks into one, CANES increases operational effectiveness. Its integrated voice, video, data and system-management functions reduce shipboard workload while its reduction of hardware requirements decreases system vulnerabilities and system administration needs, according to the Navy’s written announcement.
Kendall's signature conveys the Navy's and the Defense Department's confidence in and support of CANES. The decision also transferred oversight of the program from the Defense Department to the Department of the Navy. With the acquisition decision memorandum, which was signed on October 13, the Navy’s 240th birthday, the service can move forward to procure and install CANES on its full inventory objective of ships, submarines and shore sites.
To date, the Navy has completed installation of CANES on 25 ships with 153 remaining and due to be complete by 2024. Installed systems are performing operational missions and have received positive feedback from fleet users.
In addition to its operational advantages, the CANES acquisition strategy saves taxpayer dollars and implements a continuous competition throughout the program lifecycle. The data rights to the CANES design are owned by the government; seven qualified vendors compete for future build-to-print production unit delivery orders.

Already, CANES has realized a cost savings of more than $720 million, Navy officials report.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>The U.S. Defense Department has approved the Navy CANES program for full deployment.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
