<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Contracts</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>March 17, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Radar Program Roars Into ProductionThe AN/SPS-48 Radar Obsolescence, Availability Recovery (ROAR) program will move from the initial nonrecurring development phase into low-rate initial production. The first three of 36 total AN/SPS-48 ROAR production systems will be delivered in late 2010, the first quarter of 2011 and the second quarter of 2011. All the systems are intended to remain in service until at least 2045. The production follows a successful critical design review that took place in October 2007. AN/SPS-48 radars were first introduced to the fleet in the mid-1980s as part of the New Threat Upgrade program on aircraft carriers, cruisers and destroyers. ROAR lessens total cost of ownership by reducing the impact of obsolescence in major subassemblies, and increases fleet readiness by improving operational availability. ITT Corporation won the $18 million development contract from the Naval Sea Systems Command. As with earlier phases of the program, the majority of work will be performed at ITT Radar Systems-Gilfillan in Van Nuys, California. Less Expensive Communications for the CapitalThe Government of the District of Columbia has signed a three-year contract for local telecommunications voice, data and voicemail services at more than 200 local offices. More than 20,000 employees will receive the services including police, fire and administrative personnel. According to the District Office of Planning, the capital had 26,951 “full-time equivalent” employees working in the nation’s capital at the end of 2006. The contract is estimated to save between $6 million and $12 million on basic services and will allow the District to address most of the products and services it purchases from the provider. The agreement helps contain costs for landline and data services, while allowing District officials to take advantage of emerging technologies. Verizon Business won the contract valued at $51 million for the work. Marines to Obtain Video Capture CapabilitiesThe Tactical Video Capture System (TVCS) will be designed, fabricated, installed and tested for various Marine Corps bases across the globe. The work is expected to be completed by February 2011. Personnel at the Marine Air Ground Task Force Training Command will use the TVCS to conduct real-time visualization and situational awareness while Marine Corps units carry out military operations. They also will use the system to conduct after-action reviews of completed training exercises. Global Security and Engineering Solutions, a division of L-3 Services, Incorporated in Chantilly, Virginia, was awarded the firm-fixed-price, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract with a ceiling value of $326 million. The Marine Corps Systems Command based at Quantico, Virginia, serves as the contracting activity. The contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The agreement was procured competitively as a full and open competition. Integrated C4I for New ShipsIntegration, engineering, procurement, fabrication, assembly, test, inspection, delivery and limited installation of integrated command, control, communication, computers and intelligence (C4I) capabilities aboard new construction ships has been contracted. More than 75 percent of the work will be performed in North Charleston, South Carolina, with additional efforts in New Orleans; Pascagoula, Mississippi; San Diego; Mobile, Alabama; Green Bay, Wisconsin; Norfolk, Virginia; and Washington, D.C. The effort is expected to be completed by February 2013, but if all three, one-year options are exercised, the work will continue until February 2016. The indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-incentive fee, firm-fixed-priced, performance-based contract is worth an estimated $242 million, but could have cumulative final value of an estimated $344 million if all options are used. BAE Systems Technology Solutions and Services, Rockville, Maryland, won the work from Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command (SPAWAR). This Enterprise Platform Integration Contract was awarded by SPAWAR on behalf of its organizational partner, the Navy’s Program Executive Office for C4I. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the year. Laser Technology AdvancesResearch, design, development and testing of state-of-the-art laser technology has been procured under the Laser Application Support and In-house Research and Development (LASIR) contract. Work will be carried out at Air Force Research Laboratory sites at Kirtland Air Force Base in Albuquerque, New Mexico. Specific efforts include working to advance gas, hybrid electric-gas and chemical laser systems, as well as technologies related to high-power fiber lasers, fiber laser pumps, nonlinear optics, solid-state lasers and diode-pump lasers; coordinating, preparing and executing laser effects tests; rapid prototyping of directed energy technology, which includes semiconductor lasers, thin-disk lasers, ultra-short lasers, laser-based infrared countermeasures, and mid-wave and long-wave infrared lasers; and supporting the Laser Center of Excellence, a joint U.S. Defense Department and academic program that conducts work with gas, hybrid electric-gas and chemical laser systems. The Boeing Company won a $49 million U.S. Air Force contract for the work. Army Upgrades AbramsThe 435 M1A1 Abrams main battle tanks are scheduled to undergo an upgrade. The vehicles will be converted from their current configuration to the M1A2 Systems Enhancement Package (SEP) Version Two (V2) configuration. The M1A2 SEP V2 is the most technologically advanced digital tank. It includes improved displays, sights, auxiliary power and a tank-infantry telephone. In addition, it can accommodate future technology improvements to ensure compatibility with the U.S. Army’s Future Combat Systems. The Army’s Tank-automotive and Armaments Command Life Cycle Management Command awarded General Dynamics Land Systems, a business unit of General Dynamics, a multi-year contract for the upgrades. The first increment is valued at $39 million and will fund the upgrade of 20 M1A1 Abrams tanks. Over the course of the contract all remaining M1A1 tanks that have been in the Army’s inventory for more than 20 years will be modernized. Support Services for Navy AirCustomer support services will be provided to the Naval Air Systems Command Information Technology/Information Management Department. The work includes video technology support, national help desk support, Navy Marine Corps Intranet customer technical representative support, defense messaging support and embedded technical support. The work is expected to be completed in February 2009, and the estimated level of effort for the base year is 174,720 personnel hours. The tasks will be performed at the Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Patuxent River, Maryland. PSI Sierra LLC, Lexington Park, Maryland, was awarded the $7 million ceiling-priced, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract from the Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division. The contract was competitively procured under an electronic request for proposals as a 100 percent small business set-aside. Thirteen offers were received. Submit information about contract awards to signalnews@afcea.org.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
