<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Small-Business Member Announces STEM Scholarship</title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 1, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>STEM Education</tag>
    <tag>scholarships</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>BridgePhase LLC, a small business provider of information technology consulting and professional services, will sponsor an annual scholarship for one science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) graduate student, beginning in 2016.</abstract>
  <text> 

BridgePhase LLC, a small business provider of information technology consulting and professional services, will sponsor an annual scholarship for one science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) graduate student, beginning in 2016. The $3,000 award will recognize a student enrolled or enrolling in a STEM graduate degree program at an accredited U.S. academic institution. Selection for this program will be competitive and based on a candidate’s overall undergraduate and/or graduate academic performance.

“Offering this scholarship program through the AFCEA Educational Foundation is our opportunity to give back to our professional community, and we would like to do more in the future,” says Matt Stratford, managing principal for BridgePhase.

Eligible candidates for the BridgePhase STEM Major Scholarship must be majoring in one of the following academic disciplines: computer analytics/intelligence; computer engineering; computer forensic science; computer programming; computer science; computer systems; cybersecurity; information science; information technology; information resource management; mathematics; network engineering; network security; operations research; software engineering; or telecommunications engineering.

Submission guidelines will be announced in January 2016. Please refer to the AFCEA Educational Foundation’s website at www.afcea.org/education for further details.

Vince Patton, executive director, AFCEA Educational Foundation, challenges other members of the AFCEA small-business community to sponsor a scholarship program supporting the STEM profession. “This is a great way to help grow the business and the intellectual capital of our STEM community,” he states.

Are you an AFCEA business member interested in sponsoring a scholarship? Please contact Patton at vpatton@afcea.org or 703-631-6173.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Matt Stratford, managing principal, BridgePhase LLC (l), presents a $3,000 check to AFCEA Educational Foundation Executive Director Vince Patton to sponsor the 2016 BridgePhase STEM Major Scholarship.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
