<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>ISIL Reportedly Threatens Paris-Type Attack on Washington, D.C.  </title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>November 16, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>ISIL</tag>
    <tag>terrorism</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>A militant group claiming affiliation with the terrorist faction that carried out the deadly choreographed attacks in France on Friday released an alarming video Monday reportedly threatening a Paris-style attack in Washington, D.C.</abstract>
  <text>A militant group claiming affiliation with the terrorist faction that carried out the deadly choreographed attacks in France on Friday released an alarming video Monday reportedly threatening a Paris-style attack in Washington, D.C.

In a video circulated by several news agencies, a militant clad in a camouflage flak vest vows a new round of attacks by the Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant (ISIL), singling out an attack on the U.S. capital city.

“We say to the states that take part in the crusader campaign that, by God, you will have a day, God willing, like France’s, and by God, as we struck France in the center of its abode in Paris, then we swear that we will strike America at its center in Washington,” the man states, according to subtitled translation. SIGNAL Media cannot independently confirm the authenticity of the video.

ISIL claimed responsibility for the deadly, well-choreographed attacks in Paris on Friday that killed 129 people and wounded hundreds of others. The attackers used suicide vests and were armed with AK-47s, killing people at a restaurant, concert hall and soccer stadium. 

The Department of Homeland Security and the FBI quickly joined with French authorities to help investigate and monitor the Parisian attacks and were in contact with counterparts in the region. However, neither agency's website updated its content to reflect Monday’s blunt video threat against Washington, D.C.

The circulated six-minute video closely resembles others released by ISIL, but it “lacked the theatrics and high-quality editing that other videos have had,” according to The Washington Post.

The video, reportedly released by “Wilayah Kirkuk,” or State of Kirkuk, includes the blustering threat made by a man identified as Al Ghareeb the Algerian, who threatens European nations that contribute to strikes in Syria and Iraq against ISIL targets.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Screen shot from Twitter of ISIL's reported threat of Paris-type attack on Washington, D.C. </img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
