<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>Monday, March 17, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Rugged Bluetooth HeadsetWorkers and warfighters need reliable and durable communications gear when working outdoors. The Explorer 370 is a ruggedized Bluetooth headset built to meet U.S. military standards. The headset features QuickPair technology for simple, quick setup, and it is capable of operating up to seven hours in talk mode and up to eight days in standby. For more information, visit www.plantronics.com.Multifunction DockingPortPersonal electronic devices such as laptops and cell phones can quickly clutter a desktop with cables and other accessories. The SpaceStation is a compact multipurpose docking port for laptop users. It features a universal serial bus hub, cable management system, desk organizer and an ergonomic, cooling design. For more information, visit www.bluelounge.com.Mobile Radios for First RespondersEmergency response personnel require feature-rich and reliable equipment. The ES series of Project 25 compliant radios offers a range of trunking protocols and a streamlined design. Features include operation in Project 25 trunked and conventional modes, enhanced Project 25 Vocoders, Smartnet/SmartZone trunking protocols, and support for up to 864 channels/talk groups. For more information, visit www.efji.com.WorkstationsThis line of workstations comes with a 19-inch liquid crystal display monitor and features 10-slot passive backplanes and four drive bays. The N4W 1950G workstations can fit a range of backplanes supporting different types of single board computers, equipment and software standards. For more information, visit www.cyberresearch.com.Event Logging SoftwareKeeping track of the event log is an important part of many network administrators’ jobs. UltraAdmin 6 integrates several software applications such as Active Directory and domain management tools. Designed to provide enhanced capabilities in day-to-day Microsoft Windows domain management tasks, the software also is compatible with Windows Vista and Windows Server 2008. For more information, visit www.doriansoft.com/ultraadmin.LED FlashlightsMaintaining illumination during a disaster recovery or other emergency operation can mean the difference between life and death. This line of light emitting diode (LED) flashlights features improved light output. These enhanced models, the Argo LED and HP headlamps, the Task-Light 3AA, the Streamlight Jr. and Steamlight Jr. Reach, the TL-2 LED, the NightFighter and the Scorpion LED all feature increased light output designed to rival incandescent lights while providing the long run times and ruggedness of LEDs. For more information, visit www.streamlight.com.Submit new products for consideration to the business editor.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
