<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Air Force Adds Companies to $5 Billion Cyber Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 20, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Alion Science and Technology, Burr Ridge, Illinois (FA8075-16-D-0001); Battelle Memorial Institute, Columbus, Ohio (FA8075-16-D-0002); Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0003); Exelis Inc., Information Systems, Rome, New York (FA8075-16-D-0004); Georgia Tech Applied Research Corporation, Atlanta, Georgia (FA8075-16-D-0005); MacAulay-Brown Inc., Dayton, Ohio (FA8075-16-D-0006); ManTech Advanced Systems International Inc., Fairfax, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0007); Northrop Grumman Information Systems Sector, McLean, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0008); TASC Inc., Chantilly, Virginia (FA8075-16-D-0009); and Wyle Laboratories Inc., Huntsville, Alabama (FA8075-16-D-0010), have been added as awardees to a maximum $5 billion multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for cybersecurity and information systems technical area tasks. Contractors will provide research, development, test and evaluation efforts for technical area tasks within the software analysis, information assurance, knowledge management and information sharing and modeling and simulation focus areas. Work locations will be specific on individual task orders with the effort expected to be complete by November 30, 2020. These companies will share this award with the Multi-Award Partial Small Business Set-Aside competition pool award that was announced October 8, 2015. This award is the result of a competitive acquisition with 11 offers received. No funds are being obligated at the time of award. The Air Force Installation Contracting Agency, Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska, is the contracting activity.

 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
