<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Advanced Satellite-Based Waveform Improves Connectivity at Talisman Sabre</title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 30, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>satellite communications</tag>
    <tag>Australia</tag>
    <tag>military exercises</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>U.S. military and the Australian Defense Force noted improved connectivity while testing an advanced Time Division Multiple Access (TDMA) waveform technology during the Talisman Sabre 2015 joint training exercise.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. military and the Australian Defense Force noted improved connectivity while testing an advanced Time Division Multiple Access (TDMA) waveform technology during the Talisman Sabre 2015 joint training exercise, according to news statements.

The militaries tested a high-performance IP satellite broadband system developed by Hughes Network Systems LLC. The HX System is designed for carrier-grade IP broadband for maritime, air and ground-based mobile networks and video, voice and data trunking for mesh networks.

“Australia is still maturing its understanding of deployed TDMA satellite operations, and the support from Hughes was fundamental to both the successful outcome of the exercise and educating [the] Army on planning and executing operations utilizing TDMA waveforms,” Col. Shaun Love, ADF, director land network integration, said in a statement.

The HX system allows for flexible use of satellite bandwidth and users can configure network settings for four levels of IP traffic prioritization. The advanced waveform technology delivers higher performance satellite connectivity and planners anticipate employing it in future military exercises.

Talisman Saber 2015 is a biennial land, sea and air military training exercise between U.S. and Australian forces that features more than 33,000 personnel, 21 ships, 200 aircraft and three submarines. Its aim is to improve U.S.-Australian interoperability to respond to a wide variety of contingencies and maintain security, peace, and stability in the Indo-Asia-Pacific region. 

"Advanced TDMA waveform technology is critical for efficient global military satellite communications," Dan Losada, senior director of Defense Systems at Hughes, said in a statement.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
