<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DHS Seeks Nontraditional Partners to Protect Internet of Things</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 11, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>science and technology</tag>
    <tag>Internet of Things</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Department of Homeland Security Science and Technology Directorate announced its first Innovation Other Transaction Solicitation aimed at nontraditional performers such as technology startups to offer solutions to some of the toughest threats facing DHS and the homeland security mission.</abstract>
  <text>The Department of Homeland Security (DHS) Science and Technology Directorate (S&amp;T) today announced its first Innovation Other Transaction Solicitation (OTS) aimed at non-traditional performers such as technology startups to offer solutions to some of the toughest threats facing DHS and the homeland security mission. Awarded through Other Transaction Solicitation HSHQDC-16-R-B0005, the first call for proposals is looking for solutions to improve situational awareness and security measures for protecting Internet of Things (IoT) domains.

“Today marks an important milestone in how we do business at S&amp;T, said DHS Under Secretary for Science and Technology Dr. Reginald Brothers. “We want to remove the barriers that limit the nation’s innovators from considering us as a technology partner. The Innovation OTS will help engage some of the best minds on the most difficult homeland security problems.”  

The goal of the Innovation OTS is to help companies that have typically never worked with the government consider the DHS as a viable customer for their technology. The program is intended for startups developing concepts for commercial application that have the potential to widen their technical aperture and make available for homeland security problem sets. Advantages of the OTS framework include: a streamlined application process; fast-track selection timelines; expedited funds transfer; rapid operator feedback; and no dilution of ownership. Potential follow-on funding will be provided for promising prototypes. 

For IoT Security, DHS is specifically seeking technologies to help the department and/or critical infrastructure managers gain comprehensive and near continuous knowledge of IoT systems that affect their operations and assets. Technical areas include: Detecting IoT Components and Connections; Authenticating Components and Updating IoT Components.

For more information visit http://go.usa.gov/cKxDx  or contact dhs-silicon-valley@hq.dhs.gov.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
