<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Modifies Shipboard Electronics Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 16, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co. Integrated Defense Systems, San Diego, California, is being awarded a $28,390,942 modification to previously awarded contract N00024-15-C-2414 to exercise Option Year 1 for life cycle engineering and support (LCES&amp;S) services for Landing Platform Dock (LPD) 17 Class integrated shipboard electronic systems. The services to be provided will include: LCE&amp;S Services including post-delivery planning, logistics and engineering; homeport technical support; integrated product data environment; data maintenance, equipment management, systems integration and design engineering; software support, research engineering, obsolescence management (both technical and logistics), material readiness support, emergent repair planning, training and logistics support; planning yard support of integrated electronic systems including Fleet Modernization program planning; ship alteration development and installation; material management; configuration data management; research engineering; logistics documentation; and other logistics and executing activity coordination, management; sustaining engineering and obsolescence management support for unique LPD 17 Class integrated shipboard electronic systems. Work will be performed in San Diego, California (90 percent); Norfolk, Virginia (4 percent); Pascagoula, Mississippi (2 percent); Mayport, Florida (2 Percent); and Japan (2 percent), and is expected to be completed by December 2016. Fiscal 2015 and 2016 other procurement (Navy); fiscal 2012 and 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy); and fiscal 2016 operation and maintenance (Navy), funding in the amount of $5,067,899 will be obligated at time of award and $550,000 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
