<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Draper Labs to Support Trident Guidance Subsystems</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 16, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Charles Stark Draper Laboratories</tag>
    <tag>Trident II</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Charles Stark Draper Laboratories Inc., Cambridge, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $54,329,646  cost-plus-incentive-fee, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract to provide specialized tactical engineering services, logistics services, fleet support services, and guidance SSP alteration services to test, repair and maintain guidance subsystems, test equipment, and related support equipment in support of existing Trident (D-5) weapon systems; provide technical and engineering services necessary to support the initial fielding of the MK6 MOD 1 guidance systems; perform research in the application of technologies to support Trident II (D-5) guidance and reentry systems; provide research into the applications of technologies to meet guidance requirements for operations on the Common Missile Compartment that is part of the U.S. Ohio replacement program and United Kingdom (U.K.) Successor program; provide specialized technical knowledge and support for hypersonic guidance, navigation and control applications utilizing an integrated avionics computer and global positioning system; and provide technical and engineering services to support the guidance, navigation and control system that will support Navy hypersonic flight experiments. This contract contains options, which if exercised, will bring the contract value to a maximum dollar value of $392,953,129. Work will be performed in Cambridge, Massachusetts (95 percent); Pittsfield, Massachusetts (3 percent); and El Segundo, California (2 percent), with an expected completion date of September 30, 2016. With all options exercised, work will continue through September 30, 2020. Fiscal 2016 weapons procurement (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $35,707,806; operations and maintenance (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $ 13,919,076; and U.K. contract funds in the amount of $ 4,702,764 will be obligated at the time of the award. Contract funds in the amount of $ 35,707,806 will expire at the end of fiscal 2016. This contract was a sole-source acquisition in accordance with 10 U.S Code 2304(c)(1) and (4). The Strategic Systems Programs, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity (N00030-16-C-0014).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
