<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Lockheed to Support U.S. and U.K. Trident II</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 16, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>Trident II</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Mission Systems and Training, Mitchell Field, New York, is being awarded a $72,479,741 cost-plus-incentive-fee, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract to provide U.S. and United Kingdom (U.K.) Trident II (D5) navigation subsystem engineering support services. Specific efforts include U.S. and U.K. fleet support; U.S. and U.K. trainer systems support; Ohio-class SSBN engineered refueling overhauls; U.S. and U.K. SSI4 trainer system; SSBN-R strategic weapon training system and training system development; U.K. Successor support, software modernization; and Linked Autonomous Program Navigation Operational Trainer modernization. This contract contains options, which if exercised, will bring the contract value to a maximum dollar value of $147,383,525. Work will be performed in Mitchell Field, New York (97 percent); Oldsmar, Florida (2 percent); and Manassas, Virginia (1 percent), with an expected completion date of September 30, 2017. If all options are exercised, work will continue through September 30, 2018. Fiscal 2016 operations and maintenance (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $40,718,962; fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $19,308,197; fiscal 2016 other procurement (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $5,057,416; and U.K. contract funds in the amount of $7,395,166 are being obligated at the time of the award. Contract funds in the amount of $40,718,962 will expire at the end of fiscal 2016. This contract was a sole-source acquisition in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1). The Strategic Systems Programs, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity (N00030-16-C-0002).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
