<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Northrop Supports E-6B Aircraft</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 21, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman</tag>
    <tag>E-6B</tag>
    <tag>Multi-Role Tactical Common Data Link</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Northrop Grumman Systems Corp., is being awarded a $15,046,674 modification to a previously awarded contract for validation/verification of Multi-Role Tactical Common Data Link efforts in support of the E6-B aircraft.</abstract>
  <text>Northrop Grumman Systems Corp., Herndon, Virginia, is being awarded a $15,046,674 modification to a previously awarded cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price contract (N00019-12-C-0096) for validation/verification of Multi-Role Tactical Common Data Link efforts in support of the E6-B aircraft. Efforts will include development of a technical directive to support organic installation efforts that reflects configuration changes; equipment relocation support, including modeling and simulation tools; thermal and structural analysis of the new location; first article verification, including destructive test and evaluation of production Ka- and Ku-Band radomes; and development efforts for aircraft network architecture. Work will be performed in San Diego, California (59 percent); Greenville, Texas (21 percent); Stowe, Massachusetts (19 percent); and Salt Lake City, Utah (1 percent), and is expected to be completed in December 2017. Fiscal 2015 aircraft procurement (Navy) funds in the amount of $15,046,674 are being obligated on this award, none of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Air Systems Command, Patuxent River, Maryland, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Northrop Grumman is being awarded a contract modification for validation and verification of Multi-Role Tactical Common Data Link efforts in support of the E6-B aircraft.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
