<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Serco Awarded Anti-Terrorism/Force Protection Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 30, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Serco</tag>
    <tag>Anti-terrorism Force Protection Ashore</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Serco Inc., Reston, Virginia, is being awarded a $22,225,504 firm-fixed-price contract for lifecycle sustainment of Physical Security/Access Control and Command, Control, Communications, Computers and Intelligence systems in support of the Naval Facilities Engineering Command (NAVFAC) Anti-Terrorism/Force Protection Ashore Program at various Navy installations worldwide. The work to be performed provides for preventive maintenance of hardware, associated firmware and software; response and resolution of service calls for corrective maintenance to include equipment repair, overhaul or replacement; Information Assurance Vulnerability Alert to include version control, patch management and vulnerability scanning; asset management to track, maintain, upgrade and dispose of systems; configuration management to establish and maintain consistency of the system attributes with operational requirements and evolving technical baseline; technical refreshments, upgrades and installation of new systems; and programmatic trend analysis to identify systemic sustainment issues such as technology obsolescence. The contract also contains 19 unexercised options, which if exercised would increase cumulative contract value to $131,460,543. Work will be performed worldwide and is expected to be completed by January 2017. If all options are exercised, work will continue through January 2021. Fiscal 2016 operation and maintenance, (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $22,225,504 are obligated on this award and will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via the Navy Electronic Commerce Online website, with six proposals received. The Naval Facilities Engineering Command Engineering and Expeditionary Warfare Center, Port Hueneme, California, is the contracting activity (N39430-16-C-1811).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
