<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Motorola to Sustain Mobile Radios for Anti-Terrorism Mission</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 28, 2015</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Motorola</tag>
    <tag>Anti-terrorism Force Protection Ashore</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Motorola Solutions Inc., Columbia, Maryland, is being awarded a $20,459,980 firm-fixed-price contract for lifecycle sustainment of the Enterprise Land Mobile Radio system for Naval Facilities Engineering Command Anti-Terrorism/Force Protection Ashore Program Systems at various Navy installations worldwide. The work to be performed provides for preventive maintenance of hardware and software; response and resolution of service calls for corrective maintenance to include equipment repair, overhaul or replacement; asset and configuration management; password management; and software upgrade installation. The contract also contains three unexercised options, which if exercised would increase cumulative contract value to $76,237,089. Work will be performed worldwide, and is expected to be completed by December 2017. If all options are exercised, work will continue through December 2020. Fiscal 2016 operation and maintenance (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $20,459,980 are obligated on this award and will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was solicited on a sole source basis. Statutory authority for the use of other than full and open competition is found at 10 U.S.C. 2304 (c)(1) as implemented by Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-1(iii) - only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements. The Naval Facilities Engineering Command Engineering and Expeditionary Warfare Center, Port Hueneme, California, is the contracting activity (N39430-16-C-1812).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
