<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Supports Phalanx Weapon System for Nine Nations</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 4, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>Phalanx Close-In Weapon System</tag>
    <tag>Foreign Military Sales</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Tucson, Arizona, is being awarded a $42,217,201 modification under previously awarded cost-plus-fixed-fee contract N00024-12-C-5405 to exercise options for design agent engineering and technical support services for Phalanx, SeaRAM, and land-based Phalanx weapon systems. Phalanx Close-In Weapon System (CIWS) is a fast-reaction terminal defense against low- and high-flying, high-speed maneuvering anti-ship missile threats that have penetrated all other defenses. The CIWS is an integral element of the Fleet Defense In-Depth concept and the Ship Self-Defense Program. Operating either autonomously or integrated with a combat system, it is an automatic terminal defense weapon system designed to detect, track, engage and destroy anti-ship missile threats penetrating outer defense envelopes. The design agent engineering and technical support services are required for maintainability, reliability, and improvements. This contract combines purchases for the U.S. government (62.76 percent) and the governments of Turkey (20.14 percent); Australia (12.85 percent); Japan (2.82 percent); Canada (&lt;1 percent); United Kingdom (&lt;1 percent); Korea (&lt;1 percent); Bahrain (&lt;1 percent); Pakistan (&lt;1 percent); and Egypt (&lt;1 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales (FMS) program. Work will be performed in Tucson, Arizona (60.29 percent); Louisville, Kentucky (9.39 percent); Fort Campbell, Kentucky (5.5 percent); Melbourne, Florida (5.37 percent); Huntsville, Alabama (5 percent); Fort Sill, Oklahoma (2.75 percent); Whidbey Island, Washington (1.96 percent); McKinney, Texas (1.81 percent); McCord, Washington (1.57 percent); Norfolk, Virginia (1.18 percent); and various locations with less than one percent each (5.18 percent). Work will be completed by October 2016. Fiscal 2016 operations and maintenance (Army); FMS (Turkey, Australia, Japan, Canada, United Kingdom, Korea, Bahrain, Pakistan, and Egypt); fiscal 2016 weapons procurement (Navy); fiscal 2013, 2014 and 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy); and fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation funding in the amount of $15,282,192 will be obligated at time of award. Funds in the amount of $5,050,000 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington Navy Yard, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity. </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Raytheon is being awarded a contract modification to exercise options for design agent engineering and technical support services for Phalanx, SeaRAM, and land-based Phalanx weapon systems for nine countries.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
