<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Issues 2nd NGEN RFI to Industry</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>January 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Department of the Navy</tag>
    <tag>NGEN</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Navy released its second request for information in preparation for the recompete of a multi-billion dollar contract that provides network-centric data and services to Navy and Marine Corps personnel. The Next Generation Enterprise Network (NGEN) is the follow-on effort to the consolidation in 2000 under the Navy Marine Corps Intranet (NMCI) contract. It is the government’s largest information technology outsourcing program.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Navy released its second request for information in preparation for the recompete of a multi-billion dollar contract that provides network-centric data and services to Navy and Marine Corps personnel. The Next Generation Enterprise Network (NGEN) is the follow-on effort to the consolidation in 2000 under the Navy Marine Corps Intranet (NMCI) contract. It is the government’s largest information technology outsourcing program.

Per the new RFI, the Naval Enterprise Networks (NEN) program management office seeks industry input for the vexed recompete of the contract, which expires on June 27, 2018. The RFI seeks to engage industry and provide input to inform the acquisition strategy of the NGEN contract recompete. Interested industry members have until January 15 to complete the NGEN RFI #2 response form. 

The goal of the second RFI is to gain specific industry insight on the potential for competing and awarding an end user hardware contract. “We are using the insight from all responses, particularly as it relates to end user hardware, to further solidify the requirements and to ensure that we release a quality [request for proposal] that industry will be able to bid on and execute in order to provide optimized enterprise services to our Sailors and Marines,” NEN Program Manager Capt. Michael Abreu, USN, said in a statement.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
