<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>CERDEC to Host 2-Day Rally with Industry </title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>January 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Army Communications-Electronics Research, Development and Engineering Center will host a two-day technical interchange meeting with industry to identify and align mutually beneficial research and development investments. Registration begins on February 1.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Army Communications-Electronics Research, Development and Engineering Center will host a two-day technical interchange meeting with industry to identify and align mutually beneficial research and development investments, officials announced.

The meeting, beginning March 31 and held at Aberdeen Proving Ground in Maryland, seeks to enhance government-and-industry communication and provide industry with critical information to quickly respond to emerging requirements, according to the FedBizOps announcement.

Officials will use breakout sessions to highlight specific research and development requirements in various CERDEC mission areas, such as mission command; tactical and deployed power; tactical and strategic networks; tactical cyberspace operations; electronic warfare; countermine/counter-IED; intelligence, surveillance, reconnaissance and targeting; and intelligence analysis, exploitation and dissemination.

“If we want to leverage creativity and innovation to its fullest, Army R&amp;D must work more closely with industry in the earliest stages of the product lifecycle before requirements are firm and design concepts are determined,” Henry Muller, CERDEC technical director, said in a statement. “The sooner industry knows of our interest in a specific capability, the sooner they can begin to explore or invest in applicable technologies and formulate ideas for Army consideration.”

Registration is slated to open February 1 and close February 28. The forum is open to academia and other government organizations.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
