<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Awards Data Support Services Task Orders</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 28, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Acral Services, Arlington, Virginia (N00189-16-D-0013); CACI Enterprise Solutions, Arlington, Virginia (N00189-16-D-0014); CGI Federal, Fairfax, Virginia (N00189-16-D-0015); Deloitte Consulting, Alexandria, Virginia (N00189-16-D-0016); ECS Federal, Fairfax, Virginia (N00189-16-D-0017); IBM, Bethesda, Maryland (N00189-16-D-0018); Leidos, Reston, Virginia (N00189-16-D-0019); and Main Sail, Cleveland, Ohio (N00189-16-D-0020), were awarded an estimated $147,178,362 multiple award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price task orders contract to obtain process improvement, reengineering, management and data support services, to include Navy Enterprise Resource Planning sustainment on behalf of Naval Supply Systems Command (NAVSUP) Business Systems Center (BSC). NAVSUP BSC requires process management and data services to support current and future Navy requirements in the areas of data governance and analysis, business process re-engineering and management and business system engineering and integration. Each contract includes a 12-month base period, four 12-month option periods and the option at Federal Acquisition Regulation 52.217-8 - option to extend services. If all options are exercised, the contract value will reached a ceiling value of $809,480,995. Work will be performed in Mechanicsburg, Pennsylvania (81 percent); and Washington, District of Columbia (19 percent). Work is expected to be completed by February 2017; if all options are exercised, work will be completed by July 2020. Fiscal 2016 operation and maintenance (Navy) funds in the amount of $10,000 will be obligated on each of the eight contracts to fund the contract's minimum amount, and funds will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured with the solicitation posted to the Federal Business Opportunities website, with 15 offers received. The Naval Supply Systems Command Fleet Logistics Center Norfolk, Contracting Department, Norfolk, Virginia, is the contracting activity.

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
