<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Small Businesses Get the Inside Scoop on How to Grow a Business</title>
  <author>Katie Helwig</author>
  <date>February 8, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>AFCEA International</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA International hosts an event February 9 that offers theoretical and practical information on how to move from being a subcontractor to a prime contractor in the federal market space.</abstract>
  <text>AFCEA International will host an event February 9 that offers theoretical and practical information on how to move from being a subcontractor to a prime contractor in the federal market space.

Former Air Force contracting officer and program manager Barry Levy offers an informative and interactive classroom environment, providing facts and necessary steps for businesses to increase prime and subcontracting opportunities. This is the fourth course Levy has created for AFCEA International, third in the federal contracting series. 

Northrop Grumman in McLean, Virginia, will host the event from 3 p.m. to 7 p.m., during which Levy shares the stage with Barbara Gray, CEO of Gray Matters Technology Services, an 8(a) woman-owned, veteran-owned small business in Bowie, Maryland. Gray will offer insights on contract set-asides and how to poise your business for the next level of competition.

After two hours of classroom instruction, participants will delve into practical applications of growing a business. David Kriegman, author of "Zero to a Billion: 61 Rules Entrepreneurs Need to Know to Grow a Government Contracting Business" moderates a panel of executives who exponentially grew their businesses. Attendees will reap the benefits of lessons learned from some of the best in the industry: Heidi Gerding, CEO of HeiTech Services, Eric Gillespie, CEO of Govini, Barry Landew, CEO of Wolf Den Associates, and Vish Varma, senior vice president at SNAP.

The session, sponsored by Govini, Insperity and Karthik Consulting, concludes with a networking session.

This not-to-be-missed event is exclusive to corporate member associates and active government AFCEA members. If you are not a corporate member yet, why not? Register online by Tuesday at 9 a.m. for at least a one-year corporate membership, and I can squeeze you in to the remaining slots, offering a discount for the course as well. While the regular cost for Tuesday's course is $295, businesses that sign up as corporate members before the February 9 morning deadline will get admission to the course at a reduced cost of $250. You can save more if you choose a three-year or sustainer membership.

We haven't neglected our active government AFCEA members. Email Katie Helwig for the special registration link to attend for $25.

Katie Helwig is manager of small business programs at AFCEA International.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
