<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Commerce Department Announces Grant Awardees</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 8, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Commerce Department has announced 25 awardees that will receive $10 million under the 2015 Regional Innovation Strategies program, which is designed to advance innovation and capacity-building activities across the country through two different competitions.</abstract>
  <text>Today, U.S. Secretary of Commerce Penny Pritzker announced the 25 awardees that will receive $10 million under the Economic Development Administration’s (EDA) 2015 Regional Innovation Strategies (RIS) program. The program is designed to advance innovation and capacity-building activities across the country through two different competitions: the i6 Challenge and the Seed Fund Support (SFS) Grants competition.

“As the driving force behind the administration’s focus on entrepreneurship, the Department of Commerce is committed to helping set the conditions for innovators and entrepreneurs to test new ideas, take risks, find financing and customers, and ultimately thrive,” said Secretary Pritzker in a written announcement. “The Regional Innovation Strategies program is critical to ensuring that entrepreneurs have access to the tools they need to move their ideas and inventions from idea to market.”

Awards include an i6 investment that will help expand the Maine Center for Entrepreneurial Development’s Top Gun program into the Top Gun Rural Accelerator Network and a Seed Fund Support grant to support Coastal Enterprises Inc.’s Natural Resource Business Seed Capital Fund.

RIS i6 Challenge grantees include:

·         New Mexico State University, Las Cruces, New Mexico; $368,760 for Next Gen Entrepreneurship (Next Gen) 

·         Telluride Foundation, Telluride, Colorado; $499,720 for Southwest Innovation Corridor

·         University of Alabama in Huntsville, Huntsville, Alabama; $500,000 for UAH Virtual Proof of Concept Center (POCC): The Growth &amp; Acceleration of Products (GAP) Project

·         University of Connecticut, Storrs, Connecticut; $500,000 for Quiet Corner Innovation Cluster (QCIC)

·         Maine Center for Entrepreneurial Development, Portland, Maine; $390,000 for Top Gun Rural Accelerator Network Expansion

·         Northeast Ohio Medical University, Rootstown, Ohio; $498,282 for Accelerating Pharmaceutical Commercialization: A Rural Proof of Concept Center for Economic Development

·         University of Wisconsin System, Stevens Point, Wisconsin; $499,965 for a new Proof of Concept Center

·         Arkansas State University, State University, Arkansas; $500,000 for East Arkansas Regional Innovation System

·         CareerSource Broward, Fort Lauderdale, Florida; $499,999 for SUN i6 Challenge

·         Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia; $499,751 for CatalyzeVT: Expanding the Innovation Ecosystem in the Roanoke-Blacksburg Region of Virginia

·         Innovation Alliance, Seattle, Washington; $500,000 for Clean Water Innovation Initiative (CWII)

·         University of Hawaii System, Honolulu, Hawaii; $500,000 for XLR8UH Hawaii Innovation Ecosystem Development Project

·         Quatere, Salt Lake City, Utah; $500,000 for Quatere Cohorts Innovation Center Expansion

·         Oklahoma Innovation Institute, Tulsa, Oklahoma; $351,400 for Tulsa Research Partners Technology Commercialization Concentrator for Tulsa

·         BioHealth Innovation, Inc., Rockville, Maryland; $495,000 for expansion of the Venture Commercialization Model (V-COMM)

·         Innovation Works, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; $500,000 for a rural hardware entrepreneurship program in southwest Pennsylvania

·         Oregon State University, Corvallis, Oregon; $447,231 for Oregon State Engineered Wood Building Products Commercialization Project

 Seed Fund Support grantees include:

·         Mahoning Valley Economic Development Corporation, Youngstown, Ohio; $250,000 for Valley Growth Ventures, LLC

·         Enterprize Events Inc,, Guaynabo, Puerto Rico; $250,000 for the Puerto Rico IDE Seed Fund

·         Coastal Enterprises Inc., Wiscasset, Maine; $250,000 for the CEI Natural Resource Business Seed Capital Fund

·         Duke University, Durham, North Carolina; $250,000 for the Triangle Venture Alliance

·         BioAccel, Phoenix, Arizona; $250,000 for the Southwest Integrated Investment Ecosystem Development Project

·         Global Center for Medical Innovation, Inc., Atlanta, Georgia; $249,981 for the Global Center for Medical Innovation (GCMI) MedTech Seed Fund &amp; Accelerator Program

·         Illinois Science and Energy Innovation Fund, Chicago, Illinois; $248,200 for the Energy Foundry Seed Investor Education and Strategic Partner Development Project

·         Ben Franklin Technology Partners of Southeastern PA, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; $250,000 for Greater Philadelphia Impact Partners</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
