<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Modifies Test and Evaluation Contracts</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 8, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Gryphon Technologies, Washington, District of Columbia (N00189-13-D-0021- Mod P00007); CGI Federal, Fairfax, Virginia (N00189-13-D-0022- Mod P00009); Alion Science and Technology Corp., Burr Ridge, Illinois (N00189-13-D-0023- Mod P00009); Wyle Lab, Huntsville, Alabama (N00189-13-D-0023- Mod P00009); and Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Virginia (N00189-13-D-0025- Mod P00005), are being awarded modifications to the previously awarded indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, firm-fixed-price contracts to exercise Federal Acquisition Regulation 52.217-8 for six months for technical and analytical support to include conduct and analysis of structured operational and integrated test and evaluation of the Navy systems to Commander Operational Test and Evaluation Force. Gryphon Technologies is being awarded $7,046,968, bringing the total estimated contract value to $73,794.734. CGI Federal is being awarded $7,677,470, bringing the total estimated contract value to $48,772,431. Alion Science and Technology Corp. is being awarded $7,677,471, bringing the total estimated contract value to $52,894,807. Wyle Lab is being awarded $8,003,134, bringing the total estimated contract value to $55,121,610. Booz Allen Hamilton is being awarded $8,662,515, bringing the total estimated contract value to $59,701,675. Work will be performed in the Bahamas; Australia; England; Honduras; Singapore; Italy; Guam; Hawaii; Nova Scotia; British Columbia; Columbia; Belize; Guatemala; Souda Bay Crete, Greece; and Mexico. The percentage of work being performed at each location will be determined by task order requirements. Work will have an estimated completion date of December 2017. No funding will be obligated at the time of award. Navy working capital funds will be obligated as individual task orders are issued, and funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This requirement was competitively procured with the solicitation posted to the Federal Business Opportunities website and the Navy Electronic Commerce Online website, with seven offers received. The Naval Supply Systems Command Fleet Logistics Center Norfolk, Contracting Department Norfolk, Virginia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
