<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>November 17, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Portable Rugged VisualizationCenter Warfighters receiving live video feeds require high-grade monitors and processing equipment. The Vigor Evo HD is a lightweight, deployable system designed to support situational awareness, target acquisition, and command and control needs in tactical operations centers. The system features three 17-inch high-resolution displays, plus a central display with two fold-out screens for panoramic or multiwindow views. For more information, visit www.nextcomputing.com.Kevlar Transit CasesMilitary and commercial electronics must be protected from the elements. This line of carbon fiber and carbon/Kevlar rackmount military cases is designed for lightweight and ballistic reinforcement. Fully ruggedized, the cases are shock resistant, watertight and sealed from sand and dust. For more information, visit www.transitcases.com.Voltage-controlled Oscillators Reliable components are the heart of high-performance wireless communications equipment. This line of voltage-controlled oscillators (VCOs) is optimized for communications and instrumentation applications. The VCOs can cover frequency ranges from 5 megahertz to 7 gigahertz and provide linear monotonic tuning over the entire tuning range. For more information visit www.emhiser.com/.RadomeThis ground-based radome design is the result of a request by the U.S. Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA). The Generation II radome design features a nonsymmetric geometric panel configuration and an impedance-matched bolting seam. For more information, visit www.mfggalileo.com.Voice Communications Touch Pad Modern telecommunications equipment can be hard to use without the right interface. The VCOM Touchpanel is built around a tablet computer with a 7-inch touch screen. The VCOM’s graphic user interface supports multiple channels and is configurable for point-to-points, group calls, party lines and program audio listens. For more information, visit www.intracomsystem.com.Automated Data Capture SystemInspecting equipment and scheduling regular maintenance can be challenging in a busy military or commercial environment. Originally developed for the aviation industry, the Automated Data Capture System (ADCS) allows inspectors to use menu-driven checklists and digital aircraft and engine drawings during inspection and evaluation. ADCS allows inspectors to create discrepancy records and produce real-time reports to meet customer and specification requirements. For more information, visit www.caci.com/adcs.  New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
