<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Lockheed to Provide Trident II Inertial Navigation</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 14, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>Trident II</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Mission Systems and Training, Mitchel Field, New York, is being awarded a maximum value $93,400,000 undefinitized contract action (N00030-16-C-0045) for Trident II Inertial Navigation Subsystem (INS) design; continued development of the technology refresh efforts for Shipboard Systems Integration (SSI) Increment 8 and SSI Increment 13; delivery of eight INSs, and various test plans and reports related to the INS, gyroscope, modeling and simulation efforts; hardware and software design and temporary alterations all required for subsequent validation of performance at-sea; integration of the Electrostatically Supported Gyro Navigator-Replacement into the navigation subsystem; initiation of production activities leading to an SSI Increment 8 initial operational capability; and Multi-Star Enhanced Prelaunch tasks. Work will be performed in Mitchell Field, New York (55 percent); Huntington Beach, California (34 percent); Clearwater, Florida (7 percent); and Cambridge, Massachusetts (4 percent), with an expected completion date of November 30, 2017. Fiscal 2016 other procurement (Navy) in the amount of $42,300,000; and United Kingdom funding in the amount of $2,600,000 will be obligated at time of award. No contract funds will expire at the end of the fiscal year. This contract was a sole-source acquisition in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1) &amp; (4). The Navy’s Strategic Systems Programs, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity.   

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Lockheed Martin has been awarded more than $93 million to provide Trident II inertial navigation subsystems.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
