<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Contracts Archive</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date></date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>May 2008Secure Communications Coming to MarinesA modular, scalable Internet protocol communications and networking system will be produced for the U.S. Marine Corps as the next-generation Tactical Data Network-Data Distribution System-Modular (TDN-DDS-M). The system enables deployed Marines to establish secure, networked voice, data and video conferencing as well as other communication capabilities among commanders, joint warfighters and coalition forces. The TDN-DDS-M will connect Marines with advanced technologies that are smaller, lighter and consume less power than earlier versions of the technology. The TDN-DDS-M upgrades the TDN-DDS-Replacement. The modular system contains routers, switches, computers, power supply and other equipment needed to access the Defense Information System Network, the secret Internet protocol router network and the nonsecure Internet protocol router network along with coalition and joint forces networks. Initial deliveries of TDN-DDS-M systems are scheduled for the third quarter of 2008. General Dynamics C4 Systems, a business unit of General Dynamics, was awarded the five-year indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract. The initial award value is $130 million with a potential of $375 million if all options are exercised.  NSA ENTERPRISE ModernizesEnterprise wide systems engineering and program management for the efficient and effective modernization of the National Security Agency (NSA) will be performed under three Enterprise Program Management II (EPM II) contracts with the NSA. Each award is a single, indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract. The EPM II effort provides the contract vehicles by which the agency will obtain acquisition support for the portfolios managed by each of the program executive offices. SI International Incorporated will conduct the work on the prime contracts, which have cumulative ceiling values of more than $131 million over a performance period of five years. A potential ceiling expansion is worth an additional $200 million. Major subcontractors on the EPM II team include Booz Allen Hamilton and Lockheed Martin Corporation.  New Software Slated for PublicBuildings Service A new enterprise and software application known as the electronic Requirements Development Process (eRDP) has been contracted for the Public Buildings Service. eRDP will automate tasks such as online surveys, survey analysis utilities, property walk-throughs, business intelligence and non-space requirements management. The application integrates with multiple enterprise solutions and delivers functionality both online and offline through multiple access points, including mobile devices. The process will be the first application to fully leverage a service oriented architecture infrastructure currently being implemented for the Public Buildings Service through the eCommon initiative. The eRDP is the first phase of the Full Lifecycle of Customer Interaction (FLCI), which will cover other mission-critical systems. It is a collection of business processes the Public Buildings Service uses to meet customer space requirements. Under the contract, requirements development, business process engineering, architecture, design, development, operations and maintenance, and training will be provided. The General Services Administration awarded QinetiQ North America’s Information Technology (IT) Services Group the prime contract for the development and implementation of the software. The award has a value of almost $20 million over five years if all options are exercised.  Marines Have the JTRS Joint Tactical Radio System-approved Falcon III handheld and vehicular radio systems will be provided to the U.S. Marine Corps. The systems will be acquired through the previous Consolidated Interim Single Channel Handheld Radio indefinite delivery/indefinite quantity contract. This is the second major contract awarded by the Marine Corps under its tactical handheld radio procurement program. Marines will receive the multiband/multimission Falcon III AN/PRC-152(C), which offers single channel ground and airborne radio system capability as well as ultrahigh frequency ground-to-ground line-of-sight communications, close-air support, tactical satellite communications and programmable encryption. They also will acquire the Falcon III AN/VRC-110 high-performance multiband vehicular radio systems. The radios feature extended frequency range, significant reductions in weight and size, the ability to upgrade waveforms, programmable encryption and easy removal from vehicles. Harris Corporation received the $96.7 million award.  A Win With WIN-TSpecialized satellite communications (SATCOM) earth terminals and support services for increment 1 of the Warfighter Information Network-Tactical (WIN-T) program have been purchased. The U.S. Army will receive 299 Satellite Transportable Terminals (STTs) and two Unit Hub SATCOM Trucks (UHSTs) as well as Ka-band upgrade kits and spares. The next-generation STTs can be configured to operate over Ku- or Ka-band satellite frequencies, and the new UHSTs provide Ku- or Ka-band operation and increased modem capacity. Both the terminal and the truck interoperate with previously fielded units. The STT and UHST units enable U.S. troops to establish quickly and maintain communications in hazardous conditions. As production of these SATCOM terminals increases, the units will be available for NATO and other allies as a solution for mobile tactical SATCOM requirements. General Dynamics SATCOM Technologies won the $109 million contract from the U.S. Army Communications-Electronics Command, Fort Monmouth, New Jersey.  Tracking with GBOSSThe ability for U.S. Marines in Iraq to detect hostile troop movements will improve after acquiring the Ground Based Operational Surveillance System (GBOSS) elevated sensor systems with networked remote capability. GBOSS provides persistent surveillance using infrared sensors elevated on a stationary platform and is an enhancement of the Rapid Aerostat Initial Deployment (RAID) system currently used in operations Enduring Freedom and Iraqi Freedom. Earlier RAID versions employed an aerostat to elevate the sensors. The current tower-based systems offer an enhanced capability with fewer logistics concerns. Enhancements unique to GBOSS include the addition of a second electro-optical infrared sensor and ground-based radar networked into a single remote ground control station. This enhanced system increases the warfighters' situational awareness. Raytheon Company was awarded the $60 million contract option to provide the U.S. Marine Corps with the technology. Work will be performed at Raytheon Integrated Defense Systems' IntegratedAirDefenseCenter, Andover, Massachusetts, and The WarfighterProtectionCenter, Huntsville, AlabamaApril 2008Testbed Development for JCREWA testbed to support the Joint Counter Radio-Controlled Improvised Explosive Device Electronic Warfare (JCREW) program will be developed and demonstrated. The U.S. government will use the testbed to develop and test advanced open architecture technology for counter-improvised explosive device (IED) systems development. An open-systems digital signal processing (DSP) architecture technology and testbed systems for counter-IED research and development, along with systems engineering support services for the government and contractors who use the testbed facilities, will be provided as part of the agreement. A scalable data acquisition and processing application within a very dense, size/weight/power-constrained environment will be demonstrated. Also scheduled for demonstration is the X-Midas platform-independent software framework as an application environment, which is designed to reuse existing applications from other government and contractor sources for developing DSP applications. Mercury Federal Systems Incorporated received a $2.5 million contract for the work from the U.S. Army Fort Monmouth’s Communications and Electronics Command. Mercury also entered into an agreement with ITT Electronic Systems to collaborate and leverage each company’s strengths to demonstrate algorithm component portability for the JCREW testbed architecture. In the initial development effort, Mercury and ITT will combine forces to implement and demonstrate the portability of the Constant Amplitude Network Waveform Adaptive Combiner algorithm.Enhanced Emergency Response in MaineThe city of Bangor, Maine, installed advanced communications technology to enhance its emergency response communications system. The new tools enable the city’s legacy systems to interoperate with high-speed Ethernet systems so personnel can operate a two-way radio system over fiber. Fiber is easier to maintain and faster than copper telephone lines, reducing downtime for emergency response systems. Bangor’s system provides real-time voice and data and increased safety for first responders, and the move improves the ability of police, fire and ambulance systems to communicate. The project includes a fiber interface for voter receivers and connectivity for mobile data access points, Supervisory Control and Data Acquisition, telemetry, video security and future expansion of all city-owned facilities on one private infrastructure. Bangor selected RITEC Wireless Incorporated as the systems integrator for the mobile data project. RITEC Wireless is using Harris Corporation’s NetXpress IP (Internet protocol) multiplexers to solve the latency issues between the legacy system and the new fiber system. Products and Revisions Ordered for Flight Simulator and TrainingProducts and revisions for the V-22 Full Flight Simulator (FFS) and Flight Training Device (FTD) have been ordered. Under the agreement, analysis, design development, upgrade, enhancements, integration, installation, test, training, maintenance, logistical support and configuration management for the V-22 FFS, FTD, Aircraft Common Operational Equipment, FFS and FTD training spare parts will be provided. In addition, the contract calls for the incorporation of V-22 Training Equipment Change Requests into FFS and FTD training devices. Work will be performed in Fort Worth, Texas, and Philadelphia, and is scheduled to be completed in March 2011. The Naval Air Systems Command is the contracting authority. Bell-Boeing Joint Program Office won the $78.5 million indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity award. The contract was not competitively procured.  Construction Set for New DISA FacilityA new Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) headquarters will be constructed at Fort Meade, Maryland. The headquarters complex will be erected on a 95-acre site on the grounds of the 91-year-old Army installation. It will consolidate the operations of approximately 4,000 DISA employees who currently work in various locations in Northern Virginia and other areas of the United States, as well as tenant personnel. The U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Baltimore District, awarded the contract to Hensel-Phelps Construction Company. The single design-build contract is worth $370 million and allows Hensel-Phelps to begin construction on the approximately 1-million-square-foot, multi-story campus facility. The headquarters is estimated to be completed in three years. The contract was issued in accordance with the U.S. Defense Department Base Realignment and Closure (BRAC) actions. It adheres to the U.S. Army’s November 11, 2007, Record of Decision for BRAC actions at FortMeade. Assistance Acquired for Ballistic Missile DefenseUnder a contract with General Dynamics, systems engineering and program management assistance will be provided to the Aegis Ballistic Missile Defense (BMD) program for production, fleet introduction and fleet operations and support. Test and evaluation engineering management and safety, and quality and mission assurance engineering and support also will be provided. In addition, international programs including foreign military sales and cooperative development actions will be supported. Aegis BMD will give Navy Aegis cruisers and destroyers the capability to detect, track, intercept and defeat short-, medium- and long-range ballistic missiles in the ascent, midcourse and terminal descent phases of ballistic missile flight. The Naval Sea Systems Command awarded the contract to General Dynamics to support the Missile Defense Agency’s Aegis BMD program directorate. If all options are exercised, the contract has a total potential value of $191 million over five years. Services for Military Environmental RemediationTechnical, management, administrative and information support services for environmental remediation project management have been procured. Project scopes, schedules, budgets and service as a technical point of contact on environmental restoration projects at Base Realignment and Closure (BRAC) installations also will be provided. In addition, U.S. Navy BRAC Project Management Office policies, positions and interests will be represented in meetings with stakeholders. Work will be performed in San Diego; Philadelphia; Charleston, South Carolina; San Francisco; and Washington, D.C. SkillStorm Incorporated dba SGIS won the SeaPort Enhanced Project Management, Administrative and Information Support prime contract from the U.S. Navy. The award has a one-year base period with four option years. It is valued at more than $15 million. TRICARE TEAMS ProgramThe Office of the Assistant Secretary of Defense for Health Affairs and TRICARE Management Activity have partnered with 22 companies on a prime contract for the TRICARE Evaluation, Analysis, Management and Support (TEAMS) program. Dynamics Research Corporation (DRC) was selected as one of the companies under the program. DRC will provide services to Health Affairs in support of policy development, decision support, program and project management and administration; information management; specialized studies and analysis; performance-based budgeting; financial analysis; business process improvement; functional validation and verification; acquisition management; and logistical support. DRC was selected for the TEAMS vehicle Category 2, Program Management Support. The TEAMS contract is worth $5 billion. It has a one-year base period with nine option years.  March 2008Radar Program Roars Into ProductionThe AN/SPS-48 Radar Obsolescence, Availability Recovery (ROAR) program will move from the initial nonrecurring development phase into low-rate initial production. The first three of 36 total AN/SPS-48 ROAR production systems will be delivered in late 2010, the first quarter of 2011 and the second quarter of 2011. All the systems are intended to remain in service until at least 2045. The production follows a successful critical design review that took place in October 2007. AN/SPS-48 radars were first introduced to the fleet in the mid-1980s as part of the New Threat Upgrade program on aircraft carriers, cruisers and destroyers. ROAR lessens total cost of ownership by reducing the impact of obsolescence in major subassemblies, and increases fleet readiness by improving operational availability. ITT Corporation won the $18 million development contract from the Naval Sea Systems Command. As with earlier phases of the program, the majority of work will be performed at ITT Radar Systems-Gilfillan in Van Nuys, California. Less Expensive Communications for the CapitalThe Government of the District of Columbia has signed a three-year contract for local telecommunications voice, data and voicemail services at more than 200 local offices. More than 20,000 employees will receive the services including police, fire and administrative personnel. According to the District Office of Planning, the capital had 26,951 “full-time equivalent” employees working in the nation’s capital at the end of 2006. The contract is estimated to save between $6 million and $12 million on basic services and will allow the District to address most of the products and services it purchases from the provider. The agreement helps contain costs for landline and data services, while allowing District officials to take advantage of emerging technologies. Verizon Business won the contract valued at $51 million for the work. Marines to Obtain Video Capture CapabilitiesThe Tactical Video Capture System (TVCS) will be designed, fabricated, installed and tested for various Marine Corps bases across the globe. The work is expected to be completed by February 2011. Personnel at the Marine Air Ground Task Force Training Command will use the TVCS to conduct real-time visualization and situational awareness while Marine Corps units carry out military operations. They also will use the system to conduct after-action reviews of completed training exercises. Global Security and Engineering Solutions, a division of L-3 Services, Incorporated in Chantilly, Virginia, was awarded the firm-fixed-price, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract with a ceiling value of $326 million. The Marine Corps Systems Command based at Quantico, Virginia, serves as the contracting activity. The contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The agreement was procured competitively as a full and open competition. Integrated C4I for New ShipsIntegration, engineering, procurement, fabrication, assembly, test, inspection, delivery and limited installation of integrated command, control, communication, computers and intelligence (C4I) capabilities aboard new construction ships has been contracted. More than 75 percent of the work will be performed in North Charleston, South Carolina, with additional efforts in New Orleans; Pascagoula, Mississippi; San Diego; Mobile, Alabama; Green Bay, Wisconsin; Norfolk, Virginia; and Washington, D.C. The effort is expected to be completed by February 2013, but if all three, one-year options are exercised, the work will continue until February 2016. The indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-incentive fee, firm-fixed-priced, performance-based contract is worth an estimated $242 million, but could have cumulative final value of an estimated $344 million if all options are used. BAE Systems Technology Solutions and Services, Rockville, Maryland, won the work from Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command (SPAWAR). This Enterprise Platform Integration Contract was awarded by SPAWAR on behalf of its organizational partner, the Navy’s Program Executive Office for C4I. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the year. Laser Technology AdvancesResearch, design, development and testing of state-of-the-art laser technology has been procured under the Laser Application Support and In-house Research and Development (LASIR) contract. Work will be carried out at Air Force Research Laboratory sites at Kirtland Air Force Base in Albuquerque, New Mexico. Specific efforts include working to advance gas, hybrid electric-gas and chemical laser systems, as well as technologies related to high-power fiber lasers, fiber laser pumps, nonlinear optics, solid-state lasers and diode-pump lasers; coordinating, preparing and executing laser effects tests; rapid prototyping of directed energy technology, which includes semiconductor lasers, thin-disk lasers, ultra-short lasers, laser-based infrared countermeasures, and mid-wave and long-wave infrared lasers; and supporting the Laser Center of Excellence, a joint U.S. Defense Department and academic program that conducts work with gas, hybrid electric-gas and chemical laser systems. The Boeing Company won a $49 million U.S. Air Force contract for the work. Army Upgrades AbramsThe 435 M1A1 Abrams main battle tanks are scheduled to undergo an upgrade. The vehicles will be converted from their current configuration to the M1A2 Systems Enhancement Package (SEP) Version Two (V2) configuration. The M1A2 SEP V2 is the most technologically advanced digital tank. It includes improved displays, sights, auxiliary power and a tank-infantry telephone. In addition, it can accommodate future technology improvements to ensure compatibility with the U.S. Army’s Future Combat Systems. The Army’s Tank-automotive and Armaments Command Life Cycle Management Command awarded General Dynamics Land Systems, a business unit of General Dynamics, a multi-year contract for the upgrades. The first increment is valued at $39 million and will fund the upgrade of 20 M1A1 Abrams tanks. Over the course of the contract all remaining M1A1 tanks that have been in the Army’s inventory for more than 20 years will be modernized. Support Services for Navy AirCustomer support services will be provided to the Naval Air Systems Command Information Technology/Information Management Department. The work includes video technology support, national help desk support, Navy Marine Corps Intranet customer technical representative support, defense messaging support and embedded technical support. The work is expected to be completed in February 2009, and the estimated level of effort for the base year is 174,720 personnel hours. The tasks will be performed at the Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Patuxent River, Maryland. PSI Sierra LLC, Lexington Park, Maryland, was awarded the $7 million ceiling-priced, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract from the Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division. The contract was competitively procured under an electronic request for proposals as a 100 percent small business set-aside. Thirteen offers were received.  </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
