<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>My Two Cents About NETCENTS 2</title>
  <author>Katie Helwig</author>
  <date>March 23, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>TechNet Air 2016</tag>
    <tag>NETCENTS-2</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Robert “Gerry” Smothers, program manager, Network-Centric Solutions-2 (NETCENTS-2) offered his email to attendees at AFCEA International’s TechNet Air, being held March 22-24 in San Antonio, because “I want to know how well we are doing.”  </abstract>
  <text>Believe it or not, Robert “Gerry” Smothers, program manager for the Air Force's Network-Centric Solutions-2 (NETCENTS-2) program, offered his email to attendees at AFCEA International’s TechNet Air, being held March 22-24 in San Antonio, because “I want to know how well we are doing.”  

For small business to compete for procurement opportunities under this contract vehicle, it is necessary to hold current project management professional (PMP), capability maturity model integration (CMMI) and international organization for standardization (ISO) certifications. For those in the San Antonio area, there are immediate procurement opportunities for small business to team with NETCENTS-2 contract vehicle holders, said Smothers.

When asked the question, “Will be there an on-ramp process for NETCENTS II?” Smothers said, “no.” The contract vehicle is planning to focus on the timeline and implementation for NETCENTS III. His office is looking to the one acquisition solution for integration services (OASIS) contract vehicle for inspiration to create a point-level system to provide transparency to contract holders so each business knows where it is "racked and stacked." Zero protests have been successful under OASIS. Smothers wants to match that statistic with NETCENTS III but enhance procurement transparency. Plans are underway to roll out a NECENTS Biz Ops webpage that will house all the procurement opportunities under the contract vehicle. The procurement opportunities will be available for public viewing. Contract vehicle awardees will have a unique login and password to be able pursue opportunities.

Smothers predicts NETCENTS III to roll out in 2018. No date has been set for the NETCENTS Biz Ops webpage.

This afternoon, Smothers joins his counterparts from OASIS, NASA Solutions for Enterprise-wide Procurement (SEWP) and Federal Systems Integration and Management Center (FEDSIM) at a small business roundtable moderated by Small Business Administration representative, Sheena Little. I hope to see you there!

Katie Helwig is manager of small business programs at AFCEA International.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Robert “Gerry” Smothers, program manager, Network-Centric Solutions-2, speaks at TechNet Air in San Antonio.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
