<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Mind Your Ps &amp; Qs</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>April 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>On Cyber Patrol</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text> OK, listen up: Spot quiz. From the choice of acronym definitions below, select the ones that are correct, relevant, applicable and necessary for your immediate task set and strategic objectives. You will do this with someone barking/whining/sobbing/screaming in your ear, a flood of e-mails marked urgent clogging your mailbox, your phone(s) and Blackberry all going off simultaneously (with an embarrassing ring tone) and someone yelling to see you front and center immediately. For those in theatre, we’re going to lob a mortar round or two nearby for added excitement. EKMS Electronic Key Management Systems Enterprise Knowledge Management System Electromagnetic Kinetic Myocardial Synapse  IAVA                Iraq and Afghanistan Veterans of America Information Assurance Vulnerability Alert International Association of Virtual Assistants DAA    Designated Approving Authority Digest Access Authentication Dieticians Association of Australia DSAWGDISN Security Accreditation Working Group Defense IA Security Accreditation Working Group Dedicated Solicitors Against Wandering Grapevines CDTABCentralized Designated Tabulation Adjustment Board Cross Domain Technical Advisory Board Compact Disk Throwaway Ancillary Binding PKIProtein Kinase Inhibitors Public Key Infrastructure Performance Key Indicators IA         Insurance Agent Information Assurance Instantly Available The point is—and yes, there is a point—that the IA world is just as acronym-filled as our non-military lives. Many of these acronyms are confusing, redundant, multi-meaning and sometimes just plain wrong (on so many levels). So how do you decipher this alphabet soup? What would SGT Firewall do? There are three approaches that work best when applied together. FT: Formal Training. Make sure you are up to date on your certifications and training. And take notes this time! II: Individual Initiative. Few of us have the luxury of a full time mentor. Take it upon yourself to get up to speed on the applicable acronyms as you take on a position or duty. LTSWKWTHTATA: Listen to Someone Who Knows What the Heck They Are Talking About. This one is self-explanatory.If you have IA responsibilities (and just about everyone does), what you do and how you do it could have a significant impact on the security of Army personnel and the success of ongoing operations. It is worth being sure you know what you are talking about—down to the letter.The On Cyber Patrol© cartoon and supporting articles are created and made available by the U.S. Army’s Office of Information Assurance and Compliance, NETCOM, CIO/G6.  For more information on the OCP program or to submit ideas for upcoming cartoons/articles contact oncyberpatrol@hqda.army.mil.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
