<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Wounded Warrior, Family Get Permanent Home </title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>March 22, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>TechNet Air 2016</tag>
    <tag>wounded warriors</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Ryan Proscia and his family now have a home. That wasn't always the case. The 28-year-old wounded Army corporal and his wife of seven years, Jennifer Proscia, used to rely on the generosity of family and friends for a roof over their heads—even if just temporarily. When their luck ran out, they said they just did not know what they were going to do. Military Warriors Support Foundation ensured they wouldn't have to find out.</abstract>
  <text>Ryan Proscia and his family now have a home. 

That wasn't always the case. The 28-year-old wounded Army corporal and his wife of seven years, Jennifer Proscia, used to rely on the generosity of family and friends for a roof over their heads—even if just temporarily. When their luck ran out, they said they just did not know what they were going to do.

Military Warriors Support Foundation ensured they wouldn't have to find out.

Through the organization's efforts Proscia, Jennifer and their two young daughters on Tuesday received keys to their very own home in Spring Hill, Florida.

“This is everything to us,” Jennifer Proscia said after a presentation made at AFCEA International’s inaugural TechNet Air Symposium in San Antonio on Tuesday. “I’m still shaking,” her husband added.

Information technology services company Diligent Consulting, based in San Antonio, sponsored the Proscia’s home, working with a donor bank to provide the foreclosed property to the Proscia family.

“We want to give back to our veterans. It’s something that we’re able to do and the need is so great,” said Diligent Consulting CEO Dave Cerminaro. Over the past 5 years, the company has sponsored six homes to wounded veterans through the Military Warriors Support Foundation.

The charitable organization also provides a three year long mentorship program for recipients who learn to budget money to save, pay real estate taxes and keep their home, Cerminaro said.

Nationwide, the foundation has donated more than 700 homes to wounded troops and gold star families. They also provide other programs, such as pick up and drop off services to get wounded warriors to medical appointments, and the donations of free, new vehicles to combat veterans and gold star spouses. The foundation’s Skills4Life effort provides hunting, fishing and golf outings to wounded troops, getting people together who have served or experienced similar circumstances in activities that can provide a path toward healing, said Lt. Gen. Leroy Sisco, USA (Ret.), CEO and founder of Military Warriors Support Foundation.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Ryan Proscia (center in dark blue) and his wife Jennifer (l) receive keys to a new home in Florida donated by Military Warriors Support Foundation, Bank of America and sponsored by Diligent Consulting.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
