<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Procures Submarine Imaging Systems</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 28, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>submarine</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lockheed Martin is being awarded a contract modification for five AN/BVY-1 Integrated Submarine Imaging Systems and associated spare parts.</abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Mission Systems and Training, Manassas, Virginia, is being awarded a $9,500,548 cost-plus-incentive-fee modification to previously awarded contract N00024-09-C-6247 to procure five AN/BVY-1 Integrated Submarine Imaging Systems (ISIS) and associated spare parts. The ISIS provides mission critical, all-weather, visual and electronic search, digital image management, indication, warning and platform architecture interface capabilities for SSN 688 (Los Angeles class); SSN 21 (Seawolf class); SSGN (Ohio class); SSN 774 (Virginia class); (Ohio class) submarines; and potentially other submarines. ISIS rolls-up existing components and near term capabilities, and provides a robust architecture for efficiently inserting future capabilities as they become available for Technical Insertion Advance Processor Builds (TI/APB) Submarine Warfare Federated System process. Work will be performed in Manassas, Virginia (58 percent); Northampton, Massachusetts (19 percent); Marion, Massachusetts (12 percent); and Chantilly, Virginia (11 percent), and is expected to be complete March 2018. Fiscal 2016 other procurement (Navy); and fiscal 2016 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) funding in the amount of $9,500,548 will be obligated at time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Lockheed Martin is being awarded a contract modification for five AN/BVY-1 Integrated Submarine Imaging Systems and associated spare parts.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
