<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Exercises Sonar Technology Insertion Options</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 14, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>sonar</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lockheed Martin Corp. is being awarded a contract modification for the production and support of Acoustic Rapid Commercial off-the-shelf Insertion (A-RCI) systems for the U.S. submarine fleet. A-RCI is a sonar system that integrates and improves towed array, hull array, sphere array, and other ship sensor processing, through rapid insertion of commercial off-the-shelf-based hardware and software.</abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Corp., Mission Systems and Training, Manassas, Virginia, is being awarded a $20,516,392 modification to a previously awarded contract (N00024-11-C-6294) to exercise options for the production and support of Acoustic Rapid Commercial off-the-shelf Insertion (A-RCI) systems for the U.S. submarine fleet. A-RCI is a sonar system that integrates and improves towed array, hull array, sphere array and other ship sensor processing, through rapid insertion of commercial off-the-shelf-based hardware and software. This modification provides for continued A-RCI Technology Insertion-14 hardware deliveries. Work will be performed in Manassas, Virginia (95 percent); and Syracuse, New York (five percent), and is expected to be completed by March 2019. Fiscal 2016 other procurement (Navy); and fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funding in the amount of $20,516,392 will be obligated at time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Lockheed Martin Corp. is being awarded a contract modification for the production and support of Acoustic Rapid Commercial off-the-shelf Insertion (A-RCI) systems for the U.S. submarine fleet. A-RCI is a sonar system that integrates and improves towed array, hull array, sphere array, and other ship sensor processing, through rapid insertion of commercial off-the-shelf-based hardware and software. </img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
