<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Awarded $1 Billion Next Generation Jammer Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 14, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>jammer system</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., El Segundo, California, is being awarded a $1,012,928,257 cost-plus-incentive-fee contract for the design, manufacture, integration, demonstration and test of 15 Next Generation Jammer (NGJ) engineering development model pods in support of the engineering and manufacturing development phase of the NGJ program. The NGJ system is a pod-based tactical jammer that replaces the 40-plus-year ALQ-99 jammer system on the EA-18G aircraft. This contract also provides for the manufacture of 14 NGJ aero-mechanical test pods, which will be used to verify aircraft flying qualities and pod safe separation from the host aircraft; provide equipment needed for system integration laboratories; and mature manufacturing processes. Work will be performed in El Segundo, California (49.5 percent); Forrest, Mississippi (14.7 percent); Dallas, Texas (13.9 percent); McKinney, Texas (8.1 percent); Torrance, California (5.5 percent); Ft. Wayne, Indiana (4.2 percent); Marion, Virginia (1.6 percent); San Diego, California (1.4 percent); Andover, Massachusetts (0.8 percent); and Tucson, Arizona (0.3 percent), and is expected to be completed in December 2020. Fiscal 2016 research, development, testing and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $134,608,248 will be obligated at time of award, none of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured pursuant to 10 U.S. Code § 2304(c)(1). The Naval Air Systems Command, Patuxent River, Maryland, is the contracting activity (N00019-16-C-0002).</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Raytheon is being awarded a $1,012,928,257 contract for the design, manufacture, integration, demonstration and test of 15 Next Generation Jammer engineering development model pods .</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
