<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Office of Naval Research Awards $800 Million Electromagnetic Maneuver Warfare Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 26, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>electronic warfare</tag>
    <tag>Communications</tag>
    <tag>C4ISR</tag>
    <tag>Office of Naval Research</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin, Moorestown, New Jersey (N00014-16-D-2002); ArgonST, Fairfax, Virginia (N00014-16-D-2003); Northrop Grumman, Linthicum, Maryland (N00014-16-D-2004); Raytheon Integrated Defense Systems Advanced Technology Programs, Tewksbury, Massachusetts (N00014-16-D-2005); EOIR Technologies, King George, Virginia (N00014-16-D-2006); SI2 Technologies, North Billerica, Massachusetts (N00014-16-D-2007); S2 Corp., Bozeman, Montana (N00014-16-D-2008); Sea Corp., Middletown, Rhode Island (N00014-16-D-2009); Leidos, Arlington, Virginia (N00014-16-D-2010); Rockwell Collins, Cedar Rapids, Iowa (N00014-16-D-2011); Physical Optics Corp., Torrance, California (N00014-16-D-2012); and TiCom Geomantics, Austin, Texas (N00014-16-D-2013), are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, multiple award contract. The maximum dollar value for all 12 contracts combined is $800,000,000. The purpose of the Electromagnetic Maneuver Warfare Command and Control program is to identify the study, design, fabrication, integration and test and evaluation tasks anticipated for the development and demonstration of a set of prototypes, and their component subsystems, that integrate radio frequency (RF) functionality electronic warfare, radar, communications, information operations into a common set of multi-function apertures, electronics and software/firmware through an architecture that is modular, scalable across platforms and open at the RF, electronics and software/firmware levels. These prototypes will be capable of providing multiple, simultaneous, independent beams that can together perform any of the above functions. In addition, these open RF systems will be integrated with previously developed Integrated Topside or other RF systems, and with combat and command, control, communications, computers, intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance systems. These integrated systems will enable resource allocation, real-time spectrum operations, emissions control, and electromagnetic maneuver to improve the Navy’s ability to achieve information dominance. These 12 contractors may compete for task orders under the terms and conditions of the awarded contract. Therefore, the work could be performed in Moorestown, New Jersey; Fairfax, Virginia; Linthicum, Maryland; Tewksbury, Massachusetts; King George, Virginia; North Billerica, Massachusetts; Bozeman, Montana; Middletown, Rhode Island; Arlington, Virginia; Cedar Rapids, Iowa; Torrance, California; and Austin, Texas. The work is expected to be completed April 24, 2021. No funds will be obligated at the time of award. Future task orders will be funded with fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds.  Funds will not expire at end of current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured under solicitation N00014-16-R-0012 entitled, “Electromagnetic Maneuver Warfare Command and Control” (EMC2). Twelve proposals were received in response to the solicitation. The Office of Naval Research, Arlington, Virginia, is the contracting activity. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
