<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Brings World-Class Training to You</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA International’s Professional Development Center offers time-proven C4I courses that are internationally recognized for excellence and taught by world-class instructors.</abstract>
  <text>AFCEA International’s Professional Development Center offers time-proven C4I courses that are internationally recognized for excellence and taught by world-class instructors. Customers such as the U.S. Coast Guard Communications Command, U.S. Army Strategic Initiatives Group, U.S. Army Communications-Electronics Research, Development and Engineering Center, U.S. Navy Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command Systems Center Pacific, Offutt Air Force Base, Canadian Forces School of Communication, L-3 Global Communications Solutions, Sandia Labs, Hewlett Packard and Tobyhanna Army Depot have benefitted from AFCEA’s courses. By taking courses to the client, customers significantly save on the cost of airfare, billeting, per diem, etc. AFCEA instructors tailor courses for the students of the sponsoring organization. These courses include:

DOD Architecture Framework Implementation

The design of architectures has become a fundamental component of the architecture-based systems engineering approach required by the Defense Department and other government agencies. The architectures should be described in accordance with the current version (2.02) of the Department of Defense Architecture Framework (DoDAF). The course consists of lectures, interactive sessions and work sessions in which participants, organized into small teams, work through an example problem to produce an architecture from which selected models and viewpoints described in the DoDAF 2.02 compliance form are generated. This course focuses on architecture design using a system’s engineering approach based on object orientation and includes service orientation. The Unified Modeling Language (UML) is used as the architecture description language. In addition to the development of a DoDAF-compliant architecture description that is fit for purpose, the derivation of executable models from the architecture data is presented and their role in architecture evaluation is illustrated. The approach is then applied to the evaluation of system-of-systems architecture and resilient architectures for C2.

High Frequency Automated Radio 

In the 100 years since Marconi demonstrated trans-Atlantic communications, high frequency (HF) radio has matured from a quirky, temperamental medium requiring highly trained operators to a reliable, low-cost, automated technology with global reach. This course was developed to satisfy the need of government and industry worldwide to understand and apply 2G and 3G HF systems, and the exciting new wideband (WBHF) technology for video over HF radio. This course helps military officers, government personnel and industry managers understand the opportunities and challenges presented by HF radio communications as well as the ability of the new generations of HF radio technology to overcome the difficulties and provide reliable and economical long-range communications.

Military Satellite Communications In A Net-Centric Communications World

Satellite communications dominate current and planned military and government communications systems and make network-centric warfare possible. This course provides a review of current and future military satellite communications. Internet protocol (IP) and IP over satellite (IPoS) are addressed showing this protocol’s strengths and weaknesses as a facilitator of network-centric warfare. All of the current and future military and commercial satellite systems are described, including the evolution of military satellite communications. Course topics provide a perspective of satellite communications for military applications.

Principles of Communications and Networking 

The critical role of communications and networking in the defense community has been widely recognized. The field is broad and dynamic; while progress proceeds at a phenomenal pace, new issues and problems arise almost as fast. The underlying principles, however, change either slowly or not at all. A conceptual understanding of these principles can help those who work in all aspects of the field see the forest through the ever-changing trees. This course presents an introduction to the technical concepts that underlie the field: analog and digital communications; packet and circuit switching; voice and data networks; and the physics of radio, terrestrial and satellite links.

The U.S. Intelligence Community: An Overview 

This course provides a broad overview of the roles, functions, activities and current issues facing the U.S. intelligence community and targets government, military, academic and contractor professionals working in the field. It provides a firm basis for understanding the community’s roles, needs and culture, and the issues they face today as the community deals with a new structure and emerging threats. Instructors place special emphasis on the ongoing changes in U.S. intelligence, the issues these changes raise, the changes that have been implemented since 2001 and how they are progressing. This course comprises several modules to include: Structure &amp; Missions; U.S. National Security Threats in the 21st Century; Collection Disciplines; Intelligence Analysis; and Congress and the Intelligence Community.

These courses, provided by AFCEA’s Professional Development Center, are taught by highly regarded professionals in the applicable fields of knowledge. Feedback received has been tremendously positive. For more information, please contact Gloria Kirkland at pdc@afcea.org or 703-631-6137.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
