<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Make a Difference in the Intelligence Community</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>May 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The AFCEA Intelligence Committee is looking for a few good men and women from industry to share their expertise by serving as members of the committee. The group comprises intelligence professionals from both the public and private sectors who volunteer to oversee AFCEA’s intelligence outreach.Committee members attend monthly meetings at AFCEA International in Fairfax, Virginia, and support two symposia each year. In addition, they have the opportunity to influence the course materials used in AFCEA professional development courses by contributing ideas based on their expertise. Periodically, Intelligence Committee members also have contributed article ideas that have been followed up by SIGNAL Magazine and SIGNAL Connections staff. By serving as an intelligence community resource for AFCEA’s leadership, committee members further the association’s efforts to reach out to the intelligence community at large and facilitate a much-needed dialogue among respected professionals.While government members of the Intelligence Committee are appointed by their organizations to serve, commercial-sector professionals must be elected. The application process currently is open to members of industry who support the intelligence community, are U.S. citizens and possess a Top Secret clearance with SI/TK access.Applications must be received no later than July 31, 2008. Elections will be held in September. All candidates will be advised of the election results by September 22, 2008.And Speaking of Reaching Out…Entries for the AFCEA Intelligence Committee’s annual writing contest are now being accepted. The competition aims to expand knowledge and dialogue about pertinent issues in the intelligence community. The contest offers intelligence professionals at all levels the opportunity to express themselves on a topic of importance to the community and national security.This year’s topic is “Guidelines for Developing, Nurturing and Leading Intelligence Professionals.” The writing should be based on the following scenario: “The real capital of the intelligence community is its people. Yet many argue that the community invests more in deploying technology than it does in taking care of its human resource. You have 30 minutes with the next Director of National Intelligence and the president of the United States. What recommendations do you have for them regarding the development, nurturing and leadership of the people of the intelligence community?”Essays must be submitted by midnight, Eastern Standard Time, October 31, 2008, and be no longer than 2,500 words, excluding footnotes and bibliography. First prize is $2,000, a two-year membership in AFCEA, the AFCEA Medallion and the possibility of publication in SIGNAL Magazine; second prize is $1,000 and a two-year membership in AFCEA; and third prize is $500 and a two-year membership in AFCEA.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
