<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Exelis Awarded Two SENSOR Contract Modifications</title>
  <author/>
  <date>April 29, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Exelis Inc.</tag>
    <tag>missile defense</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Exelis Inc., Colorado Springs, Colorado, has been awarded a $58,018,301 modification (P00642) to previously awarded contract F19628-02-C-0010 for System Engineering and Sustainment Integrator (SENSOR) Ballistic Missile Early Warning System Pave Phased Array Warning System (BPP) sustainment support projects. Contractor will maintain the sustainment posture of the BPP systems, which include field service team, mission assurance, system program agency operations and weapon system management and engineering. Work will be performed at Fylingdales Air Base, United Kingdom; Thule Air Force Station, Greenland; Clear Air Force Station, Alaska; Beale Air Force Base, California; Cape Cod Air Force Station, Massachusetts and Peterson Air Force Base, Colorado, and is expected to be complete by April 30, 2017. Fiscal 2016 operation and maintenance funds in the amount of $30,046,241 are being obligated at the time of award.

The company also was awarded a $15,439,296 modification (P00638) to the same contract for the SENSOR Perimeter Acquisition Radar Attack Characterization System (PARCS) sustainment support projects. Contractor will maintain the sustainment posture of the PARCS systems, which includes weapons system management and engineering, systems engineering, hardware repairs and spares and licenses and subscriptions. Work will be performed at Cavalier Air Force Station, North Dakota, and Colorado Springs, Colorado, and is expected to be complete by April 30, 2018. Fiscal 2016 operations and maintenance funds in the amount of $7,666,515 are being obligated at the time of award. The Air Force Life Cycle Management Center, Peterson Air Force Base, Colorado, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
