<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Long-Range Anti-Ship Missile Begins Next Phase</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 16, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>anti-ship missile</tag>
    <tag>JASSM</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Missiles and Fire Control, Orlando, Florida, is being awarded a $321,847,403 cost-plus-incentive-fee contract for research and development in support of the Long Range Anti-Ship Missile (LRASM) integration and test phase. The integration and test phase completes all remaining hardware and software detailed design; systemically retiring any open risks; building and testing missile test articles to verify compliance with capability requirements; and preparing for production and/or deployment. This phase also completes full system integration; incorporates an affordable and executable LRASM manufacturing process into the existing Joint Air-to-Surface Standoff Missile – Extended Range production process; examines and defines the logistics footprint; designs for producibility; ensures affordability; protects critical program information by implementing appropriate techniques such as anti-tamper and cybersecurity; and demonstrates system integration, interoperability, safety and utility. Work will be performed in Orlando, Florida (60 percent); Troy, Alabama (30 percent); and Ocala, Florida (10 percent), and is expected to be completed in August, 2019. Fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $42,000,000 will be obligated at time of award, none of which will expire at the end of the fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured pursuant to Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-1. The Naval Air Systems Command, Patuxent River, Maryland, is the contracting activity (N00019-16-C-0035).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
