<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Two Companies to Research On-Orbit Reprogrammable Digital Waveform Generator</title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 18, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman</tag>
    <tag>Boeing</tag>
    <tag>GPS</tag>
    <tag>Air Force Research Laboratory</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Northrop Grumman Systems Corp., Redondo Beach, California, has been awarded a $13,501,251 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for the On-Orbit Reprogrammable Digital Waveform Generator (ORDWG) program. The contractor will perform the research and development activities necessary to define and validate an ORDWG design and architecture that is capable of all current and projected navigation signals and modulations and will operate securely in a contested cyber environment. Work will be performed at Redondo Beach, California, and is expected to be completed by November 24, 2020. This award is the result of a competitive acquisition with nine offers received. Fiscal year 2015 and fiscal year 2016 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $3,840,769 are being obligated at the time of award. The Air Force Research Laboratory, Kirtland Air Force Base, New Mexico, is the contracting activity (FA9453-16-C-0010).

In addition, the Boeing Co., El Segundo, California, has been awarded a $16,155,968 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for the On-Orbit Reprogrammable Digital Waveform Generator program. The contractor will advance the state-of-the art in signal generation, such as the Global Positioning System and other commercial and noncommercial position navigation and timing efforts. Work will be performed at Huntington Beach, California, and is expected to be completed by January 24, 2021. This award is the result of a competitive acquisition with nine offers received. Fiscal year 2015 and fiscal year 2016 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $8,300,000 are being obligated at the time of award. The Air Force Research Laboratory, Kirtland Air Force Base, New Mexico, is the contracting activity (FA9453-16-C-0011).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
