<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Lockheed Awarded $357 Million in AEGIS Funds</title>
  <author/>
  <date>June 27, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>AEGIS Combat System</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Mission Systems &amp; Sensors, Moorestown, New Jersey, is being awarded a $357,018,057 cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for Advanced Electronic Guidance and Instrumentation System (AEGIS) in-service combat systems engineering; computer program maintenance; annual inspection and regular overhaul execution support; in-country support; staging; replacement of legacy cathode ray tube character readout devices for Japan; logistics depot support for Norway unique line replaceable units; and AEGIS implementation studies for future Foreign Military Sales (FMS) AEGIS shipbuilding programs to fulfill AEGIS lifetime support requirements of the Japan Maritime Self Defense Force, Republic of Korea Navy, Spanish Armada, Royal Australian Navy and Royal Norwegian Navy. This contract includes options, which if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to $421,031,155. This contract combines purchases for the governments of Japan (49.6 percent); Korea (27.9 percent); Norway (16.4 percent); Australia (5.1 percent); and Spain (1 percent), under the FMS program. Work will be performed in Moorestown, New Jersey (84.00 percent); Adelaide, Australia (5.20 percent); Changwon, South Korea (3.28 percent); Tokyo, Japan (1.26 percent); Busan, South Korea (1.07 percent); Washington, District of Columbia (1.14 percent); Nagasaki, Japan (0.96  percent); Bergen, Norway (0.90 percent); Maizuru, Japan (0.87 percent); Yokosuka, Japan (0.69 percent); Yokohama, Japan (0.48 percent); Port Hueneme, California (0.08 percent); and Sydney, Australia (0.07 percent), and is expected to be completed by November 2019. FMS funding in the amount of $86,154,657 will be obligated at time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1) and 10 U.S. Code 2304 (c)(4) - only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements and international agreement, respectively. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity (N00024-16-C-5103).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
