<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Preferred Providers Offer Value to AFCEA Members</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>education</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Continue your education through one of AFCEA’s preferred providers. Earn advanced degrees and certifications at your own pace, according to your schedule, through a flexible online or classroom environment—and at a discounted rate as a member of AFCEA.</abstract>
  <text>Continue your education through one of AFCEA’s preferred providers. Earn advanced degrees and certifications at your own pace, according to your schedule, through a flexible online or classroom environment—and at a discounted rate as a member of AFCEA.

Part of AFCEA’s mission is to bring together military, government, industry and academia to increase knowledge through the exploration of issues related to information technology, communications and electronics for the defense, homeland security and intelligence communities. AFCEA members are lifelong learners, continuously striving to expand their knowledge and advance their expertise. To this end, AFCEA has partnered with American Public University System (APUS), the National Cybersecurity Institute (NCI) at Excelsior College, SANS Institute and Walden University to bring training and certification opportunities at affordable prices to its members. 

Mike Harbert, vice president, strategic relationships, APUS, states, “American Public University System is proud to partner with AFCEA to provide members increasing opportunities for professional development, education and training that support critical mission areas.”

Bray Barnes, director, NCI, adds, “Understanding the unique demands of the AFCEA professional, the National Cybersecurity Institute works collaboratively with members to identify, design and deliver training and education, both face-to-face and online, that meets their unique and specific needs.”

AFCEA preferred providers offer degrees and certificate programs with the flexibility of both classroom and online study venues. The option of online courses, scheduled at the member’s convenience, provides a great way for AFCEA members to continue their education while serving in the military or supporting those who serve. State-of-the-art learning techniques along with relevant course material make AFCEA’s preferred provider courses optimal for today’s busy AFCEA professional.

Areas of study include cybersecurity, Department of Defense 8570 compliance, software development and engineering, as well as project management, government analytics, global security studies, public management and leadership.

For more information visit AFCEA’s preferred provider page at www.afcea.org/site/?q=education/preferred-providers or contact Gloria Kirkland in the Professional Development Center at 703-631-6137 or pdc@afcea.org.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
