<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Awards Northrop Grumman $103 Million for JCREW System</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Department of the Navy</tag>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman Corporation</tag>
    <tag>Contract  Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>U.S. Navy awards Northrop Grumman $103 million contract for JCREW system</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Navy awarded Northrop Grumman Systems Corporation, Herndon, Virginia, with a $103,423,433 fixed-price, firm-fixed price, cost-plus-fixed-fee and cost-only modification to previously awarded contract (N00024-15-C-6327) for Joint Counter Radio-Controlled Improvised Explosive Device (RCIED) Electronic Warfare, Joint Crew (JCREW) Increment one build one (I1B1) systems low-rateinitial production to support the expeditionary warfare program office. JCREW systems provide combat troops protection against RCIEDs and are designed to provide protection for foot soldiers, vehicles and buildings. The JCREW I1B1 is the first generation system that develops a common open architecture across all three capabilities and provides protection for worldwide military operations. This integrated design maximizes commonality across all capabilities, reduces life cycle costs and increases protection against worldwide threats. JCREW is a joint program supporting both Navy and Air Force requirements under the management of Naval Sea Systems Command. Work will be performed in San Diego, (53 percent); Beaverton, Oregon (23 percent); Rochester, Minnesota (15 percent); Santa Ana, California (5 percent); and Sierra Vista, Arizona (4 percent), and is expected to be complete by September 28, 2018. Fiscal year 2014 and 2015 other procurement (Navy); and fiscal 2015 and 2016 procurement (USAF) funding in the amount of $103,423,433 will be obligated at time of award. Funding in the amount of $21,132,145 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
