<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Retired Navy Adm. James Stavridis Being Vetted as Clinton VP </title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>July 13, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>International</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Hillary Clinton is considering a SIGNAL Magazine Incoming columnist and current contributing editor as her running mate on the Democratic presidential ticket. Adm. James G. Stavridis, USN (Ret.) has made Clinton’s short list as she considers candidates for vice president.</abstract>
  <text>Hillary Clinton is considering a SIGNAL Magazine Incoming columnist and current contributing editor as her running mate on the Democratic presidential ticket.

Adm. James G. Stavridis, USN (Ret.), has made Clinton’s short list as she considers candidates for vice president, according to several media organizations.

Adm. Stavridis penned more than a dozen columns last year for SIGNAL Magazine, offering viewpoints on current and sometimes contentious topics, such as Iran’s nuclear capabilities; advances in biology that that will usurp information and cyber as the next big revolution in national security; and tensions in the South China Sea.  

He retired as a four-star in 2013 and served as the 16th Supreme Allied Commander for NATO and head of the U.S. European Command from 2009 to 2013. He currently serves as the dean of the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University, from which he holds a Ph.D. in international law. He is chairman of the U.S. Naval Institute’s board of directors.

Stavridis, 61, is well known and respected within military and international security circles, but is a lesser-known figure to the general population. When contacted by SIGNAL, Adm. Stavridis declined to comment and directed inquiries to the Clinton campaign. The campaign has not replied to a query seeking comment.

A Florida native, Stavridis attended the U.S. Naval Academy at Annapolis and dedicated 30 years to military service. In addition to serving as NATO’s leader, where he oversaw operations in Afghanistan, Libya, Syria, the Balkans and piracy off the coast of Africa, he commanded the U.S. Southern Command in Florida and was the longest serving combatant commander in recent U.S. history. In 2012, he shared thoughts on global security for a TED Talk.

A former U.S. military member also has made the short vice presidential consideration list for presumptive Republican nominee Donald Trump, who reportedly will announce his selection within days. Trump is considering Lt. Gen. Michael T. Flynn, USA (Ret.), former head of the Defense Intelligence Agency.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Adm. James G. Stavridis, USN (Ret.), dean of the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy and former supreme allied commander Europe, describes the global threat picture to attendees at West 2016 in San Diego in February.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
