<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>AFCEA Small Businesses Launches 3-part Contracting Series</title>
  <author>Katie Helwig</author>
  <date>July 7, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>AFCEA</tag>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA International presents its next three-session contracting series, Growing Your Business in the Federal Contracting Arena, kicking off the courses with former chief operating officer and author David Kriegman, who will share his expertise and experiences in growing a small business into a billion dollar corporation. Time is running out to register.</abstract>
  <text>AFCEA International presents its next three-session contracting series, Growing Your Business in the Federal Contracting Arena, kicking off the courses with former chief operating officer and author David Kriegman, who will share his expertise and experiences in growing a small business into a billion dollar corporation.

The first session, titled "How to Take Your Company to the Next Level," tees off July 19 at General Dynamics IT in Springfield, Virginia. This interactive session prepares companies for "full and open" acquisition capture and offers tangible tips on how to beat larger companies for coveted contracts. The course combines collaborative instruction, a topical panel discussion and an engaging networking reception to build a cache of business partners.

“We’ve reevaluated our business capture approach, company messaging and networking strategy based on the information presented at February’s course,” says Greg Rosa, director of capture management and teaming Solutions at Aquila Technology Corp. “Aquila’s relationship with AFCEA and our exposure to the learning series has been invaluable, and we look forward to the next educational opportunity.”

Guy Timberlake's federal contracting experience and small business advocacy makes him a perfect choice to moderate this session’s panel of experts:

Ludmilla Parnell, director of business development and small business partnerships for General Dynamics Information Technology
	Ralph Buona, vice present of business Development for Telos Corporation
	Kevin Carroll, president of the Kevin Carroll Group and a former government procurement executive officer.
The second session in the series, titled "Building Your Brand—Your Company's Culture is the Differentiator," takes place October 27 at CACI in Reston, Virginia. This session will discuss how companies can build their brand to attract and retain quality employees, partners and customers. Hilton Worldwide and Karen Trowbridge, president and CEO of Trowbridge &amp; Trowbridge, will engage the fall panel.

Finally, the last session of the series will take place on April 11 at CSRA in Falls Church, Virginia. This course will focus on writing a winning proposal and preparing for a contract recompete.

Courses are reserved for corporate member associates and active government personnel who are AFCEA members.

    $295 for industry
	    $25 for active government
AFCEA offers an industry bundled rate of $795 for the series of three. Those interested in registering as a government member or who would like to register for the series can email Katie Helwig for the special registration links.

Not a corporate member? Why not? Contact us to discuss how a corporate membership in a key component in growing your business in the federal market space.

July's event is brought to you in part by support of bronze sponsor and patron Argotis Inc. and General Dynamics IT. There are only two more sponsor opportunities available for the series. Email Katie for details.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img></img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
