<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Army's Cyber Quest Underway in Georgia</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 14, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Army</tag>
    <tag>Cybersecurity</tag>
    <tag>electronic warfare</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Army is testing how cyberwarriors adjust to morphing cyber threats and electromagnetic warfare (EW) attacks during its Cyber Quest 2016, an exercise now underway at the Cyber Center of Excellence at Fort Gordon, Georgia. The event examines concepts and products that could influence future technologies and requirements as well as other Army and Defense Department exercises and experiments.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Army is testing how cyberwarriors adjust to morphing cyber threats and electromagnetic warfare (EW) attacks during its Cyber Quest 2016, an exercise now underway at the Cyber Center of Excellence at Fort Gordon, Georgia. The event examines concepts and products that could influence future technologies and requirements as well as other Army and Defense Department exercises and experiments.

The event runs through July 29 and includes an infantry brigade combat team command post from the 25th Infantry Division at Schofield Barracks, Hawaii; a dismounted platoon from 1st Battalion, 29th Infantry Regiment at Fort Benning, Georgia; command post personnel from the 305th Military Intelligence Battalion at Fort Huachuca, Arizona; and the Fires Battle Lab at Fort Sill, Oklahoma.

The cyberspace and EW research and development community is represented by a host of Army organizations and more than 10 commercial vendors, Army officials said in a statement.

Experts attending the annual Cyber Quest event assess new cyber and EW technologies and concepts to gauge how they perform against requirements. Technologies include tactical radios that offer near-silent operation and direction-finding capabilities and can prevent enemy EW systems from detecting or disrupting friendly force communications.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
