<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>FLIR to Provide Electro-Optics Sensors</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 18, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>FLIR Systems Inc.</tag>
    <tag>electro-optical sensors</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>FLIR Surveillance Inc., Wilsonville, Oregon, is being awarded a $13,346,312 firm-fixed-price, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for electro-optics sensor (EOS) systems for both Sea Star Safire III and Brite Star II systems. The services under this contract cover provision item ordering spares, repairs, field repair, technical assists, travel, training and data. The Sea Star Safire III EOS system is a rugged and ship-mountable system to provide surface ships with a day/night, high-resolution, infrared and visible-band imaging capability as well as range-finding capability to augment existing optical and radar sensors to detect and identify asymmetric threats. The Brite Star II EOS system functions as the fire control system for the Patrol Coastal Griffin Missile System. It uses infrared and charged coupler device cameras to detect, identify and track targets. Brite Star II uses a laser range finder to determine the distance and position of the target and provides terminal guidance to the launched Griffin Missile seeker head with a laser designator. Work will be performed in Wilsonville and is expected to be completed by July 2021. Fiscal 2016 working capital funds (Navy) in the amount of $900 will be obligated at the time of award and will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1); only one responsible source, and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements. The Naval Surface Warfare Center, Crane, Indiana, is the contracting activity (N00164-16-D-JQ96). 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
