<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DHS Seeks Mobile Security Solutions</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 18, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Homeland Security</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DHS</tag>
    <tag>Cybersecurity</tag>
    <tag>mobile communications</tag>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>science and technology</tag>
    <tag>research and development</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Department of Homeland Security Science and Technology Directorate will host two industry days to provide additional insights to the mobile and cellular industry and researchers about the Mobile Threats and Defenses request for information (RFI).</abstract>
  <text>The Department of Homeland Security Science and Technology (S&amp;T) Directorate will host two industry days to provide additional insights to the mobile and cellular industry and researchers about the Mobile Threats and Defenses request for information (RFI). The events take place July 20 in Washington, D.C., and August 2 in Menlo Park, California. 

The RFI invites industry and the research community to share information about threats and vulnerabilities to the mobile devices federal government personnel use and seeks insights to capitalize on existing and potential technology solutions. In addition, the department is interested in best practices for mitigating potential threats and vulnerabilities.  

The department’s S&amp;T cybersecurity division will use the RFI responses to prepare a report to Congress focused on mobile device security. The report is expected to be delivered to Congress in December.

The deadline to respond to this RFI is August 22.

The DHS also has released the "Integrated Product Teams for Department of Homeland Security R&amp;D Fiscal Year 2016 Report," which identifies 24 focus areas for technological research and development in five mission categories: aviation security, biological threats, border security, cybersecurity and counterterrorism.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
