<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Awards Simulation Task Orders</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 16, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>simulation and training</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Logistics Services International Inc. and Technical Software Services Inc., are awarded contracts to provide reengineering, development and personal computer-simulation services in support of Naval Education Training Command’s Naval Training Products and Services program. </abstract>
  <text>Logistics Services International Inc., Jacksonville, Florida (N00189-16-D-Z047); and Technical Software Services Inc., Pensacola, Florida (N00189-16-D-Z048), are being awarded an estimated $167,168,947 in multiple award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price task order contracts to provide reengineering, development and personal computer-simulation services in support of Naval Education Training Command’s Naval Training Products and Services program. Each contract will run concurrently and includes a 33-month base ordering period and 36-month option period. If all options are exercised, the total estimated value of all seven contracts combined will be $344,541,804. Work will be performed 100 percent in contractor facilities in response to awarded task orders and cannot be reasonably estimated at the time of contract award. Work is expected to be completed by May 2019; if all options are exercised, work will be completed by May 2022. Fiscal 2016 operations and maintenance (Navy) funds in the amount of $5,000 will be obligated on each of the contracts to fund the contract's minimum amount, and will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured with the solicitation posted to the Federal Business Opportunities online website, with nine offers received. The Naval Supply Systems Command Fleet Logistics Center Norfolk Contracting Department, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
