<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Companies to Support Joint Staff’s C4/Cyber Program</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 24, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Joint Staff</tag>
    <tag>C4</tag>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Virginia (N00189-16-D-Z039); Lockheed Martin Missiles and Fire Control, Orlando, Florida (N00189-16-D-Z040); Science Applications International Corp., McLean, Virginia (N00189-16-D-Z041); Leidos Inc., Reston, Virginia (N00189-16-D-Z042); and Deloitte Consulting LLP, Arlington, Virginia (N00189-16-D-Z043), are being awarded a combined estimated $155,770,425 multiple award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, firm-fixed-price task orders contract to obtain analytical, engineering and project/program management services in support of the Joint Staff J6 Directorate's C4/Cyber Program. Contracts will run concurrently, and each contract includes a 60-month ordering period. Work will be performed in Norfolk/Suffolk, Virginia (49.5 percent); Eglin Air Force Base, Florida (27 percent); Arlington, Virginia (13.5 percent); and contractor facilities (10 percent). Work is expected to be completed by September 2021. Fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation (Department of Defense) funds in the amount of $50,000 will be obligated on each of the five contracts to fund the contract's minimum amount, and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. Each of the five contractors will be allowed to bid on the individual task orders as they are issued. This contract was competitively procured with the solicitation posted to the Federal Business Opportunities website, with six offers received. The Naval Supply Systems Command Fleet Logistics Center Norfolk Contracting Department, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
