<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>General Atomics to Build MQ-9 Precision Tracking Laser</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 22, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>General Atomics</tag>
    <tag>MQ-9 Reaper</tag>
    <tag>laser</tag>
    <tag>Missile Defense Agency</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>General Atomics is being awarded a contract to design, build and test in the laboratory key laser subsystems required to demonstrate precision tracking.</abstract>
  <text>General Atomics Aeronautical Systems Inc. (GA-ASI) of San Diego, California, is being awarded a $9,609,911, competitive, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract. Under this new contract, the contractor will design, build and test in the laboratory key laser subsystems required to demonstrate precision tracking. The contractor will perform systems level analyses and performance assessments based on design predictions and laboratory measurements. The contractor will develop and demonstrate, a MQ-9 flight representative laser system with the beam train optics required to upgrade a multi-spectral targeting system for use as an active tracking sensor. Under this contractual effort the contractor is to deliver a laser system sized to meet MQ-9 integration requirements. The work will be performed in San Diego, California, with an estimated completion date of September 30, 2017. This contract was competitively procured via publication on the Federal Business Opportunities website under the Missile Defense Agency's broad agency announcement for Advanced Technology Innovation (ATI), HQ0147-15-ATI-BAA. Fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $3,155,292 are being obligated on this award. In accordance with Federal Acquisition Regulation 35.006 (c), the use of a cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for this research and development effort is appropriate. This is not a Foreign Military Sales acquisition. The Missile Defense Agency, Kirtland Air Force Base, New Mexico, is the contracting activity (HQ0277-16-C-0001).</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>General Atomics is being awarded a contract to design, build and test in the laboratory key laser subsystems required to demonstrate precision tracking.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
