<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Modifies Submarine Imaging Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 26, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>Integrated Submarine Imaging System</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Mission Systems and Training, Manassas, Virginia, is being awarded a $126,292,178 cost-plus-incentive-fee modification to a previously awarded contract (N00024-09-C-6247) to exercise an option for engineering services and support of the Integrated Submarine Imaging Systems (ISIS) program. Services will include design, development, testing, reverse engineering, technology insertion/refreshment, engineering services, field engineering services and system support. The ISIS provides mission critical, all-weather, visual and electronic search, digital image management, indication, warning and platform architecture interface capabilities for SSN 688 (Los Angeles class); SSN 21 (Seawolf class); SSGN (Ohio class); SSBN (Ohio class); and SSN 774 (Virginia class) submarines, with potential for other submarines. ISIS rolls-up existing components and near term capabilities, and provides a robust architecture for efficiently inserting future capabilities as they become available for the Technical Insertion, Advanced Processing Builds, Submarine Warfare Federated System process. Work will be performed in Manassas, Virginia (73 percent); Virginia Beach, Virginia (15 percent); Northampton, Massachusetts (6 percent); Fairfax, Virginia (3 percent); Arlington, Virginia (2 percent); and Newport, Rhode Island (1 percent), and is expected to be completed by September 2017. Fiscal 2013, 2014, 2015 and 2016 other procurement (Navy); fiscal 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015 and 2016 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy); and fiscal 2014, 2015 and 2016 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $7,980,188 will be obligated at the time of award, and funds in the amount of $1,616,586 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
