<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Progeny Systems Receives Submarine C5I Funds</title>
  <author/>
  <date>August 26, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Progeny Systems</tag>
    <tag>C5I</tag>
    <tag>submarine</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Progeny Systems Corp., Manassas, Virginia, is being awarded a $31,082,204 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, performance-based contract with provisions for cost-plus-fixed-fee and firm-fixed-price task orders. The contract is for engineering and technical services for the modification and/or development of engineering tools and software, as well as the integration of hardware required to support the continued data collection of the Non-Propulsion Electronic Subsystems, Submarine Command, Control, Communications, Computers, Combat and Intelligence (C5I). The work includes instrumentation and test equipment development and associated engineering support required for the C5I System and Weapons Shipping, Handling and Launcher Integrated Test Team, and Submarine Federated Warfare Tactical Systems Integrated Management Office, in order to perform combat systems test and evaluation for new construction Virginia class submarines, and all other classes of active submarines undergoing combat systems modernization. The contract includes a single five-year ordering period. Work will be performed in Manassas, Virginia (30 percent); Norfolk, Virginia (30 percent); and Groton, Connecticut (40 percent), and is expected to be complete by August 2021. Fiscal 2011 and 2015 ship construction (Navy) funds in the amount of $940,000 will be placed on the first task order and obligated at the time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured because it is derived from efforts performed by Progeny Systems Corp. under Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phases I, II, and III in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(5), as implemented by Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-5 and 15 U.S. Code 638(r)(1) and (4). The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, South Carolina, is the contracting activity (N65236-16-D-8013).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
