<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Educational Foundation Continues Legacy of Excellence in Education</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>scholarships</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The foundation’s program of scholarships, grants and awards continues to support students, teachers, military personnel in training and future scientists and engineers in the hard science and technology disciplines.</abstract>
  <text>The AFCEA Educational Foundation’s motto, “Dedication to Excellence in Education,” is as relevant today as when the organization was established in 1979. The foundation’s program of scholarships, grants and awards continues to support students, teachers, military personnel in training and future scientists and engineers in the hard science and technology disciplines.

Although educational outreach faces challenges in this climate of underfunded programs and shrinking available dollars, the foundation, in partnership with AFCEA chapters and committees, continues the legacy set forth in its early days. The leadership and vision of its founders, Vice Adm. Jon L. Boyes, USN, and Vice Adm. Samuel L. Gravely, USN, are reflected today in the quality of AFCEA’s award programs and recipients.   

The foundation rewards study primarily in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) at both the undergraduate and graduate levels. Teachers of STEM subjects receive grants from AFCEA chapters to enhance classroom programs in these disciplines.

AFCEA’s educational programs support a unique niche in the current environment, rewarding outstanding students, teachers and military personnel. Every dollar is important for continuing and furthering this mission.  

Today’s goals are consistent with those of the past: recognizing educational excellence and partnering with corporations, chapters and individuals to continue AFCEA’s legacy. The AFCEA Educational Foundation stands as a beacon for success and remains steadfast in its focus on nurturing the next generation of STEM leaders.

Donations to the foundation can be made online at www.afcea.org/secure/sch_donate_form.asp.

Full photo caption: Mansur Hasib, chair of the graduate cybersecurity technology program at the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, presents the 2015 AFCEA STEM Major Scholarship for Diversity Students to Kiara Jones, a graduate. The scholarship was sponsored by Avaya Government Solutions. Jones received a check, a certificate and a biography written about Vice Adm. Samuel L. Gravely, USN, titled, Trailblazer: The U.S. Navy’s First Black Admiral. After his retirement from the Navy, Adm. Gravely became the first executive director of the AFCEA Educational Foundation. </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Mansur Hasib, chair of the graduate cybersecurity technology program at the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, presents the 2015 AFCEA STEM Major Scholarship for Diversity Students to Kiara Jones, a graduate.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
