<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Marines Procure Nine G/ATOR Systems</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman</tag>
    <tag>G/ATOR</tag>
    <tag>Marine Corps</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Northrop Grumman Corp., Electronic Systems, Linthicum Heights, Maryland, is being awarded a $375,582,523 four-year, fixed-price-incentive contract for the procurement of nine Ground/Air Task-Oriented Radar (G/ATOR) low-rate initial production systems. G\ATOR is managed by Program Executive Officer Land Systems, Quantico, Virginia. Work will be performed in Linthicum Heights, Maryland (55 percent); East Syracuse, New York (29 percent); Stafford Springs, Connecticut (4 percent); Tulsa, Oklahoma (2 percent); San Diego, California (2 percent); Wallingford Center, Connecticut (1 percent); Farmingdale, New York (1 percent); Gilbert, Arizona (1 percent); East Aurora, New York (1 percent); Saint Paul, Minnesota (1 percent); Londonderry, New Hampshire (1 percent); Durham, North Carolina (1 percent); and Shelby, North Carolina (1 percent), and is expected to be completed by September 2020. Fiscal 2014 procurement (Marine Corps) funds in the amount of $607,950; fiscal 2016 procurement (Marine Corps) funds in the amount of $117,944,307; and fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $621,794 will be obligated at the time of award. Contract funds in the amount of $607,950 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract is awarded as a sole-source contract in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1)(B). The Marine Corps Systems Command, Quantico, Virginia, is the contracting activity (M67854-16-C-2011).</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Northrop Grumman is being awarded a U.S. Marine Corps contract for nine low-rate initial production Ground/Air Task-Oriented Radar systems.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
