<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Marines Fund Communications Towers in Sierra Nevada Mountains</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Marine Corps</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>AT&amp;T Government Solutions Inc., Oakton, Virginia, is being awarded a $11,298,180 firm-fixed-price contract for design and construction of five new enhanced land mobile radio communication towers in various locations throughout the Marine Corps Mountain Warfare Training Center, Bridgeport. The work to be performed provides for each communication tower to be constructed as a standalone facility in remote locations within the Sierra Nevada Mountains. Towers will range from 70 to 150 feet in height, and each tower will consist of a foundation, propane generator, solar panels and batteries, equipment shelter, fence and associated support features like halo grounding, ice bridge system and propane tanks. This project will provide a safety and communications network for personnel, training, mission critical users and first responders. This project will provide radio frequency and cellular coverage between the installation and Coleville Military Housing area. This project fulfills critical needs in supporting the increased communications requirements for the installation and surrounding areas. Work will be performed in Bridgeport, California, and is expected to be completed by March 2019. Fiscal 2015 military construction, (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $11,298,180 are obligated on this award, of which $4,800,856 will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via the Navy Electronic Commerce Online website with eight proposals received. The Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Southwest, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity (N62473-16-C-0601).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
