<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DRS to Produce Data Link Technology</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DRS</tag>
    <tag>Data Link</tag>
    <tag>cryptography</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>DRS Advanced ISR LLC, Beavercreek, Ohio, is being awarded a $9,330,737 indefinite-quantity/indefinite-delivery contract for Link 11 and Link 22 Data Terminal Set (DTS) development and production. The contract covers minor development, production, integration, testing, support and sustainment of a Link 11 Data Terminal and Link 22 Signal Processing Controller solution for the command and control processor family of systems. The contractor shall provide the necessary equipment, materials, software and engineering/technical services and logistics products to provide a Link 11 and Link 22 DTS. The Link 11 and Link 22 DTS shall be integrated with data link systems, communication systems, satellite communications systems, human-machine interface systems and cryptographic systems. This contract contains options, which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to an estimated $22,009,117. Work will be performed in Beavercreek, Ohio, and is expected to be completed in August 2021. If options are exercised, work could continue until August 2026. Fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation and fiscal 2016 other procurement, (Navy) in the amount of $1,159,448 will be placed on contract and obligated at the time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This requirement was solicited using full and open competition via the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command E-Commerce Central website and the Federal Business Opportunities website, with two offers received. The Space and Naval Warfare System Command, San Diego, awarded the contract on behalf of the Program Executive Office for Command, Control, Communication, Computers and Intelligence (N00039-16-D-0100).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
