<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Zel Tech Wins $165 Million Counter-Improvised Threat Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Zel Technologies</tag>
    <tag>counter-IED</tag>
    <tag>GSA</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Zel Technologies Inc. (Zel Tech),* Hampton, Virginia, has been awarded a $165,272,923 ceiling, cost-plus-award-fee task order under the General Services Administration (GSA) One Acquisition Solution for Integrated Services (OASIS) Small Business Pool 4 contract to provide the Joint Improvised-Threat Defeat Agency (JIDA) with expertise in research, experimental development and rapid acquisition; development and fielding of counter-threat technologies; and delivering urgent mission solutions in support of operations throughout the globe. Zel Tech will identify and maintain an understanding of risks, vulnerabilities and capability gaps of the Joint Force to drive rapid assessments, thus enabling informed investments in counter-threat technologies and non-materiel solutions within the combatant command's latest time of value. This task order assists JIDA enable Department of Defense actions to counter improvised threats with tactical responsiveness and through anticipatory; rapid acquisition in support of combatant command’s efforts to prepare for, and adapt to, battlefield surprise in support of counter-terrorism; counter-insurgency; and other related mission areas including counter-improvised explosive device. Work will predominantly be performed in Virginia and the National Capital Region; however, contractor personnel will also be embedded as needed with globally deployed U.S. forces. The expected completion date is August 31, 2021. Joint IED Defeat funds in the amount of $2,652,877 are being obligated at the time of award. This task order was a competitive acquisition and three offers were received. The GSA Federal Systems Integration and Management Center is the contracting activity, in support of JIDA (GSQ0016AJ0017). (Awarded on September 1, 2016)

*Small Business</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
