<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Intelligence and National Security Summit Kicks Off Wednesday in D.C.</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>September 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Other</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>AFCEA</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The third annual Intelligence and National Security Summit (INSS) kicks off tomorrow in Washington, D.C., a premier gathering of senior decision makers from government, military, industry and academia who will tackle some of the most difficult intelligence quandaries baffling world leaders.</abstract>
  <text>The third annual Intelligence and National Security Summit (INSS) kicks off tomorrow in Washington, D.C., a premier gathering of senior decision makers from government, military, industry and academia who will tackle some of the most difficult intelligence quandaries baffling world leaders.

Presentations and discussions will center on this year’s theme: "The State of U.S. Intelligence: 15 Years since 9/11." The platform for rarely publicly discussed, intelligence-based topics will hinge on insights of the intelligence community’s advances and setbacks since the terrorists attacks on September 11, 2001, as well as remaining and new challenges that will test future leaders, to include a newly elected U.S. president.

The two-day unclassified summit will be held at the Walter E. Washington Convention Center and is co-hosted by AFCEA International and the Intelligence and National Security Alliance (INSA).

The summit features five plenary sessions, during which leaders of U.S. intelligence from the executive and legislative branches will offer assessments of these issues for national, defense and homeland security intelligence. Additionally, thought leaders from the public and private sectors will explore in nine breakout sessions enduring and emerging issues that will impact the intelligence community in the future.

Among them are several presentations that have been approved for continuing education credits for members who attend and for attendees who become members during INSS. Registration for the summit is still open.

Formal attendance documentation for designated continuing education sessions is a benefit of AFCEA/INSA membership. The continuing education program is designed to support certifications related to U.S. federal requirements and several INSS sessions will be approved to meet CompTIA and/or GIAC and might also support (ISC)2, National Contract Management Association (NCMA), Project Management Institute (PMI), GAGAS and Defense Acquisition Workforce continuing education and/or certification maintenance requirements.

Four of the six qualifying presentations take place on Wednesday: 

 “The State of U.S. Intelligence: The Enterprise View” at 8:30 a.m.
	“Managing Cyber Risk” at 10:15 a.m.
	“The New Face of Global Terrorism: A Dangerous Landscape” at 10:15 a.m.
	“A National Cyber Deterrence Strategy” at 1 p.m.
Two presentations on Thursday qualify for continuing education credit:

“Implementing the Cybersecurity and Information Security Act (CISA) Challenges and Opportunities” at 11 a.m.
	"U.S. Surveillance Policy and Law Forecast for the Future” at 11 a.m.
James Clapper, director of National Intelligence, will headline Wednesday morning. Be sure to follow SIGNAL Magazine’s event coverage for articles, blogs and a conference wrapup as well as #Intelligence2016 for real-time Twitter feeds and links to photography. To submit news leads or article ideas, contact news@afcea.org.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
