<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Awards Seven Cyber Research Contracts Potentially Valued at More than $1 Billion</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 16, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Dulles, Virginia, is being awarded a $98,090,785 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract (N66001-16-D-0442) to provide cyberspace science, research, engineering, and technology integration. Support includes technology assessment, development and transition; requirements analysis; systems engineering; operational and technical support; experimentation support; hardware and software development and prototyping; modeling and simulation; training; and security engineering/cybersecurity. This three-year contract includes one two-year option ordering period which, if exercised, would bring the potential value of this contract to $165,924,878. Leidos Inc., Reston, Virginia, is being awarded a $89,067,852 (N66001-16-D-0440) contract with an option to bring the potential value to $149,988,709. Booz Allen Hamilton Inc., McLean, Virginia, is being awarded an $88,611,546 contract (N66001-16-D-0439) with a potential value of $149,850,092. Northrop Grumman Systems Corp., San Diego, California, is being awarded an $88,018,945 (N66001-16-D-0441) with a potential value of $148,333,971. Science Applications International Corp., McLean, Virginia, is being awarded an $84,621,509 contract (N66001-16-D-0443) worth a potential $142,252,578. Scientific Research Corp., Atlanta, Georgia, is being awarded $81,035,479 (N66001-16-D-0444) potentially valued at $137,516,316. Vencore Inc., Chantilly, Virginia, receives $80,114,995 (N66001-16-D-0445) potentially valued at $134,925,210. This is one of seven multiple award contracts; all awardees will have the opportunity to compete for task orders during the ordering period. 

Work will be performed in San Diego (90 percent); and other continental U.S. and outside continental U.S. locations (10 percent). Work is expected to be completed September 14, 2019. No funds will be obligated at the time of award. Funding will be obligated via task orders. The types of funding to be obligated include research, development test and evaluation (Navy); operations and maintenance (Navy); and other procurement (Navy). Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via request for proposal N66001-15-R-0096 published on the Federal Business Opportunities website, and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website; 13 offers were received and seven were selected for award. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
