<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon to Provide Comms Link Security to Multiple Nations</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 21, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>Link  22</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Secure Information Systems, El Segundo, California, was awarded a $32,773,127 firm-fixed-price, cost-plus-fixed-fee, cost contract for NATO Improved Link Eleven (NILE)/Link 22 Modernized Link Level COMSEC (LLC 7M) production and sustainment. The NILE LLC 7M is a controlled cryptographic item system that has been certified for operational use by the National Security Agency. The NILE LLC 7M is planned for use in airborne, surface, subsurface and ground based applications by the NILE nations (Canada, France, Germany, Italy, United Kingdom, Spain and the U.S.), as well as all nations approved for Foreign Military Sales cases and as Link 22 third parties in the future. This effort includes requirements for NILE LLC 7M production, NILE LLC 7M production test sets and NILE LLC 7M sustainment, including warranty provision, engineering services, training, repair services, other direct costs, proposal preparation costs and spares provisions. It also includes the associated program management, human engineering and logistic support planning requirements. The contract includes a five-year base period and a five-year option period which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of this contract to an estimated $63,059,245. Work will be performed in El Segundo, California, and is expected to be completed September 2021. If the option is exercised, work could continue until September 2026. Fiscal 2016 other procurement (Navy) funds in the amount of $696,565 will be placed on contract and obligated at the time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the fiscal year. This contract was not competitively procured because it is a sole-source acquisition pursuant to the authority of 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1) - only one responsible source (Federal Acquisition Regulation Subpart 6.302-1). The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity (N00039-16-D-0075). </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
