<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Procures Network Tactical Common Data Link</title>
  <author/>
  <date>September 23, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>BAE</tag>
    <tag>Tactical Common Data Link Systems</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>BAE Systems Information and Electronic Systems Integration Inc., Wayne, New Jersey, is being awarded a $47,671,140 cost-plus-incentive-fee, firm-fixed-price, cost-plus-fixed-fee contract for procurement of Network Tactical Common Data Link systems that includes a design, development test and low-rate initial production (LRIP). Work consists of the development effort phase; LRIP for hardware with corresponding engineering and depot repair services; and provisioning items ordering support. This contract contains options that, if exercised, will bring the contract value to $84,712,006. Work will be performed in Wayne (60 percent); Totowa, New Jersey (20 percent); Greenlawn, New York (10 percent); and Westminster, Colorado (10 percent). Work is expected to be completed by September 2020. If all options are exercised, work could continue through September 2022. Fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation funds in the amount of $9,007,177 will be placed on contract and obligated at the time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. Funds will be obligated via incremental funding modifications issued to the contractor. This contract was competitively procured as a full and open solicitation via the Federal Business Opportunities website via the SPAWAR e-Commerce Central website, with four offers received. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, is the contracting activity and awarded the contract on behalf of the Navy’s Program Executive Office for Command, Control, Communications, Computers and Intelligence (N00039-16-C-0087).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
