<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>NOVA Chapter Members Biking Across Country to Raise Money for STEM</title>
  <author>Julianne Simpson</author>
  <date>September 27, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Three members of the AFCEA NOVA chapter are taking part in the TransAmerica Cycle for STEM. They will ride more than 4,000 miles to build awareness and support for science, technology, engineering and mathematics education for America’s youth.</abstract>
  <text>Three members of the AFCEA NOVA chapter are taking part in the TransAmerica Cycle for STEM. They will ride more than 4,000 miles to build awareness and support for science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education for America’s youth. The trip began on August 1 and will finish on October 25.

The riders are Al Mink, a retired Air Force colonel and a consultant in IT supporting national security; Tim Hoffman, a retired Army colonel and member of the Senior Executive Service; and Paul Scott, a recently retired technology leader from York, England, and a passionate bicyclist and supporter of STEM. The men intend to ride from Astoria, Oregon to Yorktown, Virginia, the route originally used to celebrate America’s Bicentennial.  

“For me, promoting STEM is promoting the future of our country,” says Mink, who also is a professor at American University’s Kogod School of Business. “The top jobs have migrated to computers and technology is constantly changing, which means it is more important than ever for young people to be engaged in STEM.”

During the three-month journey, the cyclists will travel across 10 states and cross or ride along several major waterways, including the Columbia, Snake, Mississippi and Ohio Rivers. Along the way, the riders will pass through some of the nation’s most beautiful national parks and forests, including Yellowstone and Grand Teton National Parks.

“We talk STEM wherever we go, to principals, students, parents,” says Mink. “We try to get into community events informally. You’ll find fairs going on, rodeos...so you’re talking and a group forms around you, particularly when they find out what you’re doing because it’s pretty interesting. Those are the main conversations we’re having as opposed to trying to pre-schedule specific schools along the route, which can be pretty difficult because if we get delayed a day or ahead a day, it’s tough.”

All proceeds from the TransAmerica Cycle for STEM benefit the Children’s Science Center located in Fairfax, Virginia. The Children’s Science Center’s mission is to instill a love of learning science, technology, engineering and mathematics in all children by providing unique opportunities to explore, create and be inspired. The center also encourages women and minorities to study STEM and consider STEM careers.

“This is a great initiative. And, the three riders are definitely putting skin in the game. Let’s show them that their efforts matter and help our region's youth,” says Chuck Corjay, NOVA chapter president.

To donate or support the ride, please visit www.afceanova.org/C4S.

</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>NOVA chapter members (l-r) Tim Hoffman, Paul Scott and Al Mink are riding more than 4,000 miles to build awareness and support for STEM education.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
