<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Educational Foundation Applauds Top Contributors</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Mission success continues because of dedicated individuals and organizations. It is with deep gratitude that the AFCEA Educational Foundation honors them as heroes. Their legacy will be felt far into the future.</abstract>
  <text>The shifting stability of the economy is posing complex challenges for both students and teachers. Program funding is decreasing while appeals for those scarcer dollars increases. Potential teachers are choosing more lucrative career paths to ensure they can pay back the student loans they incurred while getting their education. Current teachers in all grade levels find themselves in classrooms that lack the tools needed to teach students foundational principles, especially in the areas of science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM).

Today’s challenges are hardly unique. Nearly 40 years ago, AFCEA Educational Foundation founders Vice Adm. Jon L. Boyes, USN, and Vice Adm. Samuel L. Gravely, USN, recognized that STEM education was and always would be the cornerstone of national security and the economy. However, they also understood that tangibly supporting students seeking higher education—whether at universities or vocational schools—was a crucial investment in the future and an important part of AFCEA’s mission.

Mission success continues because of dedicated individuals and organizations. It is with deep gratitude that the AFCEA Educational Foundation honors them as heroes. Their legacy will be felt far into the future.

Top Donors to the AFCEA Educational Foundation include:

Booz Allen Hamilton
	BridgePhase LLC
	Congressional Medal of Honor Foundation
	LGS
	ManTech
	Rockwell Collins
	SAIC
In addition, the foundation thanks the AFCEA International chapters that continually support its endeavor to reward educational excellence, including the Atlanta, Central Maryland, Los Angeles, Montgomery, Northern Virginia and Quantico-Potomac chapters.

Tomorrow’s technologists, innovators, teachers and researchers depend on today’s foresight. Become part of the future today by donating to the foundation online at www.afcea.org/secure/sch_donate_form.asp.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Lt. Gen. Robert M. Shea, USMC (Ret.), president and CEO of AFCEA International, accepts a check from Susan Lepera, former president of the Central Maryland Chapter, for the AFCEA Educational Foundation.</img>
    <img>Michael Trovato (r) of SAIC presents a check to then-AFCEA Educational Foundation Executive Director Vince Patton.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
