<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Established Programs Are Top System Priorities</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman</author>
  <date>October 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>U.S. Army</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The primary fielding priorities for Gary P. Martin, U.S. Army PEO C3T, include the Warfighter Information Network–Tactical (WIN-T) Increment 2, which serves as the backbone network for the Army’s mobile network capability.</abstract>
  <text>The primary fielding priorities for Gary P. Martin, U.S. Army PEO C3T, include the Warfighter Information Network–Tactical (WIN-T) Increment 2, which serves as the backbone network for the Army’s mobile network capability. It is being fielded first to active components, while Increment 1 still dominates Guard and Reserve forces. Only about 20 percent of active-duty forces have Increment 2, and its full fielding probably will take another 10 years, Martin says.

WIN-T network operations (net ops) solutions unique to each increment will be supplemented next year by an enhanced net ops capability that supports management of the integrated WIN-T network, including both increments. Improvements include a better user interface for the unit G-6 for visualizing and planning the network, along with virtual firewalls and other enhancements for network cyber defense. One capability the Army Cyber Command is assessing would allow cyber protection teams to have remote-controlled cyber defense tools co-located on the tactical network. These all are part of the WIN-T Increment 3 program, Martin notes.

The Joint Battle Command-Platform (JBC-P) also is being fielded. It evolved from the Force Battle Command Brigade and Below (FBCB2) program, and it provides mounted command and control on mobile platforms. Manpack and Rifleman radios continue to be fielded as well. The joint enterprise network manager, which will be a net ops capability for all these radios, will be fielded over the next year.

Martin relates that the Army recently had a Milestone C review for the mounted maneuver Mid-tier Networking Vehicular Radio, which constitutes a terrestrial backbone for the Army’s satellite network at brigade and battalion levels. The goal is to begin fielding the capability in fiscal years 2017 and 2018, he notes. 

Next year may see two new systems targeted for early entry. The Enroute Mission Command Capability (EMC2) will allow the Global Response Force to maintain connectivity via the Internet while on its way by air to its destination. And the Transportable Tactical Command Communications (T2C2) satellite communications (SATCOM) system comprises two variants of a small, packable SATCOM capability that individuals can carry aboard commercial aircraft. It will provide early entry capability for brigades, divisions and signal companies. Its initial operational test and evaluation is slated for spring 2017, with T2C2 fielding taking place in summer or early fall of that year.

Read the full article, "For Army C3, Better Also Must Be Simpler"</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
