<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Nominations for DON IM/IT Excellence Awards Due December 5</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>October 3, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Defense Operations</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DON CIO</tag>
    <tag>Excellence Awards</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Nominations are now being accepted for the DON Information Management/Information Technology (IM/IT) Excellence Awards. Submissions are due by December 5.</abstract>
  <text>Nominations are now being accepted for the DON Information Management/Information Technology (IM/IT) Excellence Awards. Submissions are due by December 5. The awards recognize the superior efforts of IM/IT projects, teams and individuals in helping to transform Department of the Navy information technology.

One set of DON IM/IT Excellence awards will recognize accomplishments in 2016. Winners based on/near the West Coast will receive their awards at the DON IT Conference, West Coast 2017, scheduled for February 21-23 at the San Diego Convention Center. Winners based on/near the East Coast will receive their awards at the DON IT Conference, East Coast 2017, scheduled for May 16-18 at the Hilton Norfolk The Main in Norfolk, Virginia.

Nominations are now being accepted for the following categories:

DON IM/IT Excellence Awards (Individual and Team awards)
	John J. Lussier Electromagnetic Spectrum Award
	DON Cyberspace/IT Person of the Year Award
	DON Cyberspace/IT Rising Star of the Year Award
	Information System Security Manager (ISSM)/Information System Security Officer (ISSO) of the Year Award
	Privacy Program Excellence Award
	Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Program Excellence Award
To be considered for a DON IM/IT Excellence Award, please submit a nomination package through your command information officer or local commanding officer via email to doncio@navy.mil by December 5. All packages must be submitted using the DON IM/IT Excellence Awards Nomination Form and must follow the specific instructions included with the form.

Award winners will be notified by email no later than January 23, 2017.

Contact doncio@navy.mil for additional information.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
