<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Lockheed Awarded Nearly $149 Million for Electronic Warfare Improvement</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 3, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>electronic warfare</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Corp., Mission Systems and Training, Liverpool, New York, is being awarded a $148,905,000 firm-fixed-price contract for full-rate production of Surface Electronic Warfare Improvement Program (SEWIP) Block 2 subsystems (AN/SLQ-32(V)6 and AN/SLQ-32A(V)6) and SEWIP AN/SLQ-32C(V)6 systems. SEWIP is an evolutionary acquisition and incremental development program to upgrade the existing AN/SLQ-32(V) electronic warfare system. SEWIP provides enhanced shipboard electronic warfare for early detection, analysis, threat warning and protection from anti-ship missiles. SEWIP Block 2 and SEWIP AN/SLQ-32C(V)6 will expand upon the receiver/antenna group necessary to keep capabilities current with the pace of the threat and to yield improved system integration. Work will be performed in Liverpool, New York (23 percent); Lansdale, Pennsylvania (23 percent); Chelmsford, Massachusetts (21 percent); Frankfort, New York (9 percent); Hamilton, New Jersey (7 percent); Hauppauge, New York (7 percent); Brockton, Massachusetts (3 percent); West Yorkshire, United Kingdom (2 percent); Minneapolis, Minnesota (2 percent); Huntsville, Alabama (2 percent); Lancaster, Pennsylvania (1 percent), and is expected to be completed by November 2019. Fiscal 2015 and 2016 other procurement (Navy); and fiscal 2016 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) funds in the amount of $148,905,000 will be obligated at time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via the Federal Business Opportunities website, with two offers received. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity (N00024-16-C-5363).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
