<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Modifies Cooperative Engagement Capability Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>October 6, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>Cooperative Engagement Capability</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Integrated Defense Systems, St. Petersburg, Florida, is being awarded a $19,495,001 cost-plus-fixed-fee modification to previously awarded contract N00024-13-C-5212 to exercise fiscal 2017 options for Cooperative Engagement Capability Design Agent and Engineering Services efforts. Cooperative Engagement Capability (CEC) is a sensor netting system that significantly improves battle force Anti-Air Warfare capability by extracting and distributing sensor-derived information such that the superset of this data is available to all participating CEC units. CEC improves battle force effectiveness by improving overall situational awareness and by enabling longer range, cooperative, multiple or layered engagement strategies. Work will be performed in St. Petersburg, Florida, and is expected to be completed by September 2017. Foreign military sales (Japan) in the amount of $1,493,089; fiscal 2012 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) in the amount of $49,378; fiscal 2013 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) in the amount of $49,378; fiscal 2014 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) in the amount of $49,378; fiscal 2015 shipbuilding and conversion (Navy) in the amount of $25,865; fiscal 2015 other procurement (Navy) in the amount of $479,669; fiscal 2016 other procurement (Navy) in the amount of $23,513; fiscal 2016 research, development, test and evaluation in the amount of $134,025; and working capital fund (Navy) funding in the amount of $47,026 will be obligated at the time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, District of Columbia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
