<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Army Cyber Command Gets a New Commander</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>October 14, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Army Cyber Command</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lt. Gen. Paul M. Nakasone, USA, assumed leadership of U.S. Army Cyber Command and 2nd Army during a ceremony Friday at Fort Belvoir, Virginia. He took over responsibilities from outgoing commander Lt. Gen. Edward C. Cardon, USA, who led Army Cyber for more than three years.</abstract>
  <text>Lt. Gen. Paul M. Nakasone, USA, assumed leadership of U.S. Army Cyber Command and 2nd Army during a ceremony Friday at Fort Belvoir, Virginia. He took over responsibilities from outgoing commander Lt. Gen. Edward C. Cardon, USA, who led Army Cyber for more than three years.

The Army stood up the command in 2010. Under Gen. Cardon’s leadership, the command established the service’s cyber branch; began to build the first 41 active Army teams in the Cyber Mission Force; integrated cyber elements in overseas combat missions; and oversaw construction of the new Army Cyber Command at Fort Gordon, Georgia. 

"I consider myself fortunate to have had the opportunity to lead this remarkable command at this critical point in its history," Gen. Cardon said, according to an Army news release of his remarks. "The challenges of operationalizing a new warfighting domain—where software, hardware and people can change things at a rapid pace—while simultaneously engaging adversaries, building capabilities and building a force comprised a formidable mission.”

Gen. Cardon moves on to serve as director of the Army's Office of Business Transformation.

Gen. Nakasone comes to the command after commanding the Cyber National Mission Force at U.S. Cyber Command, where he served as the Army Cyber Command's deputy commanding general for operations. 

"Today, we are at the forefront of one of the most transformative times in our Army's history," Gen. Nakasone said. "Cyberspace is a dynamic and challenging domain that is revolutionizing the way our Army fights and wins.”</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
