<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Source Book Update</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>September 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>ATTENTION AFCEA CONTACTS: Time to Update Your Company's SIGNAL Source Book Listing 

One of the benefits of AFCEA corporate membership is the free corporate profile that companies receive annually in the January issue of SIGNAL Magazine. Called the Source Book, the listing of leading technology companies also has an online version that can be accessed at www.afcea.org/sourcebook. To ensure that your business’s most current information is available to customers, your company’s AFCEA contact can now update the corporate profile through the AFCEA member portal or can connect to the portal from the Source Book online site. The deadline for updates to be included in the January 2009 print directory is September 24, 2008.

 

AFCEA is sending each corporate contact a letter that includes instructions on how to update the company’s profile online. Contacts can wait for the letter to arrive or go immediately to the site and follow the instructions on how to update. A user identification number and password are required, but password and identification help also is available online. All corporate contacts should review their company’s profile on the site to ensure it is correct. Write-ups that do not require changes should be reviewed and approved by clicking "okay for publication." Contacts also should be sure to add their firm’s areas of expertise to the Topical Guide. 

Corporate contacts who do not receive a letter from AFCEA can e-mail the Source Book coordinator at sourcebook@afcea.org. Updates can be made year-round; however, companies making changes after the September 24, 2008, deadline will not be guaranteed a listing in the January 2009 print directory.

 

Because some companies publish contact and marketing addresses in the Source Book that are different from the addresses they use for AFCEA correspondence, the association maintains two separate databases. Both AFCEA corporate membership information and Source Book publication information can be updated via the AFCEA portal; however, changes in one database do not automatically transfer to the other database. When corporate contacts update either area, they will be prompted to update the other area.

 

Information posted is subject to review by the SIGNAL staff and will be edited for grammar, punctuation and spelling.

 

In addition to the free corporate listing, rotating banners are available on the online site. Banner advertisers also will be included in a sponsorship section in the print version. Contact Jennifer Deuterman for more information.

 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
