<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>STEM Gifts Change Lives</title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>STEM Education</tag>
    <tag>scholarships</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Notes from scholarship and grant recipients are constant reminders of the importance of corporate, member and chapter contributions to the individuals the AFCEA Educational Foundation serves. The foundation provides potential benefactors with the facts; the beneficiaries of their generosity tell the story.


“I received the AFCEA Lt. Gen. John A. Dubia ROTC scholarship. Thank you so much for your time, generosity and faith. Your scholarship really helped give me more motivation to continue to strive and put time into all the opportunities at my school, through the Army Department and the community in general.” —Cadet Kimberly Denny, Virginia Military Institute, Army ROTC

“It’s gifts like these that help us to buy the supplies we need to modify curriculum, create curriculum and participate in unique and fun activities with our students. Generous donations like yours make a difference to the quality of our classrooms. We thank you again for your continued interest and involvement in our school and our science department.” —Tim Biland, principal, Poway Unified School District, on behalf of STEM Teacher Grant recipient Linjue Cao

“As an immigrant and first-generation college student … I have come across many obstacles that would hinder my higher education, and I have overcome every single one with the help of organizations like AFCEA.” —Neel Shah, Northeastern University, STEM Major Graduate Scholarship recipient

“I was thrilled to be chosen for this honor, and I am so grateful for your support. I am proud to be an AFCEA member, and I hope in the future, I will be able to help other veterans achieve their goals just as you have helped me.” —Kendall Robinson, Regis University, recipient of the AFCEA Afghanistan and Iraq War Veterans Undergraduate Scholarship


What powerful testimony from some of the recipients of AFCEA Educational Foundation scholarships and grants. How can you support other students and teachers who will be the source of positive changes in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)? 

As you start your year-end tax planning, remember that donations to the AFCEA Educational Foundation are fully tax-deductible. Also, consider donating appreciated securities such as stocks or bonds. You can avoid paying capital gains tax and get a charitable deduction for the fair market value of your donated assets. It’s a great way to save money and invest in the future of STEM.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
