<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>CACI Wins $1.7 Billion for Counter-IED Support </title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 1, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>CACI</tag>
    <tag>counter-IED</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>CACI International Inc., Chantilly, Virginia, has been awarded a $1,773,158,264 ceiling cost-plus-award-fee task order under the General Services Administration (GSA) OASIS Pool 4 contract to provide the Joint Improvised-Threat Defeat Organization (JIDO) with deployable analytical operations, intelligence and training services to support JIDO’s Focused Support/Decisive Effort (FS/DE) mission anywhere in the world. The FS/DE task order will enhance the ability of deploying joint forces to integrate capabilities, technologies and lessons learned to defeat adversaries that employ improvised-threat weapons for strategic effect. The task order provides a key component for JIDO’s mission to enable Department of Defense actions to counter improvised threats with tactical responsiveness and through anticipatory, rapid acquisition in support of combatant commands’ efforts to prepare for, and adapt to, battlefield surprise in support of counter-terrorism, counter-insurgency and other related mission areas including counter-improvised explosive device. Work will predominantly be performed in Virginia and the National Capital Region; however, contractor personnel will also be embedded as needed with globally deployed U.S. forces. The expected completion date is October 30, 2021. Joint IED Defeat funds, along with other agency and department contributions in the amount of $12,126,590, are being obligated at the time of award. This task order was a competitive acquisition and two offers were received. It is part of the JIDO Enterprise Acquisition Strategy Initiative which is intended to (1) Meet current and evolving mission requirements; (2) Comply with acquisition laws, regulations and policies; and (3) Improve mission effectiveness, output and organizational synergy. The GSA Federal Systems Integration and Management Center is the contracting activity, in support of JIDO (GSQ0016AJ0029).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
