<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Four Companies to Support Shore Networks </title>
  <author/>
  <date>November 29, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>Engility Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Booz Allen and Hamilton</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>King Technologies Inc., San Diego, California, is being awarded a $52,503,043 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee, multiple award contract (N66001-17-D-0032) to provide shore networks support to include in-service engineering support, design, accreditation, integration, production, sustainment and life cycle support for non-integrated shore systems, network components and network service solutions for Navy and joint Department of Defense shore units worldwide. The three-year contract includes two one-year option ordering periods which, if exercised, would bring the potential value of this contract to $88,566,021. Science Applications International Corp., McLean, Virginia, is being awarded a $49,777,606 contract (N66001-17-D-0003) with a potential value of $83,855,132. Engility Corp., Andover, Massachusetts, is being awarded $48,661,024 (N66001-17-D-0005) with a potential value of $82,446,405. Booz Allen Hamilton Inc., McLean, Virginia, is being awarded $46,308,418 (N66001-17-D-0004) potentially valued at $78,516,086. All awardees will have the opportunity to compete for task orders during the ordering period. 

Work will be performed in San Diego, California (40 percent) and various locations inside and outside the continental U.S. (60 percent). Work is expected to be completed November 27, 2019. No contract funds will be obligated at the time of award. Funding will be obligated via task orders as they are issued using operations and maintenance (Navy); other procurement (Navy); and Navy working capital funds. No contract funds will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via a request for proposal published on the Federal Business Opportunities website and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website. Eight offers were received and four were selected for award. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, California, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
