<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Awarded Nearly $102 Million for Fighter Jet Radar Warning Receivers</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 12, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>F/A-18</tag>
    <tag>radar warning receiver</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Raytheon receives a contract for repair of weapon replaceable assemblies for the AN/ALR67(V)3 for the F/A-18 A/B/C/D/E/F aircraft.</abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Goleta, California, is being awarded a $101,967,288 performance-based logistics, firm-fixed-price requirements contract for repair support of 10 weapon replaceable assemblies for the AN/ALR-67(V)3 for F/A-18 A/B/C/D/E/F aircraft. The contractor is also responsible for managing technical and configuration changes, and obsolescence. This is a four-year base period contract with a one one-year option period, which if exercised, brings the total estimated value to $128,175,612. Work will be performed in Goleta, California (44.9 percent); Jacksonville, Florida (13.3 percent); Port Mugu, California (8.7 percent); Lansdale, Pennsylvania (8.6 percent); Forest, Mississippi (7 percent); Tucson, Arizona (7 percent); Chatsworth, California (5.2 percent); San Diego, California (3.5 percent); and Hudson, New Hampshire (1.8 percent). Work is expected to be completed by December 2020. Working capital funds (Navy) in the amount of $27,541,080 will be obligated to fund the delivery order concurrently with the award, and funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. One firm was solicited for this non-competitive requirement in accordance with Federal Acquisition Regulation 6.302-1, with one offer received. Naval Supply Systems Command Weapon Systems Support, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, is the contracting activity (N00383-17-D-A001).

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Raytheon receives a contract for repair of weapon replaceable assemblies for the AN/ALR67(V)3 for the F/A-18 A/B/C/D/E/F aircraft.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
