<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Four Companies to Provide Cyber and IT Training</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 9, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cyber</tag>
    <tag>Marine Corps</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Executive Protection Systems LLC, doing business as RavenTek Solutions, Chantilly, Virginia, is being awarded a $19,211,795 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, firm-fixed-price contract (N66001-17-D-0041) for cyber and information technology training in support of the Marine Corps Forces Cyber Command. This is one of four multiple-award contracts; all awardees will have the opportunity to compete for task orders during the ordering period. The three-year contracts include two one-year options, which if exercised, would bring the potential value of this contract to $31,110,172. Onyx Consulting Services LLC, Columbia, Maryland, is being awarded a $14,624,996 contract (N66001-17-D-0040) with a potential value of $24,058,751. CSR Group, Crownsville, Maryland, is being awarded a $14,162,221 contract (N66001-17-D-0039) potentially valued at $23,145,294. And Ultimate Knowledge Corp., Scottsdale, Arizona, is being awarded a $13,312,423 contract (N66001-17-D-0038) potentially worth $21,759,771.

Cyber and information technology training includes basic level courses, intermediate level courses, opportunity level courses, opportunity areas from Pipeline 2.2, and other software applications. Training will provide commercially available technical courses required to meet operational standards at national level organizations providing support to cyber security missions. Work will be performed in Washington, D.C. (25 percent); Fort Bragg, North Carolina (25 percent); Tampa, Florida (25 percent); and Scott Air Force Base, Illinois (25 percent). Work is expected to be completed December 9, 2019.  No contract funds will be obligated at the time of award. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. Operations and maintenance (Navy) funding will be obligated via task orders as they are issued. This contract was competitively procured using full and open competition via publication on the Federal Business Opportunities website and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website, with 13 proposals received and four were selected for award. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, is the contracting activity. 

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
