<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon to Provide F/A-18 and EA-18G Sensor Technology</title>
  <author/>
  <date>December 22, 2016</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>F/A-18</tag>
    <tag>EA-18G</tag>
    <tag>airborne sensors</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Raytheon Space and Airborne Systems is being awarded a $12,373,452 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract to provide sensor system software and hardware in support of the F/A-18/EA-18G.</abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Space and Airborne Systems, El Segundo, California, is being awarded a $12,373,452 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract to provide sensor system software and hardware in support of the F/A-18/EA-18G. Sensor systems include legacy AN/APG-65, AN/APG-73, AN/APG-79 and advanced systems. This effort will include the F/A-18/EA-18G sensor system software and hardware to correct deficiencies; incorporate updates, improvements and enhancements of tactical capabilities; sensor instrumentation and instrumentation interfaces for flight test aircraft; flight test engineering; library updates; performance assessment of sensor-related systems, interfaces and weapons; analysis and investigation of advanced sensor technology and resolution of existing sensor system problems; and analytical support of Navy data reduction operations for the contractor designed instrumentation. Work will be performed in El Segundo, California, and is expected to be completed in December 2021. Fiscal 2017 operations and maintenance (Navy) funds in the amount of $200,000 are being obligated at time of award, all of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via an electronic request for proposals; one offer was received. The Naval Air Warfare Center Weapons Division, China Lake, California, is the contracting activity (N68936-17-D-0004).</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Raytheon is being awarded a $12,373,452 contract to provide sensor system software and hardware in support of the F/A-18 and EA-18G.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
