<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA International Conducts Second Annual Member Survey</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date></date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>AFCEA International’s core strength is its members, and the association wants to ensure that your membership needs are being met. To collect the information it needs to continue improving service, AFCEA will send an e-mail to all members in October with a link to your opportunity to provide valuable input on the organization. The feedback from this survey will be used to plan your AFCEA of the future. Questions will focus on member satisfaction, programs and services, member benefits and AFCEA events. Your responses will help the association tailor membership benefits, programs and services to meet members’ needs.  AFCEA conducted its first annual membership survey last fall and was pleased with the results. “We had a high member response rate,” says Curt Adams, director, Member and Chapter Services. “We found that the majority of members are highly satisfied with AFCEA’s service, and we also received excellent feedback with specific suggestions for improvement.”Based on that feedback, AFCEA has made these changes:Improved new member engagement and involvement Revamped SIGNAL Source Book Redesigned SIGNAL Web site and SIGNAL Connections Provided Web 2.0 technologies, including blogs, Wiki, LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, Second Life and webinarsMarket Connections Incorporated, a full-service market research firm that specializes in public sector and association research in the defense and information technology markets, will conduct the survey.  To ensure participation in this feedback opportunity, please review your membership records through the AFCEA portal and make sure association records reflect your current information, especially an accurate e-mail address. In addition, it is important to adjust your e-mail spam filters to allow e-mails from “afceasurvey@marketconnectionsinc.com.” Market Connections will only use member e-mail addresses to invite AFCEANs to participate in the survey. All responses will be anonymous and only reported in aggregate. Questions about the survey can be sent to service@afcea.org. Thank you in advance for participating in the member survey! </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
