<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Webinar Tackles Networking Tremors</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>September 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Defense Information Systems Agency continues its work to fulfill its vision and strategy in bringing coherence to U.S. Defense Department networks to give warfighters timely access to relevant information. Achieving this goal has led to the Enterprise Information Environment, which provides standards, rules for data accuracy and the framework for placing data on the network as well as governance of information on the network. While the benefits of a multidimensional network are many, the strain this design places on the network structure also can be significant.According to the Ciena Corporation, three developments in networks currently underway are significantly affecting wide area networks (WANs). The first is a growing adoption of service-oriented architectures, or Web services, which are fundamentally shifting the way that organizations implement enterprise software. The second is the use of networked remote storage, a move with a wide range of goals that include facilitating information sharing between merged companies or ensuring continuity of operations after a disaster. The third recent development is the increase in the use of grid computing, which is the latest technical answer to asset virtualization. One outcome of these trends—not only on military networks but on commercials ones as well—is an influx of inter-site traffic, Ciena officials say.Networking experts will discuss what Ciena terms “the three tremors on the information technology landscape” as well as state-of-the-art network solutions at the next free SIGNAL Magazine Webinar, which takes place on September 18 at 1 p.m. EDT.Robert K. Ackerman, editor in chief, SIGNAL Magazine, will moderate the discussion. Scheduled to contribute to the conversation are experts in the field who will talk about technology that enables the transition from discrete elements for local area networks and remote storage to a network that can deliver a multitude of services. Webinar attendees are encouraged to use the text messaging system available on the webinar site to ask questions and contribute insights. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
