<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>High School Seniors Eligible for Engineering Scholarships</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 24, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Education</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman Corporation</tag>
    <tag>scholarships</tag>
    <tag>engineering</tag>
    <tag>STEM Education</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Northrop Grumman Corporation is accepting applications for its engineering scholars competition, which will provide $192,000 in college scholarships this year to promising high school seniors graduating from Maryland schools interested in studying engineering, according to a news release. Additionally, the company will award 26 scholarships to students who live near company campuses in Alabama, California, Colorado, Florida, Illinois, New York, Ohio, Utah and Virginia. Application deadline is February 4.</abstract>
  <text>Northrop Grumman Corporation is now accepting applications for its engineering scholars competition, which will provide $192,000 in college scholarships this year to promising high school seniors graduating from Maryland schools interested in studying engineering, according to a news release. Additionally, the company will award 26 scholarships to students who live near company campuses in Alabama, California, Colorado, Florida, Illinois, New York, Ohio, Utah and Virginia.

Students must complete an online application. This spring, the company will award individual scholarships of $8,000, payable in $2,000 installments over four years, to a qualified graduating high school senior in each of Maryland’s 23 counties and Baltimore city. Students must attend an accredited college or university school of engineering as a full-time student in an approved engineering program. The scholarship may be used for tuition, books, room and board and lab fees.

A committee of Northrop Grumman employees will select the winners. Each applicant must graduate this spring from a public or accredited private high school, have a minimum composite SAT score of 1150 or ACT score of 27 and a minimum GPA of 3.5. Recipients of any other Northrop Grumman-sponsored scholarships are not eligible. The application deadline is February 4.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
