<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Amyx Inc. to Support Joint Improvised-Threat Defeat Organization</title>
  <author/>
  <date>January 25, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>General Services Administration</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Amyx Inc.,* Reston, Virginia, has been awarded a $189,263,856 ceiling cost-plus-award-fee task order under the General Services Administration (GSA) OASIS Small Business Pool 1 contract to provide the Joint Improvised-Threat Defeat Organization (JIDO) with sensitive mission support services without organizational conflicts of interest. Services include: systems engineering and technical assistance; acquisition and program management; JIDO operations support; mission-based research and analytical assistance, as well as support services for acquisition and contracting; human capital management; resource management; security assurance; logistics; facilities safety and operations; event and communications support; process improvement; and organizational effectiveness. The task order provides a key component for JIDO’s mission to enable Department of Defense actions to counter improvised threats with tactical responsiveness and through anticipatory, rapid acquisition in support of combatant commands’ efforts to prepare for, and adapt to, battlefield surprise in support of counter-terrorism, counter-insurgency and other related mission areas including counter-improvised explosive device (IED). Work will be performed in Virginia and the National Capital Region. The expected completion date is January 17, 2022. Joint IED Defeat funds in the amount of $4,185,000 are being obligated at the time of award. This task order was a competitive acquisition and eight offers were received. It is part of the JIDO Enterprise Acquisition Strategy Initiative which is intended to: (1) meet current and evolving mission requirements; (2) comply with acquisition laws, regulations, and policies; and (3) improve mission effectiveness, output, and organizational synergy. The GSA Federal Systems Integration and Management Center is the contracting activity, in support of JIDO (GSQ0017AJ0022).

*Small Business</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
