<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>The Language of Today's Army</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>September 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>On Cyber Patrol</tag>
    <tag>September 2008</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>There’s been some discussion that today’s soldiers need to be both a warrior and a computer geek to handle the challenges of modern conflicts. This transition could possibly be a difficult one for old school Army personnel and may require significant updating of their operational vocabulary.</abstract>
  <text>There’s been some discussion that today’s soldiers need to be both a warrior and a computer geek to handle the challenges of modern conflicts. This transition could possibly be a difficult one for old school Army personnel and may require significant updating of their operational vocabulary. As part of this retraining effort, the partial list below serves as an unofficial primer in the new language of today’s Army.  Classic Term  Current Term The radio is out     The network is down The enemy is massing over the next ridge    There’s been heavy internet traffic out of the region Dig a foxhole  Put up a firewall Secure this bridge Secure this network Our lines have been infiltrated   Our network’s been hacked I almost got my a** shot off         We almost lost our computer assets Boot camp   Boot up Loose lips  Loose keyboards He lost his thumb at Quang Tri      He lost his thumb drive in Mosul Enemy irregulars Script kiddies, transnational cyber terrorists Years of Experience  IA Workforce Certification @*!%! My gun has jammed   @*!%! My screen has frozen Retired on active duty  Legacy system Fail Inspection    Not Networthy Airborne Air cards Battle hardened Cyber Warrior Forward edge of the battle area   Over the horizon Targets of opportunity  Unencrypted mobile devices While some of these substitute phrases may be tongue in cheek, it is a fact that the battlefield terminology of our father’s Army in physical space is being supplemented and increasingly supplanted by the lexicon of operating in cyber space and winning the cyber war. Soldiers need to be as well versed in maintaining and securing their information systems as they are in using their weapons systems. Each individual’s information assurance and cyber security responsibilities–regardless of rank–are as important as maintaining a secure perimeter at a forward base. Safeguarding information helps to ensure the success of operations, the protection of resources and the security of our warfighters. The On Cyber Patrol© cartoon and supporting articles are created and made available by the U.S. Army’s Office of Information Assurance and Compliance, NETCOM, CIO/G6.  For more information on the OCP program or to submit ideas for upcoming cartoons/articles, contact oncyberpatrol@hqda.army.mil.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
