<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DARPA Modifies Guided Ammo Program</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 13, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>DARPA</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Lockheed Martin Missiles and Fire Control, Grand Prairie, Texas, has been awarded an agreement modification totaling $8,153,741 through the addition of Phase II base tasks to a previously awarded other transaction (OT) for a prototype project agreement for the Multi Azimuth Defense Fast Intercept Round Engagement System (MAD-FIRES) program.</abstract>
  <text>Lockheed Martin Missiles and Fire Control, Grand Prairie, Texas, has been awarded an agreement modification totaling $8,153,741 through the addition of Phase II base tasks to a previously awarded other transaction (OT) for a prototype project agreement for the Multi Azimuth Defense Fast Intercept Round Engagement System (MAD-FIRES) program. Under modification P00005, the government negotiated and added a Phase II base effort, Option 1 and Option 2 to the previously awarded OT agreement, HR0011-15-9-0008. The MAD-FIRES program is an advanced technology development and demonstration program to create a gun-launched, medium-caliber, actively controlled, guided projectile with significantly improved range and accuracy compared with current systems. The entire Phase II program (base, Options 1 and 2) will be accomplished in 30 months. The addition of the MAD-FIRES Phase II base program increases the agreement's total cumulative face value to $18,073,602 from $9,919,861. Work will be performed in Grand Prairie (76.92 percent); Minneapolis (6.28 percent); Montville, New Jersey (4.52 percent); Dallas (3.57 percent); Brea, California (3.12 percent); Bethesda, Maryland (1.99 percent); Keyser, West Virginia (1.37 percent); Marion, Illinois (1.16 percent); and Westminster, Maryland (1.07 percent). The Lockheed Martin MAD-FIRES Phase II base program is expected to completed on November 9. The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, Arlington, Virginia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>The Phalanx close-in weapon system aboard the amphibious assault ship USS Boxer is a machine gun that can detect and automatically destroy incoming threats. The Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency has modified a contract to develop guided, medium-caliber ammunition for ship defense.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
