<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>BAH Awarded $325 Million for Improvised Threat Enterprise IT</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 15, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>counter-improvised explosive device</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Booz Allen Hamilton, McLean, Virginia, has been awarded a $325,868,201 ceiling cost-plus-award-fee task order under the General Services Administration (GSA) Alliant contract to provide reliable and secure Enterprise Information Technology (EIT) operations anywhere in the world in support of the Joint Improvised-Threat Defeat Organization (JIDO). The EIT task order enables rapid aggregation, fusion and dissemination of operational information, intelligence and technology to respond to emerging threats. It provides the DevOps-enabled path to production for JIDO mission information technology (IT) capabilities; leverages Department of Defense (DoD) and Intelligence Community enterprise services; and delivers IT capabilities in response to combatant commands, the intelligence community, military service partner organizations and other DoD/federal agencies. The task order provides a key component for JIDO’s mission to enable DoD actions to counter improvised threats with tactical responsiveness and through anticipatory, rapid acquisition in support of combatant commands’ efforts to prepare for, and adapt to, battlefield surprise in support of counter-terrorism, counter-insurgency and other related mission areas including counter-improvised explosive device. Work will predominantly be performed in Virginia and the National Capital Region; however, contractor personnel will also be embedded as needed with globally deployed U.S. forces. The expected completion date is March 5, 2022.  Joint IED defeat funds along with other agency/department contributions in the amount of $2,618,250 are being obligated at the time of award.  This task order was a competitive acquisition and two offers were received. Enterprise IT is part of the JIDO Enterprise Acquisition Strategy Initiative which is intended to meet current and evolving mission requirements; comply with acquisition laws, regulations and policies; and improve mission effectiveness, output and organizational synergy. The GSA Federal Systems Integration and Management Center is the contracting activity, in support of JIDO (GSQ0017AJ0029). (Awarded on February 10, 2017.)</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
