<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>ALOM to Compete for Information Technology Task Orders</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 24, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>ALOM Technologies Corp., Fremont, California, is being awarded a $14,250,000 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, firm-fixed-price multiple-award contract for procurement of information communication technology/equipment (ICT/E), including a broad range of procurements identified by risk. The ICT/E high-risk category includes firewalls; intrusion detection systems and sensors; routers; semiconductor chips; and switches. The medium-risk category includes encryptors; hard disk drives; multiplexers and transceivers; servers; solid state drives; workstations; and other computing devices. The low-risk category includes racks, cabinets, storage area networks, thin clients, power strips and other electrical protection and distribution devices. This is one of four multiple-award contracts, with two awardees eligible to compete for delivery orders for all risk categories and two awardees eligible to compete for delivery orders for medium- and low-risk categories during the ordering period. ALOM Technologies is eligible to supply ICT/E in the low- and medium-risk categories. This five-year contract includes no options. Work will be performed at the contractor’s facilities in Fremont and is expected to be completed on February 27, 2022. Contract funds will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. Funding will be obligated via delivery orders, which will be competed. The types of funding to be obligated include primarily operations and maintenance (Navy); other procurement (Navy); and research, development, test and evaluation. This contract was competitively procured using full and open competition via publication on the Federal Business Opportunities website and the Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command e-Commerce Central website. Six proposals were received and four were selected for award. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Pacific, San Diego, is the contracting activity (N66001-17-D-0092).</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
