<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Support STEM Grants By Donating Old Electronics</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 1, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>AFCEA</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
  </tags>
  <abstract>This year, consider donating your old electronics to benefit the AFCEA Educational Foundation. It’s a simple way to clear your e-clutter, and you could reap a tax benefit.</abstract>
  <text>In the United States, a large percentage of what people label as electronic waste is actually not waste at all, but whole electronic equipment or parts that can be refurbished and marketed for reuse or recycled. This year, consider donating your old electronics to benefit the AFCEA Educational Foundation. It’s a simple way to clear your e-clutter, and you could reap a tax benefit.

E-waste isn’t always easy and convenient to recycle, but AFCEA makes the process worry-free. All personal data on your devices will be erased using state-of-the-art technology. AFCEA also covers the cost of shipping your old gadgets. Simply go to https://afcea.causenetwork.com/upcycle, fill out the form, and you will receive a shipping label.

When your device is resold, you will receive a receipt to claim your tax deduction, and the foundation will receive a donation.

All funds from AFCEA’s e-recycling program will support the Educational Foundation’s Gravely Grants, which aid K-12 classroom science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) programs. 

It’s a win-win for STEM education and for the environment. The United States is one of the largest producers of e-waste in the world. The most recent data from the Environmental Protection Agency shows that in 2013 the average U.S. household owned 28 consumer electronics, and in that same year, the nation generated 3.14 million tons of e-waste. E-waste includes not only outdated cellphones but also old televisions, VCRs, DVD players, stereos, copiers, tablets, computers and any obsolete or unusable electronic devices.  </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
