<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DISA issues RFP for Unconventional SETI Contracting Program</title>
  <author>Sandra Jontz</author>
  <date>February 28, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>DISA</tag>
    <tag>innovation</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) is now accepting requests for proposals (RFPs) for its Systems Engineering, Technology and Innovation (SETI) contract vehicle, a $7 billion, multiyear revamped acquisition process that acutely challenges the status quo in the procurement of engineering support and services.</abstract>
  <text>The Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) is now accepting requests for proposals (RFPs) for its Systems Engineering, Technology and Innovation (SETI) contract vehicle, a $7 billion, multiyear revamped acquisition process that acutely challenges the status quo in the procurement of engineering support and services.

Traditional federal acquisition cycles take far too long to keep pace with the rapid evolutions taking place in technology fields. The SETI program objective is to invert the process for rapid and flexible contracting. The RFPs solicit for an indefinite delivery, indefinite quantity (IDIQ) multiple award task order contracts (MATOC) for systems engineering, technology and innovation projects in support of DISA and the U.S. Defense Department. 

Strategic objectives include evolving the department’s overarching Joint Information Environment (JIE) concept to streamline networking functions, delivering joint command and control (C2) and leadership support, and optimizing investments while still being required to operate within a resource-constrained environment.

The solicitation is issued for full and open competition and has two suites of contracts that include an unrestricted pool and a restricted pool, according to a DISA statement. The restricted pool is for companies that meet the definition of any federally designated small business in accordance with North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) Code 541512. 

SETI’s focus is on fostering, developing and encouraging “innovation with the goal to reduce costs, timelines and provide innovative solutions to deliver emerging capabilities as well as reliable and consistent services to our warfighters,” reads a press statement.

Even though DISA is taking on more of an operational role, it still is fine-tuning its acquisition processes and prepping for its Encore III and Systems Engineering Technology Innovation (SETI) contracts for IT systems support, Alfred Rivera, director of DISA’s Development and Business Center said in January.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img></img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
