<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Serco Supports Anti-Terrorism C4I</title>
  <author/>
  <date>February 28, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Serco</tag>
    <tag>C4I</tag>
    <tag>Anti-terrorism Force Protection Ashore</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Serco Inc., Reston, Virginia, is being awarded $27,094,715 modification to a previously awarded fixed-price contract (N39430-16-C-1811) to exercise the first option period under for lifecycle sustainment of physical security/access control and command, control, communications, computers and intelligence systems in support of the Naval Facilities Engineering Command Anti-Terrorism/Force Protection Ashore program at various Navy installations worldwide. The work to be performed provides for preventive maintenance of hardware, associated firmware and software; response and resolution of service calls for corrective maintenance to include equipment repair, overhaul or replacement; information assurance vulnerability alert to include version control, patch management and vulnerability scanning; asset management to track, maintain, upgrade and dispose of systems; configuration management to establish and maintain consistency of the system attributes with operational requirements and evolving technical baseline; technical refreshments, upgrades and installation of new systems; and programmatic trend analysis to identify systemic sustainment issues such as technology obsolescence. After award of this option, the total cumulative contract value will be $50,937,586. Work will be performed at various installations worldwide, and is expected to be completed March 2018. Fiscal 2017 operations and maintenance (Navy) contract funds in the amount of $7,625,488 are obligated on this award and will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. The Naval Facilities Engineering and Expeditionary Warfare Center, Port Hueneme, California, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
