<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Key Players in NATO's IoT Study</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers</author>
  <date>March 1, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Cyber</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Internet of Things</tag>
    <tag>NATO</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>NATO support for the ongoing study of military applications for the Internet of Things (IoT) falls under the auspices of the agency’s Science and Technology Organization (STO) and its Collaboration Support Office (CSO).</abstract>
  <text>NATO support for the ongoing study of military applications for the Internet of Things (IoT) falls under the auspices of the agency’s Science and Technology Organization (STO) and its Collaboration Support Office (CSO). The study is part of the Collaborative Program of Work of the Information Systems and Technology Panel.

Poland’s Military University of Technology leads the study. The country’s Research and Academic Computer Network (NASK), Warsaw University of Technology (WUT) and Gdansk University of Technology also are involved.

Other participants include: 

• NATO’s Communications and Information Agency (NCIA) and the Allied Command Transformation (ACT).

• The Norwegian Defense Research
Establishment (FFI).

• The U.S. Army Research Laboratory (ARL).

• The U.S. Air Force Research Laboratory (AFRL).

• The Netherlands Organization for Applied Scientific Research (TNO).

• Romania’s Military Equipment and
Technologies Research Agency.

• The Belgian Royal Military Academy.

• The Italian Defense Research Agency.

• Germany’s Fraunhofer Institute for Communication, Information
Processing and Ergonomics (FKIE).

• The Finnish Defense Research Agency.
(Finland is a NATO partner nation.) 

In addition, a number of businesses were invited to join the team through the NATO Industrial Advisory Group. Included are:

• Poland’s Atende SA. 

• Great Britain’s BT Global Services and
Cranfield University Defence and Security.

• Belgium’s Cisco.

• Denmark’s Ebicon, GomSpace and Terma.

• Italy’s IDS Ingegneria Dei Sistemi S.p.A., Rheinmetall Italia and Vitrociset S.p.A.

• The United States’ Terma North America Inc. —GS</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
