<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Baghdad Chapter Formed</title>
  <author>by Katie Packard</author>
  <date>October 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>AFCEA International is pleased to announce the creation of the new Baghdad Chapter. The chapter’s presence will help further the establishment of a viable network for Iraqi information technology professionals and will serve as a collaborative forum for Iraqi and U.S. industry, government and military personnel.The chapter’s formation has been in development for the past six months. AFCEA’s expansion policy committee supported the creation of the chapter and recently submitted a proposal to the executive committee, which approved the chapter’s formation. To establish a chapter in a country where no previous chapter exists, a chapter must obtain a petition of at least 25 members, the recommendation of the expansion policy committee, the recommendation of the president and chief executive officer of AFCEA International, and the approval of the executive committee in order to be granted charter status.Curt Adams, director of member and chapter services, credits Col. Karlton Johnson, USAF, J-6, Multinational Security Transition Command—Iraq (MNSTC-I), and chapter president, as the “prime mover” behind the chapter’s charter status. Others who played a key role in the chapter’s formation include Col. Brian Moore, USA, vice president; 1st Lt. Ashley Pyles, USAF, secretary; and Capt. Stephen Grundorf, USA, treasurer.Col. Johnson explains that the MNSTC-I helps the Iraqi government as it develops, organizes and trains its ministries and Iraqi Security Forces (SIGNAL Magazine, July, page 41). “I advise and mentor [the Iraqi government] on C4 [command, control, communications and computers]. I wanted to show them that successful nations partner with industry. I wanted to introduce them to the idea of joining a professional organization to better themselves and to introduce them to industry partners. AFCEA is one of the best [professional organizations] out there [to do this],” he shares.The chapter’s location offers the potential for U.S. government, industry and military personnel to network with Iraqi government and civilian agencies. The chapter’s focus will be supporting the professional development and training of Iraqi personnel who work in the information technology field. The colonel aims to promote dialogue and the cross sharing of ideas between Iraqi and coalition agencies.Col. Johnson notes that many U.S. industry and military partners expressed an interest in forming a chapter in Iraq. “Lots of people are interested because they know what AFCEA is about. They ask me, ‘How fast can you get this started?’” he observes. Col. Johnson says his Iraqi associates have responded positively to the idea of the chapter. “I spoke to them as Karl, not as a member of the U.S. Air Force, and told them [the chapter] would be worthwhile. They accepted the idea well.” He notes that the chapter will keep in tune with industry best practices in C4ISR (intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance) to help the Iraqi government understand C4ISR potential.The first official chapter meeting will take place next month, Col. Johnson relates. He plans to develop a chapter strategic plan as well as hold a series of briefings to determine the chapter’s goals. “Hopefully within the next six to eight months, we’ll have the first TechNet show in Baghdad to show what’s possible in [information technology] out here,” he shares. Other plans include information technology forums to help educate both Iraqi and coalition agencies on the challenges they face in country. “The biggest benefit to this chapter will be opening a dialogue between [Iraqi and coalition agencies] and showing them the benefit of industry partnerships,” the colonel says.The chapter’s meeting location will alternate between CampFreedom and CampVictory in the greater Baghdad area. Additional chapter members who helped form the chapter include Lt. Col. Donald Baker, USA; Maj. Brian Bakshas, USAF; Patricia Chica, Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA); Maj. Martin Jennings, USAF; Tech. Sgt. Charlotte Kelly, USAF; Maj. Chris Lundy, USAF; Bruce Morgan, DISA; Lt. Col. Lisa Richter, USAF; Lt. Damian Taylor, USN; Maj. John Weigle, USAF; and Capt. Chris Wiley, USAF. AFCEA also has the Camp Arifjan Chapter in Kuwait and the Afghanistan Chapter.Visit Member Service's Region and Chapter Information page to read about other noteworthy chapter events. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
