<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Apollo to Support P-8A Communications Security</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 10, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>United Kingdom</tag>
    <tag>P-8A</tag>
    <tag>Communications</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Apollo Information Systems Corp.,* Los Gatos, California, is being awarded a $13,115,787 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract for the procurement of up to 1,102 Fortinet FortiGate license subscriptions to support communications security for the P-8A Multi-Mission Maritime Poseidon aircraft for the Navy and the government of the United Kingdom. Work will be performed in Los Gatos and is expected to be completed in January 2022. Fiscal 2017 research, development, test and evaluation (Navy) funds in the amount of $83,923 will be obligated at the time of award, none of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured via an electronic request for proposals; nine offers were received. This contract combines purchase for the Navy ($12,947,943; 98.7 percent) and the government of the United Kingdom ($167,844; 1.3 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales program. The Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Lakehurst, New Jersey, is the contracting activity (N68335-17-D-0009).? Hamilton Sundstrand, Rockford, Illinois, is being awarded $12,248,136 for firm-fixed-price delivery order 7013 under a previously awarded long-term contract (N00383-12-D-011N) for the repair of the constant frequency generator used on the V-22 aircraft to support both MV-22 (Marines) and CV-22 (Air Force). Work will be performed in Rockford and is expected to be completed by September 2017. Fiscal 2017 working capital (Navy) funds in the amount of $12,248,136 will be obligated at the time of award, none of which will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was a sole source pursuant to the authority set forth in 10 U.S. Code 2304(C)(1). The requirement was posted to the Federal Business Opportunities website and the Navy Electronic Commerce Online website, with one offer received. Naval Supply Systems Command Weapon Systems Support, Philadelphia, is the contracting activity.

*Small Business

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
