<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>SPAWAR Awards IT Contract</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 10, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SPAWAR</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>ViON Corp., Herndon, Virginia, is being awarded a $34,790,000 indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contract to provide capacity as a service support to Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command (SPAWAR) headquarters, SPAWAR System Center Pacific and SPAWAR System Center Atlantic. The capacity as a service acquisition model allows SPAWAR to more accurately scale up and down its information technology (IT) infrastructure to meet evolving mission requirements. Savings are realized through no upfront costs and a pay-as-you-go acquisition model, reducing waste usually associated with overbuying IT equipment to eventually meet an expectation of mission requirement. Under this contract, ViON is responsible for providing on-demand, on-premise computing, networking and storage solutions for a variety of systems and applications for the command's research, development, testing and evaluation core infrastructures, laboratory and data center environments. This contract includes options that, if exercised, would bring the maximum contract value to $49,990,000. Work will be performed in Charleston, South Carolina (63 percent); San Diego (30 percent); New Orleans (5 percent); and Norfolk, Virginia (2 percent). Work is expected to be completed by March 2022. If all options are exercised, work will continue through March 2024. Navy working capital funds in the amount of $326,120 will be obligated for the first delivery order to be issued at contract award. This delivery order satisfies the minimum order requirement of $100,000. No funds will expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This contract was competitively procured, with proposals solicited via the Federal Business Opportunities website. The Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, San Diego, is the contracting activity (N00039-17-D-0003).? </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
