<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Hampton Roads Chapter Expands Outreach with “Lunch and Learn”</title>
  <author>by Katie Packard</author>
  <date>October 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Hampton Roads Chapter hosted “Lunch and Learn,” a new outreach event, in August for the staff of the information technology division of the Joint Forces Staff College, a component of the NationalDefense University. The chapter held the event to introduce information technology professionals to the benefits of AFCEA membership. The agenda included upcoming courses offered through the Professional Development Center to demonstrate the wide ariety of course offerings. Col. Joseph J. Frazier, USA, former acting commandant of the Joint Forces Staff College (JFSC), discusses his experience as an AFCEA member with the audience during the Hampton Roads Chapter’s Lunch and Learn in August.Lt. Cmdr. S. Michelle Layne, USN, the chapter’s military vice president, suggested the Lunch and Learn, noting it would be a new way to implement the chapter’s outreach goals outside of its monthly meetings. The chapter’s board of directors approved the idea, deciding the event would benefit individuals who do not attend the monthly meetings. Chapter members sent out e-mail notifications to colleagues and friends in addition to distributing flyers.Lt. Col. Curtis R. Fox, USA, chief of the information technology division at the Joint Forces Staff College (JFSC), invited the chapter to help it connect with information technology professionals and armed forces members. Col. Fox also served as the emcee for the event. Col. Joseph J. Frazier, USA, former acting commandant of the JFSC, hosted the lunch. Guest speakers included Capt. Kathy Donovan, USN, commander, Carrier Strike Group Ten/N-6; Col. Earnest E. Hansley, USA, chief information officer, NationalDefenseUniversity; Mark Sinclair, past chapter president; Steve Kelley, regional vice president, AFCEA; and Teresa Duvall, chapter vice president.The agenda highlighted the benefits of AFCEA membership. Scholarship and networking opportunities were discussed, and the guest speakers shared how their AFCEA memberships benefited their professional development. Attendees also received a copy of the ProfessionalDevelopmentCenter’s (PDC’s) course catalog so they could search for classes applicable to their career field. The benefits of the PDC’s leadership forum were emphasized as well. The forum offers students the opportunity to learn from senior leaders in the intelligence, command and control, and information technology fields.Glenda Bluhm, chapter president, shares, “I have received an enormous amount of positive feedback and requests for more activities and events like this.” She comments that military personnel respond well to AFCEA’s military members, who can highlight the ways in which the association benefits them during active duty and retirement. Whit Ludington, publicity committee chair, agrees with Bluhm, citing his belief that the event’s success was due in part to obtaining speakers with active duty military experience who could share their personal experiences as AFCEA members. “We wanted people the attendees could identify with directly, so we got speakers currently working with the [JFSC] to discuss their personal experiences and [the] rewards from being AFCEA members,” he states.Capt. Donovan notes that part of the event’s appeal was the relaxed atmosphere. “AFCEA offers so many benefits, from scholarships to networking, and the beauty is that folks can be as active as they desire or be a sponge and soak up the information [from the guest speakers, monthly meetings and technology shows],” she says.The Lunch and Learn’s success has encouraged the chapter to pursue similar events. The chapter continues to focus on recruiting military members in addition to government and industry personnel.Visit Member Service's Region and Chapter Information page to read about other noteworthy chapter events. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
