<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Raytheon Receives Aegis Modernization Task Order</title>
  <author/>
  <date>March 13, 2017</date>
  <departments>
    <department>Acquisition and Contracting</department>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Raytheon</tag>
    <tag>Aegis</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Raytheon Co., Integrated Defense Systems, Marlborough, Massachusetts, is being awarded a nearly $7.9 million order under a previous agreement for Aegis Modernization production requirements.</abstract>
  <text>Raytheon Co., Integrated Defense Systems, Marlborough, Massachusetts, is being awarded a $7,852,566 firm-fixed-price order under previously awarded basic ordering agreement N00024-17-G-5103 for Aegis Modernization (AMOD) production requirements. This order covers the production of Multi-Mission Signal Processor Ordnance Alteration (ORDALT) kits; kill assessment system ORDALT kits and spares; radio frequency coherent combiner kits; high-voltage power supply sidewall capacitors; traveling waves tube-monitoring circuits; stabilized master oscillator ORDALT kits; as well as test and installation efforts to support the AMOD program. The program fields combat system upgrades that will enhance the anti-air warfare and ballistic missile defense capabilities of Aegis-equipped Arleigh Burke-class destroyers and Ticonderoga-class cruisers. This order includes options that, if exercised, would bring its cumulative value to $18,041,587. It combines purchases for the Navy (97 percent) and the government of Japan (3 percent) under the Foreign Military Sales program. Work will be performed in Chesapeake, Virginia (42 percent); Andover, Massachusetts (38 percent); Burlington, Massachusetts (12 percent); and Marlborough, Massachusetts (8 percent). It is expected to be completed by September 2019. Fiscal 2017 other procurement (Navy) and fiscal 2017 defensewide procurement funds in the amount of $7,852,566 will be obligated at the time of award and will not expire at the end of the current fiscal year. This order was not competitively procured in accordance with 10 U.S. Code 2304(c)(1); only one responsible source and no other supplies or services will satisfy agency requirements. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Washington, D.C., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
    <img>Raytheon is being awarded a task order for Aegis Modernization production requirements.</img>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
