<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>2009 Security Directory Update Underway</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>November 17, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The community of companies doing business in the security arena is as large and diverse as the products and services they offer. Organizations may find it difficult to locate the company with the products and services matching their specific requirements.

To help readers compare and find solutions best suited to their needs, SIGNAL Magazine and AFCEA produce two security directories each year. The print version is published annually in the February issue of SIGNAL Magazine. The issue also will be distributed at the AFCEA Homeland Security conference, February 25-26, 2009, in Washington, D.C. Participation in the print version is open to any company that offers relevant products and services.

The AFCEA Online Security Directory will be available in early 2009. Inclusion in the electronic product is a free benefit of AFCEA corporate membership, and all corporate member companies that participate in the print directory are listed in the online directory automatically.

All companies must submit a new form each year for placement in either directory. Security Directory records are unrelated to AFCEA membership or Source Book records. Companies must update their information for the Security Directory separately.

The deadline to update is December 1, 2008.

PRINT DIRECTORY: To include your company, go to www.afcea.org/security/submission.cfm?s=w and fill out the brief submission form.

ONLINE DIRECTORY: Any company that updates the Security Directory form and is an AFCEA member will automatically have its listing included in the 2009 Online Security Directory. You must be an AFCEA member to be listed in the online directory.

To find out if your company is an AFCEA corporate member, go to www.afcea.org/sponsors. For more information about becoming a corporate member, go to www.afcea.org/membership/corporate or e-mail service@afcea.org.   

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION:

The 2008 online directory is available at www.afcea.org/security. E-mail securitydirectory@afcea.org for additional information.

For Homeland Security conference information, contact Gina McGovern at gmcgovern@afcea.org.

For information about advertising in the February issue of SIGNAL, contact Jennifer Deuterman at jdeuterman@afcea.org.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
