<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Chertoff Kicks Off SOLUTIONS</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>November 17, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Honorable Michael Chertoff, secretary of the U.S. Department of Homeland Security, will set the tone for the fourth SOLUTIONS series event with a plenary speech on the first morning. “Cyberspace: Challenges and Solutions for National Security” is the focus of the conference, which takes place December 10-11 at the Ronald Reagan Building and International Trade Center, Washington, D.C.In addition to Chertoff, a number of high-ranking officials from the federal government as well as the military will offer their insights during the conference. Speakers include Vice Adm. Nancy Brown, USN, director of command, control, communications and computer systems, J-6, the Joint Staff; Vice Adm. James Winnefeld, USN, strategic plans and policy director, J-5, the Joint Staff; Lt. Gen. John Paxton Jr., USMC, operations director, J-3, the Joint Staff; Maj. Gen. William T. Lord, USAF, commander, Air Force Cyberspace Command (provisional); Brig. Gen. Steve Smith, USNR, chief cyber officer, Office of the Chief Information Officer/G-6, U.S. Army; and Melissa Hathaway, senior adviser for the Director of National Intelligence and cyber coordination executive.Other officials who have been invited to speak include Lt. Gen. Keith B. Alexander, USA, director, National Security Agency, and chief, Central Security Service; Sergey Brin, president of technology, Google; Gen. Kevin P. Chilton, USAF, commander, U.S. Strategic Command; and Bob Lentz, deputy assistant secretary of defense for information and identity assurance. In addition to individual speakers, the event comprises four tracks that allow attendees to discuss issues of importance to them. The Emerging Network Warfare track focuses on traditional threats such as state-based warfare as well as transnational threats, including nonstate-based warfare. The Inter-Dependency of Cyber Security track sessions will include discussions about how to recognize a threat and formulate a common response as well as the role of the public-private partnership. During discussions in the How to Harness the Cyber Future track, panelists and audience members will focus on commercial trends and future technology innovations as well as the international influence on the future of cyberspace including alliances. Cyber Operations and Irregular Warfare track discussions will home in on cyber operations in an open-source environment, the influence of adversary motivations on cyber operations and the current state of cyber operations, including a “report card.”To attend the conference, register online. Information technology professionals who cannot attend the conference in person can still participate. A wiki is available as an information repository, a group discussion site will help facilitate an ongoing dialogue, and streaming video and podcasts will allow those not able to attend in person to participate in meaningful ways by tapping in right from the desktop to ask questions of speakers and panelists. Information is available on the SOLUTIONS Web site. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
