<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Homefront Help</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>December 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2008 12 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Homefront Help is SIGNAL Connections’ effort to support U.S. service members, veterans and their families. The column highlights programs that offer resources and assistance to the military community ranging from care packages to benefits and everything in between. In that same spirit, Homefront Help presents opportunities for readers to donate time, offer resources and send words of thanks to those who sacrifice for freedom. Programs that provide services are listed in red. Opportunities for the public to reach out to service members are listed in blue. Each program description includes a link to the organization's Web site, when available.Operation Support Our TroopsLike so many troop support organizations, this one grew out of a family’s effort to be there for their soldier as well as all others serving their country, and when these people got started, there was no stopping them. What began with rallies has grown to a full-fledged support mechanism that involves the provision of packages at holidays, fundraisers, and visits and supplies for those injured in combat as well as tributes to those who paid the ultimate price for home and country. The mission of Operation Support Our Troops is to offer opportunities for all Americans to demonstrate to members of the armed forces and their commander in chief that they are supported and appreciated for their service. According to the organization, the goal is to ensure that troops know that “united we stand and divided we fall are not empty words, but words to which we subscribe.”Most recently, Operation Support Our Troops adopted 10,000 deployed service members and sent them packages for Christmas. The organization collects items for these types of mailings. In addition, it also accepts cash donations and sells merchandise to raise funds for various efforts. Items can be purchased and donations can be made online. Also online are photo albums and links to various resources for the military and general public.Anyone interested in receiving regular information about the organization and its activities can subscribe to the e-mail distribution list by following the “OSOT Sign-Up” link. People interested in learning more about Operation Support Our Troops and its various programs should click the “Contact OSOT” link and find the correct point of contact for their query. Operation Goody BagOperation Goody Bag goes above and beyond traditional troop support by working with the young to boost the morale of all who sacrifice for their country. The organization instills appreciation for first responders and military members as well as awareness of the value of service in schoolchildren as a student-centric service learning initiative. Students design the Goody Bags, write personal letters of appreciation, create original poetry and puzzles, and hold fundraisers for candy and postage expenses. Each bag holds five pieces of candy, two poems, one personal letter and one puzzle. The bags are stapled shut with a copy of the “Tale of the Goody Bag.” The organization filled and shipped its 100,000th package in November. The treats are shipped to military personnel; fire, rescue, ambulance and K-9 organizations; and veterans’ homes, Veterans of Foreign Wars posts, military hospitals and U.S. military academies. The goal is to create a bond of friendship and respect among children, communities and first-responder organizations. The bond should help inspire students to participate in service organizations in the future. More information, including how to participate, is available on the Web site. Send a Holiday Greeting to the TroopsEven though the deadline has passed for sending packages to reach deployed service members by the holidays, the public can still show its support during this festive time of year through electronic messages. Several options are available for folks who want to send notes of appreciation and support. America Supports You offers a Thank the Troops Message Form that anyone can use. OperationDearAbby.net provides a means for the public to send messages, and users can even choose the branch of service of their recipients. The U.S. Army has a Web site where people can post letters to soldiers. MotoMail uses Internet technology to allow family and friends to send in their messages via the Web; physical cards will be delivered to their deployed Marines usually within a day. Those who want to send a message but do not know a specific Marine can post their thoughts and well wishes via MotoMail’s Support the Troops Bulletin Board.  The SIGNAL Connectionsstaff encourages readers to take advantage of the programs mentioned in this column and to pass along the information. In addition, if you know of a program that is helping service personnel, please let us know about it. Submit that information to SIGNAL's news editor.The SIGNAL Connections staff has made every effort to verify the legitimacy of these programs and to include information accurate at the time of publication. Inclusion in this column does not constitute an endorsement by AFCEA International or SIGNAL Connections. Homefront Help Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
