<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>December 15, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2008 12 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Infrared Tactical LightWarfighters and law enforcement personnel require rugged tactical illumination to carry out their missions. This family of handheld and  gun-mounted tactical lights is designed to provide long-range infrared illumination without compromising night vision. The handheld IR Super Tac and IR TL-2 light emitting diodes (LEDs) and gun-mounted IT TLR-1 and TLR-2 all feature a high-power, shock-resistant, 850 nanometer LED with a 20,000-hour lifespan. For more information, visit www.streamlight.com.Vehicle Mission ProcessorThis rugged multicore mission processor subsystem is designed to meet U.S. military specifications for operating in harsh environmental conditions. The DuraCOR 810-DUO is built around a modular, open-architecture design with an Intel Core2 Duo central processing unit, a flash solid state disk and an expandable rugged chassis. For more information, visit www.parvus.com.Rugged Portable Communications Platform The PlexSys-RP is a self-contained, rugged Compact PCI-based portable computer. Its chassis is made of formed aluminum sheet metal casing with a tan anodized finish. Two handles are built into the top of the chassis for portability. For more information, visit www.dtims.com/products/cpci/plexsysrp.phpSensor Stream Computing PlatformHigh-performance sensor systems require sensitive and powerful equipment for calibration. The Mercury Sensor Stream Computing Platform allows users to benchmark and evaluate application performance graphics processing units in a variety of environments. The platform uses a dual dual-core Intel Xeon-based VX6-200 single-board computer, a range of input/output interfaces and a VXS-GSC5200 dual MXM graphics processing unit module. For more information, visit www.mc.com/gpu.Digital Visual Interface SwitcherDesigned for complex graphics applications, this compact digital visual interface (DVI) switcher is packaged in a rugged and compact  chassis. The Linx 8x8SP DVI is a high-performance, nonblocking DVI matrix routing switcher with eight inputs and eight outputs. When combined with digital signal sources and displays, it provides end-to-end digital signal distribution. For more information, visit www.rgb.com.Rugged Test Equipment Cases Sometimes equipment must be tested in the field under harsh conditions. The Fluke Extreme Cases are designed to house the Fluke 287 and 289 Ture-rms Logging Multimeter and the Fluke 87V Industrial Multimeter. For more information, visit www.fluke.com.    New Products Archives</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
