<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Department of Homeland Security Reaches Out to Small Businesses</title>
  <author>by Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>January 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Small businesses interested in working with the U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS) can meet one-on-one with representatives from several components of the department as well as with the agency’s partner corporations. The Vendor Outreach Sessions program offers small business owners or their representatives the opportunity to spend 15 minutes with up to four different DHS organizations. The time can be used to explain their capabilities or obtain more information about an upcoming contract. Each month, representatives from as many as 50 companies take advantage of this opportunity at absolutely no cost to them.Kevin Boshears, director, Office of Small and Disadvantaged Business Utilization, DHS, explains that the briefing opportunities program, which somewhat resembles speed dating, came with him when he moved from the U.S. Treasury Department. The department began the program in the 1990s and found it to be extremely successful, so he decided to implement it at DHS, he says.Boshears relates that one key to the success of a program such as this is the meticulous management of each day’s activities during the monthly sessions. The meetings all take place in one room, and the day begins with a brief introduction about the logistics of the day. At 9 a.m., company representatives go directly to the table of their first appointment and the individual briefings begin. At 9:14 a.m., companies are alerted that one minute remains. At 9:15 a.m., company representatives move on to the tables of their next appointment, he explains. To arrange an appointment to meet with the DHS or corporate representatives, small firms first must be registered with the department. Once registered, the small business schedules appointments using the electronic appointment scheduling system on the Web. Scheduling opens approximately a week before the event, and spots fill up quickly, Boshears says. Because of this scheduling system, companies know beforehand which DHS representatives or corporate executives they will be meeting with face to face.In general, between 10 and 15 representatives from DHS and corporations are available for the sessions. A total of approximately 40 to 50 small businesses meet with these counselors per half-day session; each small firm generally meets with four different organizations.Next month’s event takes place on February 19 at the Holiday Inn Washington—Capitol Columbia Ballroom, 550 C Street, SW, Washington, D.C. Scheduling sign-up begins at noon EST on February 12. Boshears advises that small firms interested in taking part in the program should start by doing their homework. Review the DHS forecast of contract opportunities to determine if their company’s capabilities are a good match for one of the upcoming contract awards, he suggests. For example, if the U.S. Coast Guard has announced a specific project, companies should be prepared to address the topic of the contract. Companies then should prepare their presentations so that they can succinctly explain the solutions they offer to the counselors from each organization. Coming to the table with prepared questions also is a good idea, Boshears says.Feedback from previous sessions has been overwhelmingly positive, he relates. Attendees complete a survey at the end of each event, and 97 percent have given the event an overall rating of good or excellent.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
