<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Central Maryland Chapter Provides Specialized Outreach Through Women in Intelligence Group</title>
  <author>by Katie Packard</author>
  <date>January 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 01 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Women who work in the intelligence community and who live in Maryland are finding support through an outreach effort of the Central Maryland Chapter. Approved by the chapter in October 2007, the Women in Intelligence Group (WIIG) was established to provide a forum for women who work in this field to collaborate, network and share the issues and challenges they experience. The group’s target audience includes Young AFCEANs, technical and nontechnical members of the intelligence community, and government, military and industry personnel.Currently, the group has more than 180 participants. WIIG Chair Jennifer R. Walker, vice president of business operations, Pangia Technologies LLC, notes that as a result of WIIG programs and events, both chapter and Young AFCEAN Committee membership numbers have increased. WIIG has continued to expand in part due to its successful mentoring program. Mentorship Circles comprise two mentors and 8 to 10 junior colleagues. The circles meet quarterly to discuss topics such as networking, professional growth and development, best practices and mentorship. The circles also address such issues as targeted skills development, work and life balance and women leaders. Currently, WIIG has six active mentor circles with more than 60 participants.“The WIIG Mentorship Circle program in particular has been useful for understanding our commonality and [building] strong relationships that act as an extended resource for getting my work done and [expanding] our business,” shares WIIG member Brynn Conover, vice president, Kadix Systems.WIIG also sponsors educational programs through its community and education programs. WIIG members volunteer to speak at local high schools and colleges on topics such as women’s challenges in the information technology and scientific career fields, and the need for more women to join the intelligence community as leaders and subject matter experts. WIIG members spoke at the University of Maryland Clark School of Engineering’s first Women in Engineering DREAM conference, where WIIG presented its first scholarship, a $2,500 prize awarded to Amy Chou, a Baltimore-area high school student who is now studying engineering at the university.For the holiday season, WIIG sold gift baskets as a fundraiser. The proceeds will help fund the WIIG scholarship, which is offered to female high school students pursuing careers in the science, mathematics or technology fields, and will help promote additional mentoring programs in the community. The fundraiser generated more than $1,000.The group also has established an ongoing professional development series for women. The latest event, held in November, was titled “Cracking the Ceiling: Observations Over a Generation.” The group’s October event, a panel discussion on the topic "Keys to Successful Career Transitions," received maximum attendance.Tina Coleman, senior member, technical staff, PROTEUS Technologies LLC, appreciates WIIG’s benefits. “I’ve looked to WIIG as a vehicle to give me that cross-enterprise vision, to hear what’s important to whom and who are the key players. That we’re a group of women enabling that enterprise vision raises the level of excitement…I enjoy the opportunities WIIG offers to help and be helped by other women, just as an avenue for us to show what we can do.”Dr. Stacy Trammell, president, Zavda Technologies LLC, agrees. “[The WIIG meetings help me] gain ideas on how to make my work/life balance efficient and effective for my family and me. I truly feel that the other women in WIIG feel the same way,” she says.“For those who are a few steps ahead of me, I see now clearly that my goals can be achieved, and no, my bar is not set too high. WIIG is an excellent program for women,” Trammel adds.WIIG aims at continuing to provide timely programs and events for its members. The next networking event for WIIG members is scheduled for early March. Walker notes that the group intends to offer additional education programs and increase fundraising for the chapter’s scholarship fund. In addition, WIIG will continue to recruit new members, particularly from the government and military. The group also is willing to assist other chapters that are interested in forming their own Women in Intelligence groups.Interested in learning more? Check out the February issue of SIGNAL Magazine, in the mail to AFCEA members and subscribers February 2, 2009. For more information about purchasing this issue, joining AFCEA or subscribing to SIGNAL, contact AFCEA Member Services.Visit Member Services' Region and Chapter Information page to read about other noteworthy chapter events.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
