<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Homefront Help</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>January 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 01 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Homefront Help is SIGNAL Connections’ effort to support U.S. service members, veterans and their families. The column highlights programs that offer resources and assistance to the military community ranging from care packages to benefits and everything in between. In that same spirit, Homefront Help presents opportunities for readers to donate time, offer resources and send words of thanks to those who sacrifice for freedom. Programs that provide services are listed in red. Opportunities for the public to reach out to service members are listed in blue. Each program description includes a link to the organization's Web site, when available.Freedom Alliance“The price of liberty is eternal vigilance.” So reads the slogan of Freedom Alliance, which directs all the organization’s efforts. The charitable and educational foundation was founded by Lt. Col. Oliver North, USMC (Ret.), who said from the beginning that the goal would be to work to “keep America strong, keep America prosperous and keep America free.” The mission of Freedom Alliance is to advance the American heritage of freedom by honoring and encouraging military service, defending the sovereignty of the United States and promoting a strong national defense. Freedom Alliance carries out its mission in several ways. The organization cares for wounded veterans currently in hospitals by sending them desired resources as well as paying travel and lodging expenses for their families. Military families grieving the loss of a loved one also can reach out to Freedom Alliance for help and support. Other outreach efforts include educating the public on how to become involved citizenry through methods such as contacting elected officials and writing letters to the editor. Additional Web offerings include a column by Col. North, a link to the radio show of Freedom Alliance’s president Tom Kilgannon and issues of Freedom Alliance Review. The organization also runs a scholarship program for dependent children of active duty service members who died or were permanently disabled in the line of duty, or who currently are certified as POW or MIA. Complete qualification guidelines and the application are available online.To further its ideals of a strong America in the future, Freedom Alliance runs the Military Leadership Academy. High school students attend to gain leadership abilities through mental and physical challenges based on U.S. Army curriculum. Students also tour historical sites and military bases. Air Compassion for VeteransTroops might not always feel lifted by the wings of angels, but Air Compassion for Veterans is making sure they come close. The organization provides free travel services for eligible warfighters, wounded warriors, veterans and their families to ensure none of them is denied access to distant medical care because of a lack of means to acquire long-distance medical air transportation. Air Compassion for Veterans arranges and provides its charitable patient travel without duplicating the efforts of other charities. The Web site includes a link that lists other groups who offer similar services and may be able to assist with certain needs. People interested in seeking assistance from Air Compassion for Veterans can access the help online or call (888) 662-6794. Also posted online is information about donating to the organization. National Resource DirectoryLaunched in November 2008 as part of Warrior Care Month, the National Resource Directory is a Web-based network of care coordinators, providers and partners who have resources for wounded, ill and injured service members, veterans, their families and families of the fallen as well as those who support them. The directory includes more than 10,000 medical and other services to help members of the military community achieve their goals as they progress through recovery and rehabilitation to reintegrate with the larger community.The National Resource Directory is organized into six major categories: benefits and compensation; education, training and employment; family and caregiver support; health; housing and transportation; and services and resources. It provides helpful checklists, a Frequently Asked Questions section and connections to peer support groups. All the resources on the Web site can be found through a general or state and local search tool. The U.S. Defense Department initiated the National Resource Directory in a collaborative effort with the departments of Labor and Veterans Affairs. The SIGNAL Connections staff encourages readers to take advantage of the programs mentioned in this column and to pass along the information. In addition, if you know of a program that is helping service personnel, please let us know about it. Submit that information to SIGNAL's news editor.The SIGNAL Connections staff has made every effort to verify the legitimacy of these programs and to include information accurate at the time of publication. Inclusion in this column does not constitute an endorsement by AFCEA International or SIGNAL Connections.Homefront Help Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
