<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>January 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 01 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Rugged Military Keyboard Warfighters need equipment that can work in the harshest conditions. The KCR-106BP-612 is a rugged military keyboard consisting of an aluminum case with a compact rubber mat typing surface that includes an integrated pointing device. The keys are designed for ease of use by operators wearing full chemical, biological and nuclear equipment. Fully sealed against liquid, dust and sand, the keyboard also features backlit legends with eight levels of illumination for use in low-light conditions. For more information, visit www.devlin.co.uk.Electronics Chassis  Designed for use in tight spaces such as vehicles, this chassis can house a range of electronics such as motherboards, hard drives and cooling fans. The Rugged 3U RMSC MX is made of 1.6-millimeter steel and features a 400-watt EPS power supply, expansion slots and four open drive bays for additional equipment. For more information, visit www.cyberresearch.com/chassis.Solar-Powered Roadway FlasherBases and other austere facilities require safety and warning systems that can operate with little or no local infrastructure. The R838 wireless intelligent traffic systems (ITS) flasher incorporates solar power modules, light-emitting diodes and wireless activation technology in a single stand-alone device. The devices can be programmed to specify how long they flash before automatically shutting down. For more information, visit www.roadlights.com/content/products/r838.aspx. Board-Level Airflow SensorThis device is engineered to measure airflow across critical areas in electronic systems and warn about fan failure or blockage before temperatures rise in the equipment compartment. The F600 series of devices were designed for use in telecommunications, information technology, military and medical systems. For more information, visit www.degreec.com/standard-product/f600.html.Ethernet SwitchesIndustrial systems are becoming increasingly linked to management and control systems. The i802 and i803 line of rugged Ethernet switches are designed to support process control applications such as those in the oil and gas, petrochemical, metals and mining, and wind farm industries. The devices feature eight 10/100BaseTx ports and one additional gigabit port and include managed Ethernet switch firmware. For more information, visit www.ruggedcom.com/products/ruggedswitch/.Smartphone Armor  Personal handheld electronics can take a beating from daily use. The Defender Series case is designed to protect the Hewlett-Packard iPAQ 600 series Business Navigator smartphone. The case protects the device from drops, dust and scratches. For more information, visit www.otterbox.com. New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
