<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title> The Information Assurance New Year's Resolution List</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>January 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>On Cyber Patrol</tag>
    <tag>January 2009</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Ten things to keep in mind about information assurance in 2009.</abstract>
  <text>I will always be vigilant about my hardware, data and network access, even among fellow soldiers and coworkers, because stuff happens.I will stop putting the firewall in the safe at night because it works a lot better when left hooked to the system.I will implement all IAVAs in a timely manner because the word vulnerability is in IAVA for a reason.I will never put my personal, unsecured thumb drive on a military network – oh, wait, I forgot.  I can’t use ANY thumb drive on a military network because somebody broke this rule already and they even took our government issued drives away!I will not hook my game console up to a secure network no matter how much fun it is to play Splinter Cell™ with my buddies around the world.  (Example: Buffer overflows can allow malicious code to run on these devices.)I will make sure that I have the IA training I need to do my job.I will stop calling MSGT Bozonski a &amp;!(*%% because he made me take all the kewl videos and games I downloaded off my laptop.  Uh, he was right.  I did get a virus.  It’s safe cyber for me in 2009!I will remember to keep my circuits certified.I will not lose my CAC.I will share On Cyber Patrol with my unit because IA goof-ups are only funny in cartoons.Whatever is on your own IA New Year’s Resolution List, remember that Information Assurance prevents loss of data that can threaten operations, mission success and even personal security.  Have a safe and secure 2009!The On Cyber Patrol© cartoon and supporting articles are created and made available by the U.S. Army’s Office of Information Assurance and Compliance, NETCOM, CIO/G6. For more information on the OCP program or to submit ideas for upcoming cartoons/articles, contact oncyberpatrol@hqda.army.mil.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
