<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>February 17, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 02 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Vehicle-mounted Computer Warfighters and first responders need specialized equipment to maintain communications and manage sensor data in challenging environments. The Vehicle Mount Tracer PC is a rugged computer and monitor designed to resist heat and vibration common to vehicle interiors. The device features a 12.1-inch monitor, a fanless heat dissipation system and a fully sealed chassis that is resistant to liquids and other contaminants. For more information, contact www.devlin.co.uk.Digital TorquemeterKey vehicle components such as drive and propeller shafts require specialized sensors. The MCRT 86000V and 87000V family of torquemeters are designed to measure torque in diesel and other propulsion systems. The devices also are resistant to electromagnetic interference from other nearby systems. For more information, contact www.himmelstein.com.Coin-type CapacitorThis coin-type capacitor is designed for use in handheld wireless devices and electronics. The XH311HG series of capacitors can be  used as backup energy for real-time clocks, mobile telephones, digital cameras and personal medical devices. Other platform applications include notebook personal computers, radios, Global Positioning System devices and disk drives. For more information, contact www.seikoinstruments.com.Visual Communications SoftwareThe right tools are important for conveying information at meetings and presentations. SmartDraw 2009.5 is designed to help users work more efficiently with Microsoft applications. The program features tools to streamline the creation and use of PowerPoint presentations, interoperate with Microsoft Project charts and integrate Excel spreadsheets. For more information, visit www.smartdraw.com.Data Logging SoftwareHOBOware is a graphing and analysis software package for HOBO data loggers. The software operates on PC and Macintosh platforms and allows users to analyze environmental and energy data recorded with the loggers. A graphic user interface allows operators to select environmental parameters to display, format graphs, perform analysis and save projects. For more information, visit www.onsetcomp.com.Mobile OperationsCenter Establishing command and control during a disaster or other emergency can be difficult if existing infrastructure is damaged or destroyed. The Commander is a multipurpose portable operations center that can be customized to meet operational requirements. It provides an environmentally controlled shelter with its own power, hygiene and storage facilities. For more information, visit www.nor-e.com. New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
