<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Out of the Laboratories and Into the Seas</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>February 17, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 02 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Any leader in any of the military services will declare that support to the warfighter in ongoing operations is the top priority. For service laboratories and system integrators, support to the warfighter centers on developing and deploying new technologies as quickly as possible. It is no surprise that these technologies are changing the way war is fought. Most changes in warfare have been technology-driven. But in this post-Cold-War environment, technology change is a two-way street. Technology both is changing warfighting and is being changed by it.Again, this concept is not new. What is new is the pace of change taking place in both directions of the defense technology flow. Warfighters’ requests for new capabilities are being met in record time as the military speeds new technologies into the field. Similarly, the field is changing almost as quickly as new solutions hit the battlespace. These changes are driving the need for new technology-driven capabilities.Take networking as an example. Much of the focus has been on extending the network down to the warfighter. The nature of counter-insurgency urban operations has increased the need for the warfighter to have top-notch situational awareness. But as more capabilities enter the network, it increases the requirements for moving information down that network. And, new sources of information—sensor platforms such as unmanned aerial vehicles—are being incorporated into the force. These in turn are changing the very nature of the network, which affects how information moves down to the warfighter.And of course, the enemy changes its tactics to adjust to the new capabilities introduced by allied forces. This requires counteraction by friendly forces, which usually entails adding new technologies to regain the upper hand.Introducing new warfighter technologies is as complicated as the technologies are diverse. Some capabilities can be implemented simply as upgrades to existing systems. But other more complex systems can take years to wend their way through the traditional acquisition process. And, given the nature of information technologies, a drawn-out procurement is counterproductive to improving the force.Just as they do with technology development, defense planners constantly strive to find new ways of increasing the speed of technology deployment. One method currently bearing fruit is to attach new capabilities to system upgrades that are being moved to the field. Where this approach is applicable, it speeds innovations to the front faster than would be possible through traditional means.Military laboratories also are working with industry and academia to address mid- and long-term needs. Adapting commercial off-the-shelf technologies eliminates the long time frame required to develop military specific solutions. And, academia often performs complementary research that can be incorporated into the development of a vital military technology.The influx of new warfighter technologies is increasing; and as long as warfighters continue to need them, that flow is not likely to abate. As the force becomes even more dependent on technology at all levels, researchers likely will add to its wish list with new capabilities. The challenge may be not “how,” but “how quickly” the technology can get into the hands of the warfighter.—The EditorMore information on warfighter technologies is available in the March 2009 issue of SIGNAL Magazine, in the mail to AFCEA members and subscribers March 2, 2009. For information about purchasing this issue, joining AFCEA or subscribing to SIGNAL, contact AFCEA Member Services.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
