<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Homefront Help</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>March 16, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 03 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Homefront Help is SIGNAL Connections’ effort to support U.S. service members, veterans and their families. The column highlights programs that offer resources and assistance to the military community ranging from care packages to benefits and everything in between. In that same spirit, Homefront Help presents opportunities for readers to donate time, offer resources and send words of thanks to those who sacrifice for freedom. Programs that provide services are listed in red. Opportunities for the public to reach out to service members are listed in blue. Each program description includes a link to the organization's Web site, when available.Pro vs. GI JoeDoin’ a little for those who do a lot, this atypical nonprofit offers troops a chance to battle professional athletes and celebrities in head-to-head video game competitions via the Internet. Pro vs. GI Joe sets up real-time video game competitions among celebrities, high-ranking military officials and politicians stateside and troops overseas using Web-connected technologies such as PlayStation, Xbox Live and Nintendo Wii. The group also attempts to reunite warfighters with family members via webcam during the events.Pro vs. GI Joe works with its official partner the USO to identify participating troops and arrange for them to play from USO centers worldwide. Events have been held with troops from Iraq, Kuwait, Japan, Germany, Cuba and other locations. Currently, Pro vs. GI Joe does not have the bandwidth in Iraq to support online gaming, but service members can obtain permission to travel to Kuwait and play from CampVirginia. The organization attempts to pair up pros and Joes from the same area—for example troops from Arizona with the Arizona Cardinals—to make it easier for family members to participate. It also works to match up troops with their favorite celebrity or team, working with the USO to identify the biggest fans. Information about how GI Joes are chosen for events is available by e-mailing addie@prosvsgijoes.org. Professional athletes and celebrities who want to participate can request more information online as well by following a link after clicking on “The Pro” from the home page. Average Joes who want to help out can obtain information on donating money, sponsorships and volunteering on the Web site. Additional Web offerings include lists of competitions already held along with photos and multimedia options. Operation: Birthday CakeWant to do something sweet for deployed service members? How about sending them a gourmet cake from Bake Me A Wish! In partnership with Soldiers’ Angels, Bake Me A Wish offers two ways for folks stateside to send a special treat to troops in combat areas. The first is by purchasing The Freedom Cake, which features a layer of chocolate brownie covered with fudge frosting and topped with sprinkles and bittersweet chocolate shavings. For each Freedom Cake purchased, an identical cake will be sent to a warfighter overseas in the name of the cake recipient. The Freedom Cakes include cards, alongside U.S. flag imprints, to the recipients explaining that other cakes have been sent to military members in their names.Loved ones also can send cakes to their specific, special military member by choosing a cake from those listed on the Web site. Five percent of the order will be contributed to Operation: Birthday Cake. Bake Me A Wish can only accept “requested” delivery dates for these cakes. It takes approximately 10 to14 days for the baked goods to reach their destination. Anyone who would like to make a donation to Operation: Birthday Cake or ask a question can contact Bake Me A Wish.  My SoldierFor those without a sweet tooth or looking to offer more consistent support, My Soldier could be just the right flavor. By enrolling in the program, participants adopt deployed service members provided by the program and agree to send them periodic upbeat letters or e-mail messages. Care packages also can be sent but are not required. After enrolling, participants can download a My Soldier Starter Kit that contains instructions on how to begin the process as well as letter-writing guidelines. In addition to receiving a troop pen pal, participants also receive a bracelet, taking a cue from the POW bracelets popular in the 1970s as well as the yellow Live Strong bracelets. The bracelets are only available to program enrollees. More information about My Soldier and how to donate or participate is available on the Web site. Additional offerings include educational materials to encourage people to communicate with and understand the needs of troops and veterans. My Soldier also has spawned the spin-off program Hats Off to Veterans, which supports and honors veterans and their sacrifices. Newman’s Own AwardsThe Fisher House Foundation, in concert with Newman’s Own and the Military Times Media Group, is sponsoring the 2009 Newman’s Own Awards. The program awards grants to organizations with ideas to improve the quality of life for military and veterans’ families. A total of $75,000 is available. The top prize is $15,000, with the other $60,000 being distributed at the judges’ discretion. The deadline to apply is May 1, 2009, and winners will be announced in September 2009. Application guidelines and more information are available online.  The SIGNAL Connectionsstaff encourages readers to take advantage of the programs mentioned in this column and to pass along the information. In addition, if you know of a program that is helping service personnel, please let us know about it. Submit that information to SIGNAL's news editor.Homefront Help Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
