<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>March 16, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 03 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text> Digital Ethernet ChassisElectronic components sometimes have to fit in tight spaces. The DNR-6-1G six-slot HalfRACK is a portable Ethernet input/output (I/O) chassis designed to provide all the features of a 12-slot model in a half-rack configuration. The DNR-6 features more than 30 I/O modules that can be configured to meet a range of requirements. For more information, visit www.ueidaq.com.Disaster Recovery SoftwareThe ability to recover data after a server crash or fire is critical for businesses and government agencies. The Point-Click Recovery software for Microsoft servers protects data through encryption and tamper-proof mechanisms. A point-and-click feature allows rapid data recovery for e-mail and other data in Microsoft Exchange, SQL and Windows servers. For more information, contact www.sonasoft.com. Handheld ReceiverThis lightweight palm-size receiver is designed for use in a range of applications, including confidence monitoring and security surveillance. The RFX-PRX-II coded orthogonal frequency division multiplexing monitor/receiver is equipped with a replaceable flash memory card and a 5.6-inch screen. The device is available in the 2-gigahertz, 5.8-gigahertz and 6.4-gigahertz bands. For more information, visit www.rfcentral.com.Tactical Weather StationUnmanned aerial systems (UAS) require good weather data to support operations. The TACMET II tactical weather station is a  portable system designed to provide UAS groundstations with real-time surface weather data. The system uses little power, operates on a range of AC/DC sources and uses the WeatherView and AWeather software packages for real-time display and analysis. For more information, visit www.climatronics.com.Cellular Video Modem This lightweight video modem allows users to access remote camera imagery wherever wireless access exists. The Colby Cellular Video Modem transmits live video, stereo audio and four channels of bi-directional data via any cellular system to the Internet. The data then can be accessed on any Windows personal computer with Internet access. For more information, visit http://colbysystems.com.Mobile Video Wall SystemCommand centers for warfighters and first responders rely on large video display walls to view live data feeds and obtain situational  awareness. The Rotolift Dual ELU-50RX2 is designed to lift a display out of its protective case and rotate it horizontally for automatic viewing. The second display is stored in the same case and can be mounted to the display frame to combine images or can be used separately for multiple feeds. For more information, visit www.jelcoinc.com. New Products Archives</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
