<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Chapter's Mentoring Program Encourages Students to Pursue Hard Sciences</title>
  <author>by Katie Packard</author>
  <date>April 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>200904SIGNALConnections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Stuttgart Chapter has implemented a mentoring program to reach out to area high school students and encourage the students’ interest in the hard sciences. The chapter’s goal is to increase the likelihood of students pursuing education and careers in the sciences field.Established in 2008, the mentoring program is a result of the chapter’s successful scholarship program. Tatiaunna Maldonado, chapter vice president for membership, encouraged the chapter’s board members to develop an additional program that would benefit students. To make her case, Maldonado cited success stories from scholarship recipients who majored in the sciences in college and went on to pursue science-related careers.Col. Michelle M. Fraley, USA, chapter president, liked the idea. “We are always looking for ideas on how to make a stronger impact in the community that extends beyond the [U.S. Defense Department and the military],” she shares.The program focuses on students at PatchAmericanHigh School, the local Department of Defense Education Activity school. Chapter members provide 30-minute lessons on information technology and science-related technologies to educate students on the value of science and technology and to increase awareness of careers within those fields.“Our goal is to encourage students to consider a hard-sciences college education in the hopes that they can join our ranks in the future,” Col. Fraley says.Mentors include personnel from the military, the Defense Department and industry. For now, the mentoring program is offered only at Patch American. The chapter is looking forward to expanding the program in the future as best practices are developed.The chapter also offers VIP tours during its winter and summer technology expositions. Small groups of high school students receive brief, audience-specific presentations from vendor representatives during the exposition.Learn more about the Stuttgart Chapter’s scholarships and expositions on its Web site. Visit Member Services' Region and Chapter Information page to read about other noteworthy chapter events.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
