<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>April 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>200904SIGNALConnections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>High-Speed ModemModern warfighters need high-bandwidth communications to manage their battlefield connectivity requirements. The RC-50 is a high-frequency modem for the Codan 2110M military manpack radio. With a speed of 9,600 bits per second, the device allows the high-speed transmission of e-mail, imagery and other applications over busy and operationally challenged high-frequency networks. For more information, contact www.codan.com.au. Mobile SATCOM TerminalDesigned for both land and maritime platforms, this stabilized satellite communications (SATCOM) terminal enables units to conduct on-the-move communications. The SATCOM on-the-move terminal can access most Ku-band satellites for broadband communications at speeds up to 10 megabits per second. For more information, contact www.swe-dish.com.Extender ModulesConnecting office and command center networks sometimes requires specialized equipment. The Universal Serial Bus (USB) EXT130  line of extender modules connects with Cat-5 or Cat-6 cables that greatly extend the distances high definition multimedia interface (HDMI), digital video interface (DVI), video graphics array (VGA) and USB signals can be sent. The extenders allow USB signals to travel up to 130 feet, HDMI and DVI signals to 150 feet and VGA signals to 160 feet. For more information, visit www.cyberresearch.com.Rugged Laptop Staying connected in harsh environments is a must for warfighters and road warriors. The Durabook D15RP laptop computer meets U.S. military drop/shock/spill standards. It features a 15.5-inch liquid crystal display screen, three Universal Serial Bus 2.0 ports, an IEEE 1394 port, one Type II Express Card slot and an RS232 serial port. Optional features include encrypted hard drives, a smart card reader and 3G card support. For more information, visit www.durabook.com.Digital Multimeter  This device allows electricians and electronics specialists to perform a series of sophisticated electrical tests. The Fluke 289 Industrial Trending Digital Multimeter can record events taking place in a circuit over time, and collected data can be downloaded onto a personal computer, where it can be converted into charts and graphs. For more information, visit www.fluke.com.BlackBerry Armor Busy professionals need their personal electronic devices to work despite the occasional bump or jolt. This case is designed to protect the BlackBerry Curve 8350i against damage from drops, dirt and scratches. The case consists of a high-impact polycarbonate shell, a silicone skin to absorb bumps and shocks, a clear PVC membrane protecting the keypad from dirt and dust, and a built-in window to protect the screen and camera. For more information, visit www.otterbox.com. New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
