<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>News Briefs</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>April 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>200904SIGNALConnections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>New Satellite Support for Unmanned VehiclesCommercial satellite support for U.S. military forces in the Middle East and Asia is being boosted by an Intelsat orbiter that is being moved halfway around the world to cover the region. The international satellite consortium, responding to a U.S. Defense Department request in February, is repositioning its Galaxy 26 U.S. domestic satellite from its 93°W slot over the Western Hemisphere to a new location over the Indian Ocean. The Galaxy 26 orbiter will provide vital bandwidth for unmanned aerial vehicles conducting surveillance operations throughout its area of coverage, which ranges from Germany to Southeast Asia. The Defense Department awarded a contract to Intelsat via Artel Incorporated as part of its Defense Information Systems Network Satellite Transmission Services–Global (DSTS-G) contract.Venue Enables FCS Teamwork An innovative environment will support a virtual collaborative zone within the U.S. Army’s Future Combat Systems (FCS) program. The FCS Advanced Collaborative Environment (FCS ACE) is a secure Web environment that enables government and industry participants to work together and access product, technical and program management information. A $4.3 million contract win allows Alion Science and Technology to help streamline and improve business processes and control investment costs for FCS ACE’s entire life cycle. Airborne Robot Command and ControlThe Boeing Company and the Australian government demonstrated the ability to simultaneously command and control three robot aircraft from an airborne command platform. The demonstration featured three ScanEagle unmanned aircraft systems (UAS) controlled from a Royal Australian Air Force Wedgetail 737 airborne early warning and control aircraft. Operating 120 miles from the Wedgetail, the ScanEagles were assigned tasks such as area search, reconnaissance, point surveillance and targeting. The aircraft demonstrated extended sensing; persistent intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance; and the transmission of real-time video imagery of ground targets. Small Business to Receive Big BoostThe U.S. Air Force is redoubling its efforts to reach out to small businesses. David Van Buren, principal deputy assistant secretary of the Air Force for acquisition, and Ronald Poussard, director of the service’s small business programs, explain that this effort seeks to remove the “check-the-box” mentality often associated with small business outreach. Innovation, agility, responsiveness and efficiency are some of the attributes small companies offer, but Van Buren also says, “We don’t have enough competition now. Growing these innovative small businesses will help us rectify that by increasing the industrial base.” The service plans to enhance its relationship with small businesses by helping them move into the more mature states of development and production.Air Force Announces Preferred Location for CommandU.S. Air Force officials named Barksdale Air Force Base as the preferred alternative for the location of the Air Force Global Strike Command (AFGSC) headquarters. The AFGSC is a new major command focused on the nuclear and global strike mission. A final decision about the permanent headquarters location is expected this summer and will be made after the environmental impact analysis process required by law is complete. The selection of Barksdale was based on the base’s ability to provide nuclear mission synergy as well as its facilities and infrastructure, support capacity, transportation and access, communications and bandwidth, and security capabilities. Green UAVs Quietly Fly ForwardIon Tiger, an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) research program at the Naval Research Laboratory, is merging UAV technology and fuel cell systems that are more efficient and reduce noise. An Office of Naval Research-sponsored program, the Ion Tiger UAV tests a hydrogen-powered fuel cell design that has more endurance in flight distance and payload weight than battery-powered designs. The UAV also features a low heat signature and no emissions. Still in the testing phases, the aircraft’s flight trial this spring is expected to deliver results that exceed the duration of previous flights sevenfold: 24 hours with a five-pound payload.Army Fields Advanced Night Vision The U.S. Army Program Executive Office Soldier delivered 300 sets of the AN/PSQ-20 Enhanced Night Vision Goggles (ENVG) to the 10th Mountain Division, the first unit other than special forces to receive them. The ENVG incorporates image intensification and long-wave infrared sensors into a single integrated system. It has a thermal camera that increases mobility and situational awareness regardless of light, weather or battlefield conditions, and it offers faster threat recognition. The ENVG’s compatibility with current aiming lasers enables a fully integrated system of thermal, laser and image intensification. A digital update for the ENVG is in development. With that, soldiers will be able to import and export digital files.Tag-Team Approach Lengthens Raven Flight TimeU.S. Army and industry representatives have demonstrated that a team of RQ-11B Raven small unmanned aircraft can remain in flight for 30 hours. Using one system, which comprises three aircraft and two ground control stations, the demonstration proved that surveillance of an area could be maintained using two-person crews operating in eight-hour shifts. In addition to recording imagery, the aircraft streamed real-time video from the operation via webcast throughout the demonstration. This duration illustrates that the aircraft could provide prolonged tactical-level surveillance similar to troops at the battalion and below level.Communication Connections Head for the FieldNATO forces soon will deploy a new communications system that enables field headquarters to connect to other NATO forces. The NATO Deployable Communication and Information System (DCIS) is designed to support NATO Response Forces by allowing them to deploy up to 20 users or as many as 150 users in a field communications headquarters with voice or datalinks to other units. Manufactured by the EADS Group, the DCIS will become a key capability that will allow NATO signals battalions to support deployment into operational theaters. Latest Military e-Learning Standard ReleasedThe U.S Defense Department has issued the 4th edition of its Web-based e-learning standard, which allows government, commercial and international agencies to exchange online training, learning and educational content. Referred to as the Advanced Distributed Learning Sharable Content Object Reference Model (SCORM), the standard ensures consistent experience and performance data tracking of training courses taken online and allows collaboration among users. The newest version corrects previous system defects, adds enhancements that were a direct result of community collaboration and increases SCORM's interoperability across learning management systems.  News Briefs Archives </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
