<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Navy Blue Coast Conference Focuses on Small Business Opportunities</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>April 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>200904SIGNALConnections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Department of the Navy Office of Small Business Programs and AFCEA International will host a three-day educational outreach conference for small businesses May 12 to 14, 2009, at the Virginia BeachConvention Center. The Navy Blue Coast Small Business Training and Opportunities Conference, “Aligning Your Business with Tomorrow’s Navy,” aims at providing insights to small businesses and offering the Department of the Navy, AFCEA and its corporate members the opportunity to learn from one another.Although the focus of the Navy Blue Coast Conference is outreach and education, the event also offers adequate time for developing business relationships through networking. In addition to Navy command briefings, subject matter experts will share their views in plenary and panel sessions. Offerings are included for all experience levels—from novice to seasoned business professionals. The conference culminates in a matchmaking event where small businesses can discuss their capabilities with representatives from both government agencies and large prime contractors. Now in its third year, this East Coast complement to the Navy’s long-running Gold Coast Conference is not a stand-alone offering but rather a conference within a conference. The event is co-located with the AFCEA/USNI Joint Warfighting Conference. This inclusive format allows small businesses the opportunity to maximize their time by attending training sessions while participating in a broader conference and exhibition as well. BlueCoast attendees can take part in luncheons, keynote addresses and receptions with Joint Warfighting Conference participants. They are able to hear firsthand from key government leaders and mingle with all levels of industry.Small businesses often offer the most agile and innovative solutions to assist the federal government in fulfilling its mission. Given the voluminous and rapidly changing roster of small companies, uncovering the best solutions is a significant and recurring challenge for the government. Once companies are identified, the government also strives to facilitate the process of doing business in the federal market though educational efforts.The Department of the Navy embraces a culture that recognizes the critical role of small businesses in supporting its objective of “Building the Navy–Marine Corps Force for Tomorrow.” The department has a decentralized procurement structure that purchased approximately $93 billion in goods and services during fiscal year 2008. Each of the department’s contracting commands is responsible for acquiring the goods and services to fulfill its mission to support the Department of the Navy at sea, in the air and on land. The Navy has 11 major contracting commands, each with an associate director for small business programs that serves as the point of contact for small business procurement opportunities. Representatives from each of these commands are scheduled to attend the conference and participate in the matchmaking sessions. Department of the Navy speakers also include Rear Adm. Robert D. Reilly Jr., USN, commander, Military Sealift Command; and Timothy Foreman, director, Department of the Navy Office of Small Business Programs.Small business owners, business development professionals, large business liaison officers for small business, Historically Black Colleges and Universities and Minority Institutions, and established companies with an interest in pursuing business with the Navy and other federal government customers are encouraged to attend the conference. There is a special early registration fee available through April 30, 2009. Details and registration are available online. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
