<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>May 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 05 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Installation Kit Technicians need top-notch tools to help them set up communications systems. The Noyes Pro Installer kit is an installation and test kit featuring a variety of fiber optic testing, cleaning and installation equipment, allowing users to verify the integrity of installed fiber networks. The kit consists of an optical time domain reflectometer with an integrated visual fault locator, optical power meter, an optical light source and a fiber connector inspection scope. For more information, visit www.afltele.com.LED FlashlightA reliable personal light source is priceless when the chips are down and the lights go out. The 2360 LED  flashlight is powered by two AA batteries and can run up to 2.5 hours. The light also features a multiposition, removable black oxide coated metal clip. For more information, visit www.pelican.com.Voice Touchpanel This rack-mounted voice communications touchpanel is designed to support intercom functions in broadcast, defense, industrial and commercial applications. The TCP-401 VCOM touchpanel features a 7-inch touch screen with a graphic user interface that supports hundreds of channels that are configurable for point-to-point calls, group calls and party lines. For more information, visit www.intracomsystems.com.Cargo Tracking SystemMonitoring the status of cargo in shipping containers is vital for both retailers and governments. The SaviTrak wireless tracking cargo device attaches to container doors and receives Global Positioning System data. Sensors embedded in the tag detect and record security breaches of the container doors as well as changes of temperature, light and humidity within the container. The device then transmits the data via radio frequency identification or global system mobile cellular networks using general packet radio system signals. For more information, visit www.savinetworks.com.Mini Computer Designed for high-power computing in small spaces, this series of miniature computers can support thin client and mobile applications. The MEPC series of computers are encased in an aluminum case and feature 1.2. gigahertz VIA Esther central processing units. A wireless local area network is optional for all versions. For more information, visit www.cyberresearch.com.Power ConverterKeeping communications equipment and other electronics running and powered is a vital mission for robust  equipment. The C/B5800 series of 12,000 watt DC/DC converters, AC/DC power supply and battery-charging devices can be rack- and wall-mounted. The converters are designed to support communications systems, military applications, transportation, alternative energy systems and process control systems. For more information, visit www.schaeferpower.com. New Products Archives</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
