<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>June 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 06 Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Solar-Powered Area LightLighting is vital for security and work purposes at military and corporate installations. Designed for street and parking lot applications, the EverGEN 1500 solar-powered area light provides high light output with the advantage of a stand-alone power source. The light uses light-emitting diodes to deliver up to 6,800 lumens of illumination. For more information, visit www.carmanahlighting.com.Multipurpose Printer This series of color laser printers provide fast, high-quality color printing, copying, faxing and scanning. The Lexmark X730 and C730 series allow users to convert hard copy to digital documents quickly. For more information, visit www.lexmark.com.Rugged Mobile RouterDesigned for installation on military and civil vehicle and aircraft platforms, this rugged mobile router  subsystem is based on Cisco Systems’ 3230 mobile access router technology. The DuraMAR 3230 features sealed military standard-compliant connectors for a Cisco internetwork operating system (IOS)-managed 10/100 wide area network port, three IOS-managed 10/100 switch ports, 13 10/100/1000 Gigabit Ethernet switch ports, two multiprotocol serial ports and an RS-232 management console port. The unit also is equipped with a data zeroization button for enhanced security and a conductively cooled chassis with an almost cable-less internal design for reliability under high mechanical stress. For more information, visit www.parvus.com.Application SoftwareDeveloping and deploying business applications can be challenging without the right software platform. Release 4 of the 4D v11 SQL integrated software platform features new commands and parameters to provide increased control over vector graphics and illustrations. The software also includes enhanced security features for Windows to ensure that 4D applications can be installed without configuration changes. For more information, visit www.4d.com. Multi-Image Display Processor Managing multiple video images requires dedicated, powerful equipment. The VN-Quantum Connect is a multi-image display processor designed to integrate and scale multiple video and graphic images onto single or multiple displays. It is a dedicated video processor that can size and place up to 128 windows across multiple displays. For more information, visit www.electrosonic.com.Digital MultimeterEngineered for industrial technicians, the Fluke 289 Industrial Trending Digital Multimeter features automatic safety features such as  ghost voltage detection, enhanced logging with better display for troubleshooting, filters for variable frequency drive output readings and on-screen help. The device also includes capabilities such as saving, recording and trend capture, low pass filter and an information button to provide immediate manual references. For more information, visit www.fluke.com. New Products Archives</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
