<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Homefront Help</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>July 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 07 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Homefront Help is SIGNAL Connections’ effort to support U.S. service members, veterans and their families. The column highlights programs that offer resources and assistance to the military community ranging from care packages to benefits and everything in between. In that same spirit, Homefront Help presents opportunities for readers to donate time, offer resources and send words of thanks to those who sacrifice for freedom. Programs that provide services are listed in red. Opportunities for the public to reach out to service members are listed in blue. Each program description includes a link to the organization's Web site, when available.Operation Send-OffYou say goodbye or you say hello. Or both. Operation Send-Off is dedicated to ensuring that troops leaving for or returning from deployment have the proper send-off and an honorable welcome home. It currently operates at the Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport with plans to expand to Hartsfield-JacksonInternationalAirport. The idea was conceived to exhibit appreciation and support to offset the presence of protesters. The nonprofit group also sends care packages to warfighters overseas and is developing a mobile canteen to visit military bases throughout the world. As part of its efforts, the organization supports and comforts military family members as well. Volunteers are critical for the success of Operation Send-Off’s efforts, and help is needed in several areas such as package preparation, fundraising, administrative duties, general nonprofit support and, of course, seeing troops off and cheering their return. Donations also are greatly appreciated since the organization has very limited funds. Stephen Butler, the media relations contact for the organization, who also served in the Marine Corps and is an active volunteer, says the money the organization receives is spent quickly to buy drinks and other items for the troops once they pass through security. Butler brings his seeing-eye dog Sgt. Maj. Blaze with him to his airport visits and has found that the pooch draws attention from even the shyest soldiers, who then talk about their canines. Blaze also serves as a comfort to children who have said goodbye to a parent. Children can e-mail Blaze at blaze@operationsendoff.org and will receive a response. Anyone interested in volunteering can request more information by e-mailing volunteers@operationsendoff.org. Those interested in scheduling a group to go to the Dallas airport should e-mail operations@operationsendoff.org. People in other locations who want to support similar activities can e-mail Butler at Stephen.Butler@operationsendoff.org. Additional contact information and resources are available online, including links to other military support groups and photographs. Wounded Soldiers Wish FoundationThis fledgling organization falls under the established A Million Thanks program, taking the idea of showing gratitude to troops to a new level. The purpose of Wounded Soldiers Wish is to grant the wishes of warfighters injured in the Global War on Terrorism, similar to how the Make A Wish children’s charity functions. Troops hurt in battle are suffering from a variety of wounds, including lost sight, limbs and hearing, and Wounded Soldiers Wish wants to provide them what they need through donations from those who want to thank them for their service. The foundation is in the final stages, with a Web site under construction, but already it has received wishes from wounded troops who heard about the project. Unfortunately, the organization currently lacks the funds to meet these requests, so the group is asking those who would like to fulfill immediate needs to donate money or to consider coordinating future fundraising events. Anyone interested in the latter should e-mail aMillionThanks@aol.com. A link for donations is available on the A Million Thanks Web site. Real Warriors CampaignThe Real Warriors Campaign combats the stigma associated with psychological health care and treatment. By increasing awareness and use of resources, the group is encouraging troops to obtain the services they need. The Defense Centers of Excellence (DCoE) for Psychological Health and Traumatic Brain Injury launched the Real Warriors Campaign to promote the process of building resilience, facilitating recovery, and supporting reintegration of returning service members, veterans and their families into everyday life.To spread the word about the importance and availability of mental health services, the campaign performs outreach using print materials, the media, an interactive Web site, social media and partnerships. Real Warriors features stories about actual troops who have sought treatment and continue to maintain successful military and civilian careers. In addition, the DCoE created a 24/7 OutreachCenter staffed by health resources consultants who offer confidential information about psychological health and traumatic brain injury. The center can be reached at (866) 966-1020 or at resources@dcoeoutreach.org. A live chat option is available on the Web site as is the number for the suicide prevention hotline. Additional Web site options include a list of partners, a sign-up for e-mail updates as well as detailed lists of resources for active duty, Guard and Reserve, families, veterans and health care providers. The SIGNAL Connections staff encourages readers to take advantage of the programs mentioned in this column and to pass along the information. In addition, if you know of a program that is helping service personnel, please let us know about it. Submit that information to SIGNAL's news editor.Homefront Help Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
