<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>July 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 07 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Web Site Monitoring ServiceKeeping track of Web sites that are running interactive applications can be challenging for administrators. Transaction Perspective 9.0 is a site monitoring service that features support for interactive Flash and Silverlight, composite Web transactions and third-party online ad tracking. The latest version of the service also includes a new end user portal, an overview dashboard and access to real-time tests. For more information, visit www.keynote.com.Flexible Mold Power and Thermocouple Cables This line of flexible mold power and thermocouple cables for injection molders can be used in a range of applications such as sensors and temperature/process controllers. The cables are available in 10- to 20-inch lengths and are produced through an extrusion/corrugation process to create a seamless, corrugated nylon tube. For more information, visit www.athenacontrols.com.Web Service Telephony UtilityManaging computer and voice over Internet connections can become time consuming without the right tools. M5Connect is a Web services application program interface utility that allows both personal computer and Web-based applications to interact with the M5 phone system. The software allows users to click-to-dial and enables automatic screen pop-ups providing call data and contact information for incoming calls. For more information, visit www.dataritesys.com.Rugged Digital Camera Designed for use by special forces, military and law enforcement personnel, this rugged digital camera includes remote and autonomous capabilities such as wireless data transmission over tens of kilometers and wired transmission without detectable radio frequency signatures. The FrogEye camera supports a variety of image sensors, including electron multiplier charge-coupled device (CCD) night vision systems. A 14-megapixel sensor is available for autonomous observation of large buildings and areas in high detail. For more information, visit www.desertstar.com.Enterprise Archiving SoftwareLarge enterprise systems have the potential to make complex tasks more difficult due to the sheer size and variety of the network. NearPoint 4.0 is designed to help expedite archiving, discovery and preservation of electronically stored information. The software supports multiple data capture methods and provides case management and workflow tools to support legal and compliance teams. For more information, visit www.mimosasystems.com.Liquid Tight Tubing Fabricated for use in high vibration or flexing applications, this line of fittings and tubing is designed to provide permanent assembly between fittings and tubing. Heyco-Flex III tubing is made of halogen-free nylon 6, is flame retardant and can be used in very tight quarters. For more information, visit www.heyco.com.New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
