<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Homefront Help</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>August 17, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 08 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Homefront Help is SIGNAL Connections’ effort to support U.S. service members, veterans and their families. The column highlights programs that offer resources and assistance to the military community ranging from care packages to benefits and everything in between. In that same spirit, Homefront Help presents opportunities for readers to donate time, offer resources and send words of thanks to those who sacrifice for freedom. Programs that provide services are listed in red. Opportunities for the public to reach out to service members are listed in blue. Each program description includes a link to the organization's Web site, when available.Operation Bacon SaltAs this column has shown—and said—many times before, there is no limit to how people with a passion can support the troops. The gentlemen behind Operation Bacon Salt have a passion for, well, bacon, and conceived the idea for the outreach program when a U.S. Marine corporal e-mailed them detailing a horrible condition they felt no person should have to endure: life without bacon. Since the initial shipment to that group of Marines in Iraq, Operation Bacon Salt has sent its goods to other service members in places where fresh bacon is hard to come by such as Iraq, Afghanistan, aircraft carriers and Apache helicopters because everything really is better with bacon. Bacon Salt is a meat-free seasoning that is designed to impart bacon flavor to any food item. It comes in several varieties and because it is a dry mix does not require special storage conditions. While the Bacon Salt organization currently lacks the resources to send its product to all troops stationed overseas, it plans to sponsor one group of soldiers a month until they all come home. Anyone interested in receiving or sponsoring a shipment can send an e-mail to supportthetroops@baconsalt.com. People stationed overseas who have military addresses or those sending the packages overseas to military addresses can use the coupon code “baconsaltfortroops” to get a 50 percent discount of anything purchased from the company. The Web site includes the e-mail that started it all as well as the thank you after the Bacon Salt arrived. Also posted are links to the story of the company’s conception and to items for purchase, but the real treasures on the site are the photos of troops enjoying their bacon-flavored goodness. After all, according to the people behind Operation Bacon Salt, “We thought we’d put up this Web site as a reminder that there are people out there who are putting their lives on the line far away from home who could use your support.”Warmth For WarriorsThis outreach effort also aims at providing the comforts of home by sending troops and veterans warm wool hats and other items made with love. The headwear provides physical comfort and a "hug of thanks." Volunteers knit and crochet hats and send them to medical units where ill and wounded military members prepare to leave for hospitals in Germany or the United States. As of July 1, 2009, the nonprofit had sent 3,569 fuzzy head coverings to those sacrificing for freedom.As an all-volunteer organization, Warmth for Warriors always is appreciative of monetary donations or completed hats. The Web site includes a file to download with instructions for easy hats as well as recommendations for the types of wool to use. Contact information, including a mailing address for completed caps or funds, also is posted online. G.I. Bill Transfers AuthorizedAs of August 1, 2009, military members enrolled in the Post-9/11 G.I. Bill program can transfer unused educational benefits to their spouses or children. The Defense Department released guidance on June 23, 2009, establishing the criteria for eligibility and transfer of the benefits. Information about the criteria, transferability, how to apply and more is available on the G.I. Bill Web site. Other information and resources can be found at the Defense Department site.  The SIGNAL Connections staff encourages readers to take advantage of the programs mentioned in this column and to pass along the information. In addition, if you know of a program that is helping service personnel, please let us know about it. Submit that information to SIGNAL's news editor.Homefront Help Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
