<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>August 17, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 08 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Satellite Communications/Search and Rescue System Military personnel and first responders often work in isolated areas where satellite links are the only reliable means of communications. The HOOK2 GPS (Global Positioning System) combat search and rescue (CSAR) system consists of a software-defined, upgradeable AN/PRC-112G transceiver or an AN/PRC-112B1 transceiver, and a handheld GPS Quickdraw2 interrogator. The system provides two-way messaging and GPS positioning for accurate location data. The Quickdraw interrogator also can turn most aircraft into a CSAR platform by plugging the device into the aircraft’s intercom system. For more information, visit www.gdc4s.com.E-mail System ProtectionSpam and e-mail threats can shut down an unprotected government organization’s information technology resources. E-mail System Protection 365 (ESP 365) features message journaling that can integrate with third-party archiving and e-discovery systems, advanced cluster management, and option auto-accept for incoming compliant list/news group messages, and it offers an enhanced queue summary. For more information, contact www.sendio.com.Memory Card Cracker/Reader Law enforcement agencies and military units often have difficulty trying to open confiscated or captured personal identification number (PIN)-locked flash memory devices. Crowbar is a portable, handheld device designed for tactical field operations that can determine if a memory card is PIN-locked, corrupt or damaged. The device can crack PIN codes, create forensic images of unlocked cards for further analysis and serve as a write-blocked card reader for unlocked cards. For more information, visit http://cybersolutions.mantech.com.Kilowatt Hour Transducers Designed for use with HOBO data loggers, this family of kilowatt hour transducers measures 1-, 2- or 3-phase power in 2-, 3- or 4-wire configurations. The transducers connect directly to Web-based HOBO U30 monitoring systems and stand-alone HOBO Energy Logger Pro data loggers and can be installed in service panels and junction boxes. For more information, visit www.onsetcomp.com.Speech-Enabled WarehousingStoring supplies and equipment can lead to errors without an accurate data collection system. The Gemini Voice system enables hands-free picking and putaway of items to enhance productivity and accuracy in material-handling operations. The system integrates with Oracle data storage applications, can support more than 36 languages and can filter out background noise to enhance data capture. For more information, visit www.takesupplychain.com.Cybersecurity ToolsMaintaining network security and real-time situational awareness in today’s high-threat environment can be challenging for system administrators. The Qosmos Network Intelligence (NI) software identifies and extracts information traveling across Internet protocol networks in real time. The software’s tools classify protocols and applications, generate metadata for all sessions, and extract content. The NI tools also selectively perform reassembly, manage duplicated and de-sequenced packets, and enable correlation of any activity between all network layers. For more information, visit www.qosmos.com. New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
