<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Be Rewarded for Sharing Your Insights</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>September 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 09 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Two contests currently are underway that enable everyone interested in the intelligence profession to share their ideas and win cash prizes plus memberships in the essential professional organizations. AFCEA International and Naval Intelligence Professionals (NIP)/Naval Intelligence Foundation are sponsoring the competitions.The 2009 AFCEA Intelligence Essay Contest topic is “Collecting Intelligence: Balancing Safety, Security and Privacy.” Writers must discuss the implications of the new and different methods of collecting intelligence that are being used to forestall future terrorist attacks. Essayists must take a position on the topic, develop the position logically and make recommendations for government action. The minimum essay word count is 1,500; the maximum is 3,000. Entries can include photographs and must be received via e-mail by October 31, 2009. Additional rules for entry are available on the AFCEA Intelligence Department Web site.First prize for the AFCEA contest is $2,000 and a two-year AFCEA membership; second prize is $1,000 and a two-year AFCEA membership; and third prize is $500 and a one-year AFCEA membership. Essays also may be published in SIGNAL Magazine, SIGNAL Scape, AFCEA’s intelligence department Web site and/or the NIP Quarterly. Winners will be notified no later than January 15, 2010.The NIP is offering another opportunity to write and win by writing about any subject pertaining to naval intelligence or intelligence support to naval forces. The first-place prize is $1,000, a five-year membership in the foundation and a two-year membership in AFCEA. The second-place winner will receive $500 and one-year memberships in both the foundation and AFCEA. Once again, these essays also may be published in SIGNAL Magazine, SIGNAL Scape, AFCEA’s intelligence department Web site and/or the NIP Quarterly.Entries for the foundation’s contest can be no more than 2,000 words and must be submitted via e-mail. Photographs also can be submitted to complement the essay. The deadline for submitting material is November 1, 2009, and winners will be notified by January 15, 2010. Additional information about entering the Naval Intelligence Professionals contest is available on its Web site. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
