<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>September 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>2009 09 SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Processor Blade State-of-the-art telecommunications equipment requires powerful and flexible components to process data and video streams. The ATC6239 is a Dual Opteron Socket-F (1207) processor board design that can support Hex-Core 2.1 gigahertz (Istanbul) or Quad-Core 2.4 gigahertz (Shanghai) processors, each with a 512 kilobyte L2 cache per core and 6 megabytes of shared L3 cache. The base design can include up to 32 gigabytes of memory and utilizes a high-speed hyper transport link to connect with the Broadcom HT2100 and HT1000 server class chipset. For more information, visit www.diversifiedtechnology.com.Debugging SoftwareChecking device and application software for bugs can be a complex, time-consuming task. Green Hills Probe is a microprocessor debugging tool that allows software developers to perform board bring-up, device driver development and other system debugging tasks efficiently. The tool provides a seamless debugging experience by offering synchronized multicore run control, inter-core cache coherency features and intelligent inter-core breakpoint management. For more information, contact www.ghs.com.Airborne Datalink Datalinks for unmanned aerial systems (UAS) must balance performance with size and weight savings. The C-band Starlink digital datalink is designed to transmit airborne video images in real time to commanders in the field while being resistant to jamming and radio frequency interference. The datalink can operate at distances up to 100 kilometers. For more information, contact www.elisra.com.Flash Drive Administration ToolsThis family of products is designed to help systems administrators manage and secure flash drives. The Kanguru Administrator Tool allows personnel to configure the Kanguru Defender and Kanguru Bio AES secure, encrypted flash drives to comply with security policies. Available in two options, the Administrator Tool can be used either in conjunction with the Kanguru Remote Management Console or as a stand-alone application. For more information, visit www.kanguru.com.Software EditorDesigned to edit software written in the S1000D specification, the S1000DauthorPro XE browser-based what-you-see-is-what-you-get (WYSIWYG) editor can be integrated into existing S1000D publishing suites. The editor allows coders to quickly create and edit content to facilitate browser-based authoring. For more information, visit www.inmedius.com.Broadband Satellite RouterFirst responders and warfighters require robust links for mobile communications. The HX280 is a broadband satellite router designed to provide carrier-grade Internet protocol services with enhanced security and on-the-move capabilities. The router has integrated Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS) 140-2 cryptographic security and also supports the newly released HX System Enhanced Signaling Security feature, which protects all data, management and signaling traffic over a satellite network. For more information, visit www.hughes.com.  New Products Archive</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
