<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Homefront Help</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>October 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Homefront Help is SIGNAL Connections’ effort to support U.S. service members, veterans and their families. The column highlights programs that offer resources and assistance to the military community ranging from care packages to benefits and everything in between. In that same spirit, Homefront Help presents opportunities for readers to donate time, offer resources and send words of thanks to those who sacrifice for freedom. Programs that provide services are listed in red. Opportunities for the public to reach out to service members are listed in blue. Each program description includes a link to the organization's Web site, when available.American Freedom FestivalThe American Freedom Foundation will host the 2009 American Freedom Festival November 7 at 7:30 p.m. at the Patriot Center in Fairfax, Virginia. The event is a tribute to veterans to honor them and to recognize the sacrifices members of the armed forces make every day. It raises money and awareness for veterans and their families whose lives have been affected by operations Enduring Freedom and Iraqi Freedom. The 12th Sergeant Major of the Army, Sgt. Maj. Jack Tilley, USA (Ret.), is a co-chair of the festival.Several big-name musical acts such as Montgomery Gentry, LeAnn Womack and Phil Vassar are scheduled to perform at the event. Tickets can be ordered through the foundation’s Web site. Event sponsorships also are available, ranging from the In-Kind Sponsorship that costs less than $2,500 up to the Presenting Sponsorships, which start at $100,000. Each level comes with its own set of benefits, including tickets, advertisements and commemorative gifts. The American Freedom Foundation raises money and awareness for various veterans' organizations. It places special emphasis on welfare and education issues facing veterans who were wounded in action and families of veterans killed in action during operations Enduring Freedom and Iraqi Freedom.Operation Healing AngelOperation Healing Angel needs cards—LOTS of cards. The group takes the mail it receives for any wounded hero and puts it in the hands of recovering troops and the service member doctors and nurses who care for them. The organization just expanded its effort to the largest combat hospital in Iraq and already covers the LandstuhlRegionalMedicalCenter in Germany, TriplerArmyMedicalCenter in Hawaii and the JamesV.HaleyVeteransAffairsMedicalCenter in Florida. Donors can designate which facility they would like to support.Operation Healing Hands asks that people make their cards personal and add photos when possible to give each message an individual touch. Laminated items last longer, and the group recommends it as a great idea for groups of children who want to participate. Operation Healing Angel also seeks items for care packages and sells special patriotic rubber ducks that people can donate to wounded warfighters. Information about donations and how to send in photos for the Web site, thank-you messages and much more is available online.Donations can be sent to:Operation Healing Angel1449 Tiger Lake DriveGulf Breeze, Florida32563Operation ShowerDelivering entire baby showers in one package, this organization provides presents and fun to pregnant women with deployed spouses or in other stressful military situations. The group puts together showers-in-a-box for the expectant mommies, and Operation Shower Teams deliver them during unit-wide showers to show appreciation to military spouses. The events give the mothers a chance to gather with other moms in their unit and celebrate the babies on the way. Anyone who wants to contribute to the effort can donate money or new goods for moms and babies, become a sponsor or join with a group to gather donations.  The SIGNAL Connectionsstaff encourages readers to take advantage of the programs mentioned in this column and to pass along the information. In addition, if you know of a program that is helping service personnel, please let us know about it. Submit that information to SIGNAL's news editor. The SIGNAL Connections staff has made every effort to verify the legitimacy of these programs and to include information accurate at the time of publication. Inclusion in this column does not constitute an endorsement by AFCEA International or SIGNAL Connections.   </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
