<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>October 15, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>GPS Asset Tracker Keeping track of supplies and equipment during commercial or military operations can be a challenge. The TRAX MT-13 compact Global Positioning System asset tracker is a rugged device designed to wirelessly track lightweight to medium-weight equipment. In addition to tracking and tracing equipment, the MT-13 can be programmed over the air and can perform functions such as geo-fencing. For more information, visit www.moreycorp.com.Handheld Thermal ImagersThese two lightweight thermal cameras are designed to meet homeland security and surveillance requirements. The Sophie ZS and Sophie XF cameras feature a continuous optical zoom with image stabilization and autofocus. The cameras can provide smooth image ranging from wide to narrow fields of view. The Sophie ZS is dedicated to long-range surveillance via an optical zoom, while the Sophie XF is designed for long-range target location and surveillance. For more information, contact www.thalesgroup.com.Conference Calling and Planning SoftwareTight economic times are forcing more organizations to opt for conference calls over expensive business travel. The latest version of Infostreet’s Calendar application now integrates a conference calling application. When users plan a meeting or send a meeting request or invitation, the software automatically generates and embeds a unique conference number and caller identification in the invitation. For more information, contact www.infostreet.com.Rugged Smartphone Case First responders and business professionals sometimes need to carry nonruggedized personal communications equipment into rough areas. The i1015 case is designed to protect iPhones, iPod touch and smartphones from damage caused by falls, moisture and dust. The case features a clear lid that allows users to read e-mail and text messages or watch video while protecting the device. An external headphone jack enables users to listen to music or voice communications while the case is closed. For more information, visit www.pelican.com.Voltage TesterMaintenance, service and safety personnel working around communications and electrical equipment must  always be careful of live or defective circuitry. The VoltAlert alternating current noncontact voltage tester is similar to a pen that can test for current by touching its tip to a terminal strip, outlet or power cord. The device’s tip will glow red if voltage is detected. For more information, visit www.fluke.com.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
