<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>November 16, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Secure File-Sharing SoftwareDesigned for secure file sharing, the GigaTribe software package allows users to share photos, videos, music and other files with GigaTribe users in a private, fully encrypted peer-to-peer environment. Only recipients selected by users can see the files and can decide whether they wish to download them. The company claims there are no files to upload, no size limitations and all transfers are encrypted. For more information, visit www.gigatribe.com. LED Power SupplyThe LD12 series of AC-DC power supplies are designed for light-emitting diode (LED) lighting and display applications with output ratings up to 12.6 watts. The series includes both constant voltage and constant current models. The devices are 12-watt AC-DC encapsulated drivers/suppliers that are designed to be splash proof and operate with universal power inputs of 90 to 265 volts/AC. For more information, visit www.us.tdk-lambda.com/lp/products/ld12-series.htm. Rugged LaptopWarfighters and first responders need reliable equipment that can operate in harsh conditions. The rugged Durabook D14RM is a slim, lightweight laptop that meet military specifications for drop, shock, spill and dust resistance. It is housed in a magnesium alloy anti-shock case that protects its hard drive and liquid crystal display from damage. For more information, visit www.gammatechusa.com/PRO/D14RM/index.html.Rugged ServerDesigned specifically for shipboard, airborne and land-based applications, this rugged three-drive server is engineered to resist  extremes of temperature, vibration and shock. The RS363SF is 13 inches deep with three removable 3.5-inch hard drives or six removable 2.5-inch drives. The server is available with either the Intel Harpertown or Intel Nehalem Xeon processor. For more information, visit www.crystalrugged.com.Gigabit Ethernet SwitchThe Duranet 1268 is a compact Layer 2+ Gigabit Ethernet switch subsystem equipped with 10 triple-speed ports for connecting Internet protocol version 4- (IPv4) and IPv6-compatible computing devices on space-constrained ground, air and sea platforms. Designed to meet MIL-STD-810F standards for ruggedness, the unit features a nearly cableless design, a fully submersible chassis and no moving parts. For more information, visit www.parvus.com/product/overview.aspx?prod=DuraNET1268.Long CasesThese two cases are designed to move long objects, from machine guns to industrial equipment. The Pelican 1740 and 1770 long cases feature 6,600 and 7,300 cubic inches of storage space respectively. Both cases contain configurable, open cell core, polymer wall construction engineered to protect sensitive equipment from harsh conditions. For more information, visit www.pelican.com.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
