<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>The Gift of IA Awareness Keeps on Giving</title>
  <author>SIGNAL Staff</author>
  <date>December 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>On Cyber Patrol</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>During the holidays, people around the world are going to receive computers, upgraded Internet access, video game consoles, MP3 players and many other gadgets and gizmos that will connect them to the wonders of the Internet. Many of these gifts will be ordered and paid for over the Internet. In addition to gift giving, there will be an upswing in charitable donations, and many will seek to spread holiday cheer via electronic means. At the same time, an international array of talented, unscrupulous and sometimes downright evil cyber criminals are gearing up to feast on this annual frenzy of online goodwill. The results won’t be pretty. </abstract>
  <text>During the holidays, people around the world are going to receive computers, upgraded Internet access, video game consoles, MP3 players and many other gadgets and gizmos that will connect them to the wonders of the Internet. Many of these gifts will be ordered and paid for over the Internet. In addition to gift giving, there will be an upswing in charitable donations, and many will seek to spread holiday cheer via electronic means. At the same time, an international array of talented, unscrupulous and sometimes downright evil cyber criminals are gearing up to feast on this annual frenzy of online goodwill. The results won’t be pretty. Online and traditional media are adding Internet dangers to their list of holiday warning stories. Unfortunately, many of the most likely victims never see those articles, videos and TV stories. They are too busy buying, donating and making new friends online. Internet access is the BB gun gift of generations ago. If you are not taught how to use it correctly, then “you could shoot your eye out.” Today, that classic threat to one’s sight comes in the form of lost money and stolen identities that are the main diet of Internet bad guys.  There is a way to make your digital gifts safer than foam rubber BBs. This season, give the gift of Information Assurance. Share with your loved ones and friends what you know about Internet dangers and how to avoid them. Pass along those articles about online safety to your digital network. If you are able, make sure that security software is part of every applicable hardware gift (making sure it is up and running earns you extra points). Teach people what makes a secure password and how to keep it safe from prying eyes. Show others how to do that neat spy stuff like encrypting data and securing storage media such as flash drives.Like goodwill, charity donations and gift giving, sharing your Internet security knowledge is a year-long need. Don’t stop helping people avoid online scams after the New Year. By constantly seeking out opportunities to educate, you will keep the joy of your digital holiday gifts in people's hearts—and the bad guys out of their bank accounts and identities. The On Cyber Patrol© cartoon and supporting articles are created and made available by the U.S. Army’s Office of Information Assurance and Compliance, NETCOM, CIO/G6. For more information on the OCP program or to submit ideas for upcoming cartoons/articles, contact oncyberpatrol@hqda.army.mil. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
