<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>February 16, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Small Satellite Data TransceiverDesigned for embedded applications such as remote asset tracking, this small satellite data transceiver permits two-way communications to and from remote devices. The matchbox-sized Iridium 9602 transceiver can be remotely reprogrammed and adjusted to provide specific data updates. For more information, visit www.iridium.com. All-Weather Enclosure and Backbone SystemCommunications and networking equipment in austere military and commercial facilities must be protected from the elements. The RuggedBackbone MX5000 is a military-standard hardened multiservice platform designed to operate across a wide temperature range and to support high-density routing and switching while being resistant to high levels of electromagnetic and radio-frequency interference. The MX500 can be housed in the RuggedEnclosure, a welded aluminum, hard-mount enclosure engineered to house networking and communications equipment and to enhance their resistance to shock, vibration, emissions, temperature and humidity. For more information, visit www.ruggedcom.com.Graphics Extension ModulesSometimes users need to link multiple monitors together to analyze or view video and graphics data. The DualHead2Go and TripleHead2Go Graphics eXpansion Modules (GXMs) can drive four to six monitors respectively from a single system or work station. The GXMs allow users to build multiple screen presentations for applications such as digital signage platforms. For more information, visit www.matrox.com.Power ConvertersThis family of direct-current-to-direct-current (DC-DC) converters are designed for use in telecommunications, networking, distributed power and process control applications. The CC-P-E Series are ultra-compact, fully isolated converters featuring a range of DC inputs (24 volts or 48 volt nominal). The converters are available with DC output voltages of 3.3 volts, 5 volts, 12 volts or 15 volts. For more information, visit http://us.tdk-lambda.com/lp/products/cc-series.htm.Portable Suitcase and Handheld ReceiversWarfighters and law enforcement personnel require connectivity even in the most remote regions. The PSRX6D Portable Suitcase Six-way and MobilCMDR handheld two-way coded orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (COFDM) diversity receivers are designed for government applications such as airborne downlinks and mobile vehicles operating in tactical and/or strategic settings. The PSRX6D can receive microwave signals from two, four or six different antennas, while the MobilCMDR can receive microwave signals from two different antennas. For more information, visit www.vitecgroup.com.Miniature Wilkinson Power DividerEngineered for use in small, lightweight consumer handheld devices, this small Wilkinson power divider measures 1 millimeter by 1 millimeter. The divider supports 2.4 and 2.5 gigahertz applications such as WiMAX, ISM, 802.11, Bluetooth, Bluetooth Low Energy and Zigbee. Designed to save space on boards, the device also is only .62 millimeters thick, allowing it to be used in very thin wireless handhelds. For more information, visit www.anaren.com. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
