<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Veterans Get Boost Into Job Market</title>
  <author>by Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>March 15, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>In an effort to help members of the military move from "boots to suits," a program will begin that helps warfighters turn in their weapons for a computer keyboard.</abstract>
  <text>In an effort to help members of the military move from “boots to suits,” a program will begin that helps warfighters turn in their weapons for a computer keyboard. The industry-led initiative includes cash and software grants to organizations that—through a request-for-proposals process—demonstrate they have the outreach and facilities to connect with a substantial number of veterans. Although the goal is to train veterans in technical fields, the project also will work to meet tangential needs such as child care, transportation and housing so warfighters and/or their spouses can take advantage of the training.Microsoft Corporation is leading the effort, and the first organization to join the coalition is the Iraq and Afghanistan Veterans of America (IAVA). According to Andrea Taylor, director of community affairs for North America, Microsoft, this latest effort is a follow-on to the Elevate America program, a Microsoft initiative that provides technical training to U.S. citizens so they can fill technical job openings. IAVA is involved in the veteran project because it collects a host of data about veterans that can be used to determine the most effective locations to offer the programs. Taylor says that other groups—including organizations in the private and public sectors—are being sought to join the coalition.The company has committed to contributing $2 million in cash and up to $6 million in software to the program. Organizations with projects designed to offer veterans and their spouses support—particularly those in the 18- to 24-year-old age range—must submit requests for proposals (RFPs) no later than April 30. A panel of advisers will review the proposals and choose the 10 to 12 organizations that receive the grants and software.Organizations that receive grants and software will offer the training directly in the communities in locations such as veteran centers, community colleges and the YMCA. Today’s Elevate America program offers online training as well as class material in multiple languages, and Taylor anticipates that the veterans programs also will include these alternatives.Unlike the initial program, which began in February 2009 and ends this month, the veterans program is a two-year project. During the first year, organizations will develop their offerings; during the second year, the groups that show the most promising programs in terms of effectiveness and the ability to be replicated in other locations, will receive additional support. “The idea is to be able to scale these programs up,” Taylor explains.Today’s meager job market is one reason Microsoft decided to develop and support the initiative. “Veterans are challenged to find opportunities, and they may not have had the chance to gain industry skills before entering the service, especially since many went in immediately after secondary school,” she says. Training in Microsoft’s specialties is particularly valuable. Many employers have found that they have hired people who claim to be able to use the company’s programs but in fact are not fluent in them. Microsoft certification alleviates this problem so companies can be confident that job applicants who are certified actually possess the skill set they say they have, Taylor shares. “Right now, there are six workers for every one job out there. These certifications can make a veteran stand out,” she states.In addition to getting the word out about these programs via the media, Microsoft plans to use social media to spread the word. For information about this program, visit the Elevate America Web site. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
