<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>April 15, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>April 2010</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Wireless Microwave TechnologyCommercial and government wireless carriers require seamless connectivity between handheld devices and the fiber optic network. Developed for North American and Japanese service providers, the FlexiPacket Microwave capability combines Carrier Ethernet transport with microwave radio technology to replace existing proprietary mobile backhaul platforms. It uses standard gigabit Ethernet interfaces to connect directly with existing base stations and seamlessly provide a wireless extension of packet-based, optical-fiber networks. For more information, contact www.nokiasiemensnetworks.com. Virtual Shelter Design SoftwareThis software application allows users to design their own shelter applications. Developed by shelter manufacturer DHS Technologies, the Virtual Tactical Application Program (VTAP 2.0) allows users to build two-dimensional and three-dimensional renderings of a Deployable Rapid Assembly Shelter (DRASH) system complex as it would appear in the theater of operations. VTAP 2.0 features a menu that offers a variety of shelter and trailer formats that can be added to the virtual footprint. For more information, visit www.drash.com/vtap. Rugged RoutersThese two routers are engineered for use in electric power utilities, industrial plants and traffic control systems. The RuggedRouter RX1500 and RX1501 are flexible, modular platforms that allow users to modify the hardware configuration in the field as needed. The RX1500 is a hardened, integrated layer 3 Ethernet switch and router that permits operators to select between digital subscriber line, cellular, T1/E1, digital data system, serial and Ethernet options. The RX1501 features increased port density in 100 megabytes per second line rates, and it can support up to 24 optical ports and 36-port copper 10/100Base-TX. For more information, visit www.ruggedcom.com.Communications Intelligence Receiver/JammerIn modern combat situations, warfighters require systems capable of switching between intelligence gathering and electronic warfare modes. The Tactical System Receiver 2300 is a communications intelligence device capable of locating, listening, recording, disseminating data and jamming support for a range of communications. It can perform intelligence and jamming missions in many environments aboard air, land and seagoing platforms. For more information, visit www.elisra.com. E-mail Security Virtual MachineManaging and securing e-mail in any size organization can be challenging. ModusGate VM is an e-mail security virtual machine that uses an organization’s underutilized computing resources to provide security storage and processing without adding extra hardware. The software is optimized for small and medium-sized corporate and service provider environments. ModusGate VM runs on Windows 2003 and 2008 guest operating systems, and it performs spam filtering for virtual and physical e-mail servers, including Exchange 2003, 2007 and 2010. For more information, visit www.vircom.com. Embedded Computer ModuleDesigned for low-power use and a high degree of configurability, the ETX270 is an ETX 3.0 Embedded Computer Module capable of supporting both peripheral component interconnect (PCI) and PCI Express architectures. The ETX270 is a system on module design engineered for use in cost-saving and space-limited environments. For more information, visit www.dtims.com/products/sff/etx270.php.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
