<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>Helen Mosher, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>June 15, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>June 2010</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Low-Light Security Camera Digital and infrared imaging solutions help provide situational awareness and long-range observation capabilities in security systems. FLIR Systems has developed the ChromaNox cameras, which use electron-multiplying charge-coupled device technology. With near-infrared response and on-chip gain amplification, the cameras provide high image quality in a wide range of lighting and environmental conditions. Two models are available in 640×480 and 1280Ã—1024 resolution, respectively. GPS ReceiverSymmetricom has released the the RoHS-certified XL-GPS Time and Frequency Receiver, a network-managed Global Positioning System (GPS) instrument that generates precise time and frequency signals referenced to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC). It is suited for applications in test and measurement, central timing systems, process automation, test range timing and the power industry. The XL-GPS conforms to the European Union RoHS Directive as well. More information is available here.Wall Plate Transmitter Audio-visual technology isn’t just digital anymore; it’s high-definition. Crestron’s latest wall plate allows for high-definition multimedia interface (HDMI) connections from Blu-ray and other HD playback devices. The DM-TX-200-2G enables switching between one HDMI and one RGB input. The HDMI input supports HDMI with high-bandwidth digital content protection (HDCP), WUXGA computer resolutions and 1080p60 HDTV with multichannel lossless audio. With audio and USB access, as well as a PC port, the transmitter allows users to integrate digital and analog signals.Compact Low-Angle Radiation AntennaThe Low Observable antenna from Spectrum Advanced Specialty Products is more discreet and compact than a comparable 5/8 whip antenna while still producing a low angle of radiation. The linear antenna has a 3dB beamwidth horizon to a 55-degree elevation with less than 3dB azimuth variation, a peak gain of -3dBil and a scalable frequency of 136 to +915MHz. It also features rugged construction and a wide range of sizes. High-Speed Rotation Stage The URB100CC rotation stage is designed for motion applications that require fast moves over larger angles or continuous rotation at very high duty cycles, with high-precision performance relative to wobble, angular repeatability and speed stability, such as light detection and ranging and three-dimensional imaging. The URB100CC is based on the Newport’s URS series but features a belt drive instead of a worm gear. The belt drive provides significantly higher rotation speeds of up to 720 degrees per second without sacrificing life, according to the company. The two-piece design provides stiffness and reliability while minimizing wobble and eccentricity. Rugged Dual ServerWhen virtualization isn’t possible and space is at a premium, Crystal Group’s RS101x2 offers performance, ruggedness and reliability, according to the manufacturer. The RS101x2 contains two computers in the same chassis, each with 2.53GHz Intel Core 2 Duo Mobile, Penryn T9400, Socket P and micro-FCPGA478. A short-depth (18 inches) rugged dual server, the RS101x2 includes one slot per side—a Mini-PCIe, 1XSD and Mini PCI—and one external 3.5-inch bay, capable of one to two removable 2.5-inch Serial Advanced Technology Attachment hard disc drives, for up to four drives total in each server.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
