<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Protecting Your Own</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>September  2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>On Cyber Patrol</tag>
    <tag>September 2010</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>A soldier in harm’s way has no greater ally than other soldiers watching his or her back. That trust is the key component of a good unit. Usually, the bond of trust that only members of the military share is built during training and missions. That trust is priceless in theater, but what about other environments? Dark alleys, sketchy neighborhoods, the bleachers of an away game – soldiers have that covered. But, who has your back in cyber space?</abstract>
  <text>A soldier in harm’s way has no greater ally than other soldiers watching his or her back. That trust is thekey component of a good unit. Usually, the bond of trust that only members of the military share is builtduring training and missions. That trust is priceless in theater, but what about other environments?Dark alleys, sketchy neighborhoods, the bleachers of an away game – soldiers have that covered. But,who has your back in cyberspace?Because of the interactivity and connectivity of the web and military networks, a moment of inattentionor negligence can put lives and missions at risk half way around the world. Cybercriminals and foreignagents are always looking for weak spots and open doors in our secure networks. Even when all securityprotocols are in place our military networks are under constant attack. That’s no secret. Yet, it is notalways obvious to military personnel stateside or down range, that a single unauthorized download ora network access point left unsecured can endanger fellow soldiers. Once a bad guy is inside the cyberwire it might take months to fully realize the damage done and the missions and lives compromised.That means a person who just has to bend or break IA policies and procedures “just this once,” maynever fully understand the harm that once instant could cause.The news is full of stories of leaked information from within our own ranks. If one of our own can do it,what about those with whom we are at war or those who do not have our national interests at heart?Is there a degree of blame for the loss of secure data whether someone who purposely leaks data orsomeone who lets a bad guy in because of negligence? The stakes are too high when it comes to theloss of military data or personally identifying information. Blame becomes secondary when the realproblem is that it happened in the first place. We may not always be able to prevent data loss causedby someone who we thought we could trust. However, every soldier, civilian worker and governmentcontractor can remember that there are soldiers in harm’s way who are trusting us to protect the dataand communications that could put them at riskI’m sure the information assurance message must be getting old to people who cannot fully understandthe potential risks of allowing even one network breach. For those who understand the consequences,no amount of training and reminding will be enough. Our cybersecurity technology is constantlyimproving and evolving to meet increased and often very sophisticated threats. Yet, technologicalsafeguards can still be compromised by a determined and knowledgeable person. It doesn’t even takesomeone who is trying to cause harm. It just takes someone that has to have that new online gameor has to take advantage of the free music, or has to tell everyone in a social networking group aboutthe “really interesting” stuff going on at work. Whether it’s in Kansas, Korea or Kandahar, anyone withaccess to military data and military networks has the responsibility to keep the bad guys out. We allneed to have each other’s cyber back.The On Cyber Patrol© cartoon and supporting articles are created and made available by the U.S. Army’s Office of Information Assurance and Compliance, NETCOM, CIO/G6. For more information on the OCP program or to submit ideas for upcoming cartoons/articles, contact oncyberpatrol@hqda.army.mil. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
