<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>MOUNTING A VIGOROUS DEFENSE IN DEPTH</title>
  <author>Bob Gourley</author>
  <date>Tuesday, October 05, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Intel Tech Blog</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>I know some guys who are really good at external validation of enterprise security posture. There are some folks so good that nothing will totally stop them. The history of computer science makes me think world-class-best folks like that will always be with us and there will never be a system that is perfectly defendable. But still, there are steps you can take to dramatically enhance the security of your enterprise. I've reviewed some of these before, like ensuring endpoints are protected from malware, using defense in depth to enhance your security posture, mitigating IPv6 security threats, and studying the threat. With this post I'd like to mention another capability that belongs in your defense in depth tool suite: the Microsoft Security news, products, updates and tools site at http://microsoft.com/security The security site at Microsoft is a way for enterprise and home users to tap into three key security centers: The Microsoft Security Engineering Center, The Microsoft Security Response Center, and The Microsoft Malware Protection Center. It is good to know all three of those, but the best way to interface with them, in my opinion, is through the security site...</abstract>
  <text>I know some guys who are really good at external validation of enterprise security posture. There are some folks so good that nothing will totally stop them. The history of computer science makes me think world-class-best folks like that will always be with us and there will never be a system that is perfectly defendable. But still, there are steps you can take to dramatically enhance the security of your enterprise.I’ve reviewed some of these before, like ensuring endpoints are protected from malware, using defense in depth to enhance your security posture, mitigating IPv6 security threats, and studying the threat.With this post I’d like to mention another capability that belongs in your defense in depth tool suite: the Microsoft Security news, products, updates and tools site at http://microsoft.com/security The security site at Microsoft is a way for enterprise and home users to tap into three key security centers: The Microsoft Security Engineering Center, The Microsoft Security Response Center, and The Microsoft Malware Protection Center. It is good to know all three of those, but the best way to interface with them, in my opinion, is through the security site.Anyone who uses any Microsoft products or capabilities (which means anyone who works in a company and most of us who have a computer) should put the Microsoft security site on their short list. It has turned into a solid source of information relevant to protecting your IT and informing your decisions.  Here are a few key capabilities you will find there:News: This site focuses on news and alerts Microsoft wants to highlight, which means you will also want to consume news from other sources like SANS.org, but you definitely also want to track this official source. Analysis: The Microsoft Security Intelligence Report provides comprehensive, wide-ranging assessments and analysis on the cyber threat, showing trends in software vulnerabilities, exploits, malware and other adversary activity. Download the SIR volume 8. Key findings of this report will help inform your strategic decision-making. Products: You will find links at the Microsoft Security site for the most important security enhancing products available.  This includes a link to Windows 7, which is the platform your enterprise should be running desktops on to ensure the right mix of functionality and security.  But the site also links to several other products, like Microsoft Security Essentials.  This capability provides enhanced real-time protection for your home PC. Enterprises will make use of other high end tools, but businesses small and large should ensure all your users have protection at home too, it is a key part of your defense in depth. Updates: Links from the Microsoft Security Site will point to you ways to ensure you are running the most up to date software on your PC.  This is a critically important step in maintaining a defense in depth. Tools: Microsoft provides tools that will aid in removing malicious code from infected PCs.  How will you know if you are infected with bad code?  It can be really hard to tell, so the recommendation is to download and run the right tools from this site and let the tool tell you what is going on.Bottom line here: The site at Microsoft.com/security is an important site to know about before you get into trouble.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
