<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>IN-Q-TEL TECHNOLOGIES/CAPABILITIES HIGHLIGHTED</title>
  <author>Bob Gourley</author>
  <date>Monday, March 14, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Intel Tech Blog</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Forbes ran a nice piece on In-Q-Tel.  The article is worth reading in its entirety.  Here is a link: Startups Backed By The CIA.

The In-Q-Tel mission is to identify, adapt and deliver innovative technology solutions to support the missions of the Central Intelligence Agency and the broader US Intelligence Community, including the Department of Homeland Security.</abstract>
  <text>Forbes ran a nice piece on In-Q-Tel.  The article is worth reading in its entirety.  Here is a link: Startups Backed By The CIA.The In-Q-Tel mission is to identify, adapt and deliver innovative technology solutions to support the missions of the Central Intelligence Agency and the broader US Intelligence Community, including the Department of Homeland Security.As a teaser till you get around to the article, here is a list of companies in the order written about there, including a short bullet of their capability and a hot-link to their site:·         Cleversafe – Smart way to save your data in the cloud. Clever and Safe.·         AdaptivEnergy – Capture energy from vibrations.·         Qynergy – New battery technology.·         Infinite Power Solutions – Thin-film batteries to power RFID.·         ThingMagic – Advanced RFID solutions.·         GainSpan – WiFi enablement.·         Image Tree Corp – Figure out what is growing on the earth.·         Fortius One – Advanced, easy geospatial.·         Geosemble – Map people, places, things using data from RSS feeds and tweets.·         LensVector – Taking moving parts out of cameras.·         3VR – Video analytics.·         Recorded Future – Gain knowledge of the future by looking for events mentioned on the net.·         Visible Technologies – Analysis.·         FMS – Analysis.·         StreamBase – Capture and analyze data in stream.·         Destineer Studios – Advanced immersive environments.·         Sonitus Medical – hear from your teeth.·         Basis Technology – Search in multi-language. (These technologies (and others) are also listed on the CTOvision.com Disruptive IT list).Congrats to all the companies mentioned here for the great write-up in Forbes.  And congrats to forward thinkers in the intelligence community for creating a structure that enables quicker discovery of technologies of interest to your mission. This is a win-win-win.  A win for the intelligence community, a win for companies involved, and a win for national security.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
