<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>April 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>April 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Peek-a-Boo Backpack The latest version of the Prism through-wall radar product line fits in a backpack and can provide intelligence on the location and movement of any people inside a particular room simply by having the operator stand with the radar pack next to the wall. The recently launched Prism 200c is lightweight and inconspicuous and can be used for counterterrorism, military or police special operations missions. The Prism 200c, which was developed by Cambridge Consultants, shaves seconds off the setup process by allowing the operator to lean against a wall to either monitor or record the activity within a building while maintaining cover by operating it via a handheld laptop computer or similar personal device. The new device boasts up to eight hours of battery life, reduced weight load, and resistance to water and dust, and it works even in environments such as modern offices with a lot of radar reflecting surfaces. It offers user-friendly data presentation on-device and remotely. It also offers a 3-D view. The devices are available in North America, Europe and Asia.Enhanced Signal JammerAn enhanced jamming capability for the U.S. Army Common Infrared Countermeasures (CIRCM) self-protection system integrates a continuous laser autoboresight module into a lightweight, small and reportedly inexpensive jam head designed specifically for rotary-wing applications. The laser autoboresight module ensures that laser energy is aligned with the jam head track point to maintain jamming energy on the threat missile. Developed by Northrop Grumman and SELEX Galileo, the new functionality automatically maintains good laser pointing in the rotary-wing environment, and it can maintain the laser beam on the dome of small, man-portable missiles moving faster than the speed of sound. The autoboresight module is designed to work with any jamming laser, enabling future laser upgrades without having to modify the jam head. The multiband Viper laser, currently in full-rate production, and a small jam head were used during a recent demonstration. The module also measures laser power in the jam head prior to exiting the system to ensure the system is fully functional. Shut UPSA recently introduced Rugged Uninterruptible Power Supply automatically shuts off during vehicle and power equipment roll-overs caused by shock, vibration or kinetic impact during combat. Uninterruptible power supplies (UPS) that remain turned on in such situations create a hazard for vehicle occupants, power generators and sensitive electronic equipment, according to officials at Acumentrics Corporation, the company that makes the Rugged-UPS 2500 DC series of uninterruptible power supply and power conditioner units. The units automatically sense the orientation of the vehicle or piece of equipment and shut off when necessary. The units can also send a trigger signal to another system, for example, to relay an emergency alarm or activate another safety-related device. For added flexibility, the manufacturer can change the angle of activation and users can disable the function. The units can be used in Humvees, ships, trains, planes, tracked vehicles or construction equipment where significant roll, inversions or vibrations can present hazardous situations. They can also be used in stationary power systems, such as gas, solar and wind generators; batteries; and capacitors that need to be oriented precisely.FAST-acting CommunicationsThe Forward-Deployed Asset Support Terminal (FAST) provides quick-deploy communications in an enterprise-class platform capable of delivering tens of megabits of connectivity and technology options that turn the platform into a multipurpose hub for local communications. Designed for use in the aftermath of tsunamis, earthquakes, hurricanes or floods, each FAST unit, developed by Globecomm Systems Incorporated, can deploy its SatCell Instant Mobile Network, which can provide local and long-distance mobile service and advanced calling features. The contractor can also provide short-notice set-up and maintenance of the hub, shipping coordination and satellite bandwidth on-demand.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
