<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>New Products</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>July 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>July 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Squad Car Command Center A newly introduced video downlink technology transforms emergency responder vehicles, such as police squad cars or firetrucks, into mobile command centers. The in-car downlink system is touted by its maker as providing seamless integration into any first responder vehicle. Recently introduced by Integrated Microwave Technologies (IMT), the system can be integrated into the existing infrastructure on a squad car or first responder vehicle; no hardware or software modifications are required, and the system reportedly creates no interference with the existing computer set-up. IMT’s ruggedized Mobile Tactical Receiver lies at the heart of the system, which also includes a coded orthogonal frequency division multiplexer receiver with an Ethernet port for streaming video over Internet protocol or local or remote software to hardware decodes. This allows many remote viewers, in addition to the first responder vehicle, to monitor the same video simultaneously, increasing situational awareness.Next-Generation 3-DCurrent three-dimensional (3-D) imaging methods require the camera sensor to remain static during the capture time, which limits the ability to capture dynamic scenes or images while in motion. Methods that may enable motion range imaging suffer from a variety of problems, such as poor resolution, low accuracy, bulkiness and nonrobustness. A near real-time, free-motion, handheld 3-D imaging capability has extensive applications in the military environment, in homeland security and the commercial sector. Some of the basic applications include battle damage assessment and recovery, counter-improvised explosive device detection and neutralization, forensics, explosive ordnance disposal, modeling and simulation, training, mission planning and rehearsal, intelligence operations and many civil engineering applications. In order to meet these critical requirements, CACI Technologies Incorporated has teamed with Mantis Vision to develop the MVC F-5 handheld 3-D camera system that provides a near real- time image gathering capability that can be tailored for a wide array of missions. The system can obtain angle, distance, diameter or volume measurements of the interior or exterior section of a complex structure with millimeter accuracy. It also can capture an object in motion under all light conditions. The Mantis Vision Producer Software (MVP 2.0) offers a variety of tools for 3-D modeling, file management, data processing, visualizations and measurement of 3-D point cloud models. Sensor on a Pole The MX-10GS electro-optical/infrared (EO/IR) imaging turret integrates L-3 WESCAM’s MX-Series technology into vehicle mast or tower-mounted turret configurations, providing force protection, border security and ground combat mission crews with a solution to continuously identify, track and deter threats from the ground. The 37-pound system incorporates imaging capabilities, high-definition resolution and a 360-degree vantage point that enables long-range missions to unfold whether crews are stationary or on the move. It can be configured with up to six leading imaging and laser sensors, and its patented stabilization, passive isolation design and high optical magnification capabilities support covert range performance outside the audible range. In addition, the system’s rapid zoom technology provides a wide field-of-view and pinpointed ability to identify urban and asymmetrical threats, increasing warfighter survivability in engagement areas. Iridium MessengerThe DeLorme inReach is an Iridium-based personal communicator designed to deliver global two-way satellite text messaging, delivery confirmations, emergency SOS signaling capabilities, remote tracking and an Android smartphone interface. The inReach is marketed as a way for people to stay affordably connected over the 90-percent of the Earth’s surface not covered by cellular and land-based phone service. The system’s core communications component is the Iridium 9602 short-burst data transceiver, which provides two-way communications connection through the Iridium satellite network. Iridium’s pole-to-pole global connectivity means inReach users can send and receive messages anywhere on the planet, according to DeLorme officials. The Global Positioning System (GPS)-enabled system can be used by itself or paired with either an Android smartphone or a DeLorme Earthmate PN-60w. When using the inReach as a stand-alone device, users can send preloaded text messages to designated recipients and activate remote tracking, allowing others to follow their travels online via a continually updated “bread crumb” trail. It also confirms message delivery. Emergency messages automatically activate remote tracking. The SOS feature is protected to prevent false alarms. The compact device is waterproof, floatable and impact-resistant, and it can maintain satellite signal lock even in difficult GPS environments. It will be available in October.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
