<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Partners with U.S. Coast Guard</title>
  <author>George I. Seffers, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>August 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>August 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Under a memorandum of understanding announced on July 14, the U.S. Coast Guard Command, Control, Communications, Computers and Information Technology (C4IT) Service Center will leverage AFCEA resources for providing market research, identifying technology trends and raising awareness of ongoing initiatives.</abstract>
  <text>Under a memorandum of understanding announced on July 14, the U.S. Coast Guard Command, Control, Communications, Computers and Information Technology (C4IT) Service Center will leverage AFCEA resources for providing market research, identifying technology trends and raising awareness of ongoing initiatives.As part of the agreement, Mark Powell, director of the Coast Guard’s C4IT Service Center, has been elected as a liaison member of the AFCEA Technology Committee. The committee enhances AFCEA’s outreach to the information technology communities; cultivates partnerships among government, industry, academic and scientific leaders; and focuses on finding solutions for the information technology and related management problems facing specific objectives. Those objectives include facilitating networking, outreach and collaboration opportunities; and promoting discussion forums and seminars in support of government agency, industry and scientific solutions and their adaptation. “AFCEA International is excited to partner with the U.S. Coast Guard and work with industry to collaboratively address problems and share best practices,” says Kent Schneider, president and chief executive officer of AFCEA International. “Mark is the perfect fit for our Technology Committee based on his capabilities and thought leadership. The insight he will provide into the Coast Guard’s and Department of Homeland Security’s strategic vision will not only benefit technology committee members but the entire government IT community as well.”For more information, visit www.afcea.org/committees/technology.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
