<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Directories Speak to Government Acquisition Professionals</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>August 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>August 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Joining AFCEA provides business-building opportunities. Your company’s visibility is elevated through its corporate profile listing in the AFCEA Source Book.</abstract>
  <text>Joining AFCEA provides business-building opportunities. Your company’s visibility is elevated through its corporate profile listing in the AFCEA Source Book. As a corporate member, your company receives space in the January issue of SIGNAL Magazine describing corporate capabilities and contact information. Sustaining members also can include the company logo and a photo of a senior executive officer. The Source Book is published annually and is distributed to the association’s nearly 34,000 members. The online version includes a direct link to your company website and is keyword searchable. Your company’s digital profile will be included in four online databases: the Source Book, the Health IT Directory, the Cybersecurity Directory and the Intelligence Directory.Companies in the Source Book also can enhance their digital profiles through one of four premium packages, which include priority and enhanced search results as well as digital and print advertising space. For more information or to see a demonstration online, email Maryann Lawlor or call (703) 631-6179.It is very important for companies in the Source Book to update their profiles online regularly so potential clients and partners see current information. AFCEA members searching the Source Book statistically have a high buying power. SIGNAL readers influence a budget of $51.2 million for communications, security, electronics, components, equipment and systems. A typical reader’s organization spends more than $3 million in these areas. The key to a good profile is being specific. Provide examples of what your company offers, the organizations you have worked with and your company’s specialties. To update your company’s profile, click here.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
