<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>From the Editor</title>
  <author></author>
  <date>August 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Beginning with this issue, SIGNAL Connections has been enhanced to better meet your needs as an AFCEA member. Each issue will highlight events that are taking place in your area, as well as news about your chapter, the association, AFCEA benefits and fellow members. Also featured will be industry news and commentary from other SIGNAL media to provide a comprehensive package of information. 
</abstract>
  <text>Beginning with this issue, SIGNAL Connections has been enhanced to better meet your needs as an AFCEA member. Each issue will highlight events that are taking place in your area, as well as news about your chapter, the association, AFCEA benefits and fellow members. Also featured will be industry news and commentary from other SIGNAL media to provide a comprehensive package of information. The goal of the new design is twofold. First, SIGNAL Connections will continue to bring you up-to-date information about recent activity in the government and information technology arenas. Second, this networking tool will include the information you need to know to connect with potential business partners and take full advantage of your membership.Also new with this issue is the introduction of a mobile version of the e-newsletter. You now have the option to view SIGNAL Connections specially formatted for your phone. Click the link at the top of the email to get to the Web version of the newsletter, and if the mobile version does not load automatically, scroll to the bottom of the page for a "mobile" link to switch to this view.We welcome your input into this forum. SIGNAL Connections is a means to enhance your business and professional relationships, so let us know how we can improve. Drop me a note at mlawlor@afcea.org.~Maryann Lawlor</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
