<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Introduces TechNet Land Forces</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>September 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>September 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>To bring solutions and ideas closer to centers of expertise, AFCEA International will offer three new regional events in 2012.</abstract>
  <text>To bring solutions and ideas closer to centers of expertise, AFCEA International will offer three new regional events in 2012. Although focused on the land forces—the U.S. Army and U.S. Marine Corps—members from all five U.S. military services as well as coalition partners will be invited to participate.TechNet Land Forces–Southwest is scheduled to take place in Arizona at the Tucson Convention Center March 27-29, 2012, where government leaders and attendees will discuss network and security operations. The second event, TechNet Land Forces–South, will take place in Tampa, Florida, as LandWarNet has in the past, July 9-12, 2012, and will center on joint and coalition programs and initiatives. Rounding out the trio of conferences is TechNet Land Forces–East, planned to take place August 13-16, 2012, in Baltimore, where military leaders will examine the challenges and opportunities cyber offers and explore the solutions they need. Each event will include speakers, panels and exhibits as well as opportunities for in-depth dialogue. Government leaders and the association decided to position these land forces events nearer to the hubs of military activity in these specific specialties to increase the convenience for participants.Lt. Gen. John Dubia, USA (Ret.), executive vice president, AFCEA, says the association team, in conjunction with the government, continues to concentrate attention on the questions that need to be answered. “Efforts in the areas of network and security operations, joint and coalition activities, and cyber remain dynamic, and the challenges continue. Government and coalition leaders are working with the association to sharpen the focus toward finding solutions. Positioning these events in these specific locations facilitates support for that work,” he says.For more information about participating in the TechNet Land Forces events, contact J. Spargo &amp; Associates or AFCEA International.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
