<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Corporate Membership Means Dollars and Sense</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>October 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>October 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Corporate membership has doubled in the past five years—now topping 2,000. Corporate members benefit from a high degree of visibility in the command, control, communications, computers, intelligence and information technology military and government arenas.</abstract>
  <text>Through AFCEA, corporate members benefit from a high degree of visibility in the command, control, communications, computers, intelligence and information technology military and government arenas. This visibility creates the opportunity to network, build relationships, exchange information and contribute to ongoing discussion. Corporate membership has doubled in the past five years—now topping 2,000—because of these benefits, but in addition to the somewhat intangible value of visibility, corporate members enjoy more concrete financial benefits. Corporate members receive high priority in exhibit space selection and table assignments at all AFCEA International events. In addition, they are eligible for an average discount of $450 for exhibition space, and AFCEA corporate associates receive reduced registration fees and tickets for association events. AFCEA also rewards corporate loyalty with premium exhibit locations. Companies receive points for being a corporate member or a sustaining member as well as repeatedly hosting exhibits at events. The number of points coincides with seniority placement of exhibits. As part of a corporate membership, companies designate a number of employees who become individual members of the association. The benefit enables companies to leverage individual memberships within their organizations by choosing those staff members who can best take advantage of the networking AFCEA offers. If a designated individual leaves the company, the AFCEA individual membership stays with the organization, and it can be assigned to another staff member.AFCEA members in a shopping mood can take advantage of several discount programs on hardware and software. Special deals are available from HP, Dell and Microsoft.All association corporate members receive a 25 percent discount for Federation for Identity and Cross-Credentialing Systems (FiXs) credentials provided by Widepoint/ORC. FiXs credentials enable identity authentication and access to participating government systems as well as physical access to participating facilities. Corporate members also are eligible for measurable financial benefits in the new online AFCEA directories with a member-only discount on Premium Packages of up to 40 percent. As an enhancement of the free corporate profile, features of these packages enable organizations to boost the notoriety and the usefulness of their companies’ corporate profile with priority search results placement, e-advertising and search capabilities that extend into the company website. Corporate profiles also are printed in the AFCEA Source Book in the January issue of SIGNAL Magazine; listings in the printed version are limited to corporate members. In addition, shortly after joining AFCEA, a new corporate member’s corporate profile appears in a current issue of SIGNAL Magazine. Various levels of corporate membership are available. For more information, contact Diane Dellen at ddellen@afcea.org or (703) 631-6150 or visit the AFCEA membership page.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
