<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Citizens Stand Behind U.S. Troops</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>November 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Veteran Focus</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA International and its members have a long history of supporting the military community. Bringing people together is a large part of our mission; supporting veterans, troops and their families is undoubtedly our passion. This publication is intended to highlight other groups that reach out to the military in a way that is helpful to veterans from every war, to troops and to their families. It is not intended to be comprehensive. Indeed, that would be almost impossible because the outpouring of support for the military is so large and varied. It also is not promoting the organizations included as better than ones not mentioned. The goal of the following articles is to provide information about reputable groups that offer different forms of support in a variety of ways. But more importantly, this publication is designed to showcase the immense pride and gratitude the people of our great nation feel for their service members.</abstract>
  <text>This is one of several articles published in our Veterans Focus. To see all articles from the series, please visit www.afcea.org/signal/veteran.asp.AFCEA International and its members have a long history of supporting the military community. Bringing people together is a large part of our mission; supporting veterans, troops and their families is undoubtedly our passion. This publication is intended to highlight other groups that reach out to the military in a way that is helpful to veterans from every war, to troops and to their families. It is not intended to be comprehensive. Indeed, that would be almost impossible because the outpouring of support for the military is so large and varied. It also is not promoting the organizations included as better than ones not mentioned. The goal of the following articles is to provide information about reputable groups that offer different forms of support in a variety of ways. But more importantly, this publication is designed to showcase the immense pride and gratitude the people of our great nation feel for their service members.While researching these articles, I had the chance to talk to some amazing people. I spoke with wounded warriors working to prevent anyone else from going through the pain they endured; I interviewed amputees who are showcasing how an injury does not define a life; I talked to young adults who were children when they started to use their money and free time to benefit the military; and, I listened to many veterans, family members and civilian citizens eager to ensure that veterans and troops feel cared for and valued. The timing of this publication is no coincidence. It comes in the month we celebrate Veterans Day, during the year we mark a decade of war. Ten years ago, the United States suffered a shocking blow when terrorists killed thousands of citizens on the nation’s own soil. The troops and veterans who joined the military after 9/11 knew full well that signing on that dotted line meant deploying to war. Never before have ribbons and support been so necessary for so long. But the information included here is for all who have served and share the bonds of conflict. These men and women range from veterans of World War II who found themselves in a situation similar to 9/11 70 years ago, when a different sneak attack launched the United States into war across the Pacific and in Europe, to the veterans of Vietnam and Korea, who understand guerilla warfare in far-off foreign places. AFCEA also has other forums to promote participation in and discussion of military charities. These include Homefront Help blog posts (www.afcea.org/blog) and the Homefront Help Facebook page (www.facebook.com/homefronthelp). People who would like to contribute information about their efforts are encouraged to share through these electronic offerings or to look for connections that could help extend their outreach. No matter how you show your support, we want to hear about it and help. Contact me at rboland@afcea.org.To all our veterans, we offer a simple but deeply felt message: Thank You, and Welcome Home.—Rita Boland</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
