<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Support</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>November 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Veteran Focus</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>This is one of several articles published in our Veterans Focus. To see all articles from the series, please visit www.afcea.org/signal/veteran.asp.The following is a small sampling of charities that AFCEA International and its corporate members support. This list is representative of the variety of organizations that benefit under the broad AFCEA umbrella, but it is not complete. Many other initiatives happen on the local or regional level, and many companies support the veteran needs of individual employees and their families. All AFCEA companies were invited to submit information for this report, and the information in this list includes all of the submissions received as of September 6, 2011. AFCEA companies can add their information to this list online at AFCEA.org/veterans.Allied Associates InternationalArmy Scholarship FoundationInstitute for Veterans Education &amp; Training (I-VET) Applied Integrated Technologies, Inc. Association of the United States ArmyArmed Forces Communications and Electronics Association (AFCEA) InternationalAFCEA Educational FoundationFisher House FoundationFisher House Smart House at LandstuhlHomefront HugsHomeward DeployedOperation GratitudeOperation Iraqi ChildrenSgt. Mac FoundationUSOWounded Warrior Amputee Softball TeamWreaths Across America The Boeing Company-Intelligence Systems GroupUSOWarrior Gateway Booz Allen HamiltonMore than 80, including:Aleethia FoundationOperation HomefrontParalyzed Veterans of AmericaUSOCACI  AFCEA Educational FoundationAirborne Mine Countermeasures Association Inc.Air Force Aid SocietyAmerican Freedom FestivalAssociation of the United States ArmyCauseCoast Guard FoundationDisabled Sports ProjectDisabled Sports USA/Wounded Warrior Fisher House FoundationMilitary Order of the Purple Heart Service FoundationNational Maritime Historical SocietyNaval Academy Athletic AssociationNaval Submarine LeagueNaval War College FoundationNavy Historical FoundationNavy League of the United StatesNavy SEAL FoundationPease GreetersProject Healing WatersRide 2 RecoverySpecial Operations Warrior FoundationTechAmerica Operation Jump Start VII Sponsorship OpportunityTragedy Assistance Program for Survivors (TAPS)Tuskegee Airmen IncorporatedUnited States Navy Memorial FoundationU.S. Army Cadets Corp Inc.USOVirginia War MemorialWorld War II FoundationWounded Warrior ProjectWreaths Across America Cannon Construction Inc.Association of the United States ArmyFriends of American Lake Golf CourseSupport our Soldiers CDW-GOperation HomefrontOperation Support Our Troops-AmericaWounded Warrior Project ClearanceJobsAssociation of the United States ArmyIowa Remembrance Run Crane Aerospace &amp; ElectronicsHero Box CTI Resource Management Service Inc. (CTI)USOWounded Warrior Project Defense Integration Solutions LLCMassachusetts Iraq and Afghanistan Fallen Heroes MemorialGreater Omaha ChamberAFCEA Educational FoundationAssociation of Defense CommunitiesEmployer Support of Guard ReservesNebraska Military Support CoalitionSpace FoundationStrategic Command Consultation Committee Harris CapRock CommunicationsDoctors Without BordersInternational Red CrossLiving Water InternationalUNICEF  HPCamp Lejeune 4th of JulyCamp Lejeune MayniaCamp Pendleton 4th of July Beach BashCamp Pendleton Mud RunFort Bragg Race SeriesFort Knox 10 Miler races (two yearly)Hawaii Race SeriesHenderson Hall Races (four yearly) Hosting Wounded Warriors in HP Suite at Redskins football game Marine Corps MarathonMCRD Fun RunsMilitary Appreciation Concert National Disabled Veterans Winter Sports ClinicNational Memorial Day ParadeNMCI Toys 4 TotsOkinawa Newcomer’s Orientation Brief Paralyzed Veterans of America GalaParalyzed Veterans of America GamesSan Diego MCRD Santa’s Arrival San Diego MWR Race Series and Family EventSemper Fi Fund Pasta DinnerU.S. Marine Corps Community ServicesUSO Military Family Care Package Stuffing PartyWounded Warrior Bike RideWounded Warrior ExperienceWounded Warrior Project Soldier RideICF InternationalAmerican Freedom Foundation, TheDisabled American VeteransJBMAssociation of the United States ArmyEmployer Support of the Guard and Reserve (ESGR)Marine Corps Scholarship Foundation (MCSF)Special Operations Warrior FoundationWounded Warrior ProjectWounded Warrior Project Soldier Ride MiCORE Solutions Inc.Disabled American VeteransWounded Warrior Project MIL Corporation, ThePatriot Cruise and Salute Inc. MITRECompany-wide Summer Troop Care Package DrivesSuits for VetsNational Disabled Veterans Winter Sports Clinic NES AssociatesMaude FoundationWounded Warrior Project NJVCLaptops for the WoundedNorthrop GrummanArmed Forces FoundationArmed Services YMCA of the USAAssociation of the United States ArmyDisabled American VeteransFisher House FoundationHomes for Our TroopsOperation HomefrontParalyzed Veterans of America Special Operations Warrior FoundationUSOVeterans of Foreign WarsWounded Warrior Project QinetiQ North AmericaEOD Memorial FoundationHope for the WarriorsNight Stalker AssociationOperation Helping Hands for HeroesProject Healing WatersTragedy Assistance Program for Survivors (TAPS)Wounded Warrior Project SAICAl Barry Foundation, TheAmerican Freedom FoundationAmerican LegionArmed Forces FoundationArmed Services YMCA of the USAAssociation of the United States ArmyCauseDisabled American VeteransFisher House FoundationHouse of HeroesInjured Marine Semper Fi FundOperation HomefrontOperation Welcome HomeParalyzed Veterans of AmericaPets for PatriotsPros 4 VetsQuality of Life PlusSpecial Operations Warrior FoundationTragedy Assistance Program for Survivors (TAPS)USOVietnam Veterans of AmericaWomen in Military Service for America MemorialWounded Warrior ProjectWreaths Across America SI Organization Inc., TheOperation First ResponseTrout Unlimited Wounded Warrior Program SNVCAurora Foundation, TheUSO Tellabs and Tellabs FoundationFisher House FoundationMarine Corps Scholarship Foundation Teradata CorporationFreedom AllianceHometown Heroes  VerizonUSO </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
