<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Know Your AFCEA Benefits: Get "LinkedIn"</title>
  <author>Helen Mosher, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>December 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>December 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Social networking has revolutionized the way that people interact both online and off. AFCEA offers many opportunities for its members to connect using these interactive platforms.</abstract>
  <text>Social networking has revolutionized the way that people interact both online and off. AFCEA offers many opportunities for its members to connect using these interactive platforms. Currently, the association features its own Facebook page and Twitter account. By utilizing both these tools, members and nonmembers can access AFCEA news, Professional Development Center course updates, scholarship alerts, SIGNAL Magazine articles, photos and more. In addition, AFCEA hosts a group on LinkedIn, the professional networking site that enables people to network and share news and links of interest with their colleagues and business acquaintances. Of all AFCEA’s social media sites, the AFCEA group on LinkedIn is the only online community where you must be an AFCEA member to join.Conversations flow in the AFCEA LinkedIn group in a way that they don’t elsewhere on the Web. Sometimes members share interesting articles they have read in the C4ISR space or interesting tips on succeeding in business. The association also is in the process of forming several subgroups—including one for chapter and regional officers that provides leaders and future leaders with a place to discuss ideas and best practices for running chapters and promoting chapter events. Discussions in this subgroup range from suggestions for fundraising events to registration links for chapter training webinars and calls for advice from fellow AFCEANs. Overall, the AFCEA members-only LinkedIn group features nearly 3,200 members. AFCEA looks up each and every individual who requests to join the LinkedIn group using his or her member number. As a result, it takes some time for the authentications to go be processed; however, this ensures a secure environment for important member discussions.If you experience any problem joining the group or have any questions regarding AFCEA’s social media offerings, please email New Media Editor Helen Mosher or call (703) 631-6196.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
