<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Postponement of NGEN RFP Not Likely to Delay Program Implementation</title>
  <author>Robert K. Ackerman, SIGNAL Online Exclusive</author>
  <date>December 15, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Online Exclusives</tag>
    <tag>December 2011</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Navy's rescheduling of the Next Generation Enterprise Network (NGEN) request for proposals (RFP) should not delay the program, according to a Navy official. After slating an RFP release for December 21, the Navy changed course and extended the RFP release date to sometime in late January 2012 at the earliest.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Navy’s rescheduling of the Next Generation Enterprise Network (NGEN) request for proposals (RFP) should not delay the program, according to a Navy official. After slating an RFP release for December 21, the Navy changed course and extended the RFP release date to sometime in late January 2012 at the earliest.Navy officials say that the reason for delaying the RFP is to update sections L and M. Section L deals with instructions, conditions and notices to offerors, while Section M addresses evaluation ratings. The updated sections, which will contain the latest revisions since the release of a draft RFP in September, are being released to industry for review and comment. The officials note that these changes came about as a result of industry input on the most recent draft RFP as well as from Navy internal reviews. Sections L and M had been focus areas emerging from that draft RFP, the officials relate. Because these two sections involve detailed instructions on how to construct a proposal, on acceptable thresholds and on evaluation factors, the Navy opted to clarify the points raised by industry and the Navy review. The officials add that these changes are an attempt by government to solidify requirements before the formal RFP is released.The Navy is emphasizing that this new RFP date will not change the overall schedule for the contract award and transition of the network from the Navy/Marine Corps Intranet (NMCI) to NGEN. More information on the NGEN program is available in "NGEN Race Heats Up," from the December 2011 issue of SIGNAL Magazine. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
