<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Launches First TechNet Land Forces Event</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>February 15, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>February 2012</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>“Operating and Defending the Cyberspace: Tomorrow’s Playbook” is the theme of the first of the TechNet Land Forces trio of events that have evolved from the previous LandWarNet conference.</abstract>
  <text>“Operating and Defending the Cyberspace: Tomorrow’s Playbook” is the theme of the first of the TechNet Land Forces trio of events that have evolved from the previous LandWarNet conference. Taking place at the Tucson Convention Center March 27-29, 2012, TechNet Land Forces Southwest–Network and Security Operations speakers and panels will focus on the ground component of the U.S. Army and Marine Corps.“While the Land Forces title highlights Army and Marine Corps organizations, this conference series will provide a forum for all Defense Department forces, along with joint, coalition partners, nongovernmental organizations and interagency organizations,” explains Mike Warlick, vice president for regional/chapter outreach and operations, AFCEA International. “It will highlight the operational security of the department and industry networks, operations and cyber operations. Additionally, government, industry and academia speakers will address a broad range of critical topics that focus on the challenges of working with the Defense Department and other organizations within the department.”Presentations and discussions at the March event will feature information about the interconnection among the military and homeland security, industry, academia and border control. They will examine the parallels between industry and the Defense Department in cyberspace defense, the impact of mobile communications on the battlefield and cyberwarrior training. Among the featured speakers at the TechNet Land Forces premiere is Lt. Gen. Susan S. Lawrence, USA, chief information officer/G-6, U.S. Army; Maj. Gen. Jennifer Napper, USA, commanding general, Network Enterprise Technology Command/9th Signal Command; and Brig. Gen. Kevin J. Nally, USMC, director, command, control, communications and computers/chief information officer, Marine Corps. In addition, Brig. Gen. David W. Coffman, USMC, former commanding officer, 13th Marine Expeditionary Unit, and currently assigned to the National Military Command Center, will speak, and Lt. Gen. Rhett A. Hernandez, USA, commanding general, U.S. Army Cyber Command/Second Army, has been invited to address conference attendees.Track sessions will offer information about the recruitment and retention of cyberwarriors, revolutionizing cybertraining and education, and the integration of operations and intelligence into the cyber battlespace. “Each event will have a different regional and operational focus,” Warlick explains. The second TechNet Land Forces event trio —TechNet Land Forces South–Joint and Coalition—takes place July 10-12, 2012, at the Tampa Convention Center, and the third—TechNet Land Forces East–Cyber—takes place at the Baltimore Convention Center, August 14-16, 2012.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
