<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Know Your AFCEA Benefits: Discounts on Hardware and Software</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>May 15, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>April 2012</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEANs receive deep discounts from Microsoft, Dell and HP as well as are eligible to join the Pentagon Federal Credit Union (PenFed), which offers member benefits of its own plus highly competitive interest rates on mortgages, auto loans and credit cards.</abstract>
  <text>If it’s time to upgrade a computer or refinance a loan, it’s time to take advantage of association member benefits. AFCEANs receive deep discounts from Microsoft, Dell and HP and are eligible to join the Pentagon Federal Credit Union (PenFed), which offers member benefits of its own plus highly competitive interest rates on mortgages, auto loans and credit cards.Depending on the product, AFCEANs can save hundreds of dollars on Microsoft software such as Office Professional Plus 2010 with Total Training, which is available for $89.95, a $450 savings. Microsoft Office Professional Plus 2010 is available for $79.95, a $420 savings. Mac owners also can realize savings on Microsoft Office 2011, which is priced at $84.95 through the AFCEA membership discount. Microsoft’s Creative Suite 5.5 Design Premium Student and Teacher Edition, which has a suggested retail price of $1,899, is available for less than $500, and the Creative Suite 5.5 Production Premium Student and Teacher Edition is $448, a savings of more than $1,200.In addition, AFCEA members are eligible for the HP Employee Purchase Program (EPP). The program offers up to 10 percent off starting prices of HP and Compaq products; national mail-in and instant rebates, coupons and exclusive EPP deals can be applied to the discounted prices. Products include configure-to-order notebooks and desktop computers, printers, handheld devices and home servers. Purchases can be made online or at (866) 433-2018.Dell offers AFCEANs a similar discount program, including the best price on all of the company’s commercial PCs. Laptops and desktop computers start at $350. Other electronics and accessories, including televisions, also are discounted an additional 10 percent.PenFed recently redesigned its website to make it more user-friendly. Members receive more than just competitive rates on loans, they also enjoy other benefits. For example, they are entitled to discounts on USAA financial services, long-term care insurance and auto services.To find out more about how much money your membership can save you, sign into the AFCEA member portal and click on the icons in the Computer Purchase and Other Benefits in the left column. You’ve invested in AFCEA, and the association’s benefits help you invest in your future.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
