<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>Personality Profile: Master Sgt. Paul Kammerman, USAF</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>May 15, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>May 2012</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Few people have the nerve to take on huge tasks and the stamina to see them through, but Master Sgt. Paul Kammerman, USAF, certainly is one of them.</abstract>
  <text>Few people have the nerve to take on huge tasks and the stamina to see them through, but Master Sgt. Paul Kammerman, USAF, certainly is one of them. From 19 years of marriage to 22 years in the U.S. Air Force to traveling on foot more than 37 miles in eight hours in Sarzana, Italy, Master Sgt. Kammerman demonstrates a stick-to-itiveness that truly is commendable. Perhaps it’s because he admires Dan Gable, an Olympic wrestler whose famous quote is “Once you’ve wrestled, everything else in life is easy.” But more likely, it’s because he comes from a family with several members who have defended the United States through their military service: a dad who was a missileer, one uncle who served as a radar technician and another uncle who was a military medical tech and went on to become a doctor. Examples like those may be hard to follow, but the master sergeant certainly has forged his own way in terms of accomplishments.The weekend volksmarching adventure in Italy is just one example he—and his wife—is unlikely to forget. “The location was especially appealing to us, because it was near the white marble quarry where the statue of David was carved,” Master Sgt. Kammerman explains. “Upon arrival, we were invited to join some seasoned older locals for a pasta/pizza meal and discuss what this run was all about; this turned out to be both good and bad. By the end of the meal, we were filled with enough calories to climb Mount Everest, which met our intentions. The bad? We were encouraged to run the entire 60 kilometers. After walking, running and even crawling for eight hours, we were both in so much pain we could hardly drive the car home. We learned to stick with the locals for the cuisine, but leave the extreme sports to the pros,” he quips.His dedication also applies to his thirst for knowledge. The master sergeant has an associate’s degree in electronics engineering technology and a bachelor’s degree in information systems technology; he is now pursuing a master’s degree in IT management.A member of the Tidewater Chapter, Master Sgt. Kammerman brings this perseverance to his participation in AFCEA as well. In addition to supporting events such as the Joint Warfighting Conference and the chapter’s recognition meetings, he is a member of a small team that implements the monthly member luncheon meetings, which comprise 21 sponsored tables and as many as 210 attendees.Master Sgt. Kammerman is the superintendent of the plans and resources flight for the 10th Intelligence Squadron, Joint Base Langley–Eustis, where he works with a team of 52 airmen and civilians. The team maintains the Air Force’s Sentinel-1 weapon system for U-2, Predator, Reaper and Global Hawk intelligence collection, processing, exploitation and dissemination in support of joint task force and combatant commanders.The master sergeant’s commitment to the Tidewater Chapter is motivated by how he has seen the association build ties between the military and civilian sectors and bridges between industry goals and the military’s focus, he says. “My current assignment in a communications logistics squadron supporting a DCGS [Distributed Common Ground System] C4ISR [command, control, communications, computers, intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance] enterprise has afforded me the opportunity to see firsthand how the military and the civilian technical companies drive each other to produce the best support possible to the troops on the ground. At the end of the day, it is about supporting the men and women in harm’s way,” Master Sgt. Kammerman states.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
