<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>National Intelligence Writing Contest Underway</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>May 15, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>May 2012</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA International and the Naval Intelligence Professionals (NIP) are sponsoring a national intelligence writing contest that offers a top prize of $3,000 and a three-year membership in both organizations.</abstract>
  <text>AFCEA International and the Naval Intelligence Professionals (NIP) are sponsoring a national intelligence writing contest that offers a top prize of $3,000 and a three-year membership in both organizations. Essays must propose the intelligence community’s priorities, how to enhance integration and how to bring about efficiencies in today’s tight budget environment. The deadline for entries is June 30, 2012.Two additional prizes will be awarded: second prize is $1,500 and third prize is $750; each of these awards also includes three-year memberships in both organizations.One goal of the contest is to encourage discussion of issues relevant to today’s intelligence and national security environment. Entrants can approach the topic from any relevant perspective, including strategic, operational and/or tactical. Submissions must be no more than 2,000 words in length and should be double-spaced using a minimum of 12-point font.Entries must be submitted by email with the subject line “NIWC Contest.” The body of the email must include the author’s name, mailing address, email address, telephone number and the exact title of the submission. The email must include two attachments: the author’s biography of no more than 50 words and the essay with a file name that reflects the essay’s title. To ensure anonymity during judging, the essay should NOT include the author’s name on any page; however, the title should be on each page. Graphics or illustrations are permitted but not necessary.A panel of intelligence professionals from the AFCEA Intelligence Committee and NIP will judge the submissions based on originality, strength of argument and recommendations as well as spelling, grammar, syntax and clarity. Winning essays may be published in SIGNAL Magazine and the NIP Quarterly.Additional information and guidelines are available online.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
