<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA Announces New Chairman</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>June 15, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>June 2012</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The AFCEA International board of directors elected Alfred Grasso, president and chief executive officer of The MITRE Corporation, to serve as the association’s chairman of the board.</abstract>
  <text>The AFCEA International board of directors elected Alfred Grasso, president and chief executive officer of The MITRE Corporation, to serve as the association’s chairman of the board. In this position, Grasso will oversee the association’s Executive and Compensation committees as well as participate on the AFCEA Educational Foundation’s board of directors.Grasso has been an AFCEA member for more than a decade and has served as the vice chairman of the board for the past two years. In addition, he has been a member of the association’s Audit and Government committees and most recently as the co-chairman of the Budget and Finance Committee.As president and chief executive officer of MITRE, Grasso develops and leads the nonprofit corporation’s strategic and business operations for five federally funded research and development centers. He was appointed to the Defense Science Board in 2010 and is a special adviser to the U.S. Strategic Command’s Strategic Advisory Group. As the president of the National GEM Consortium’s board of directors, Grasso leads the nonprofit organization in its work to promote the participation of under-represented groups in science, technology, engineering and mathematics careers.Kent Schneider, AFCEA International’s president and chief executive officer, praises Grasso as a talented and accomplished leader in the global security community “whose guiding hand will be critical as we seek to contribute in a period of global unrest and economic challenge.”</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
