<article>
  <type>article</type>
  <title>AFCEA POCs: It's Time to Update Your Corporate Profile</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor, SIGNAL Connections</author>
  <date>August 15, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Connections</tag>
    <tag>August 2012</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>This month, all AFCEA corporate member points of contact (POCs) will receive a package that includes their current corporate profile and details about how to update this information.</abstract>
  <text>This month, all AFCEA corporate member points of contact (POCs) will receive a package that includes their current corporate profile and details about how to update this information. Only profiles that have been reviewed since January 1, 2012, will be included in full in the January 2013 Source Book issue of SIGNAL Magazine. All others will include only a company’s name and contact information. To review, update and approve a corporate profile, the organization's AFCEA POCs log into the portal with their AFCEA membership number and password. Corporate POC Tools are located in the column on the left. Click on Update Corporate Profile, then either on "Approve Corporate Profile As Is" or "Update Profile Write-up and Categories." Clicking on the latter leads to the profile in an editable format. Tips about writing an effective profile are available online.In addition, companies now have the opportunity to increase the attention their online corporate profiles receive through the Premium Packages Program. Packages include priority placement in the search results page, keyword searches that add direct links to the company's site within the profile, and affordable online and print advertising. Instructions for user name and password assistance are on the portal. For answers about the AFCEA 2013 Source Book, Online Directories and Premium Packages Program, please contact Maryann Lawlor at mlawlor@afcea.org or (703) 631-6179.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
