<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Culture Must Promote Purpose</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>March 1, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Incoming</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Tech-savvy younger workers from Generation Y are accustomed to easy, speedy access to information. In the not-too-distant future, late Boomers and even Generation X workers will have to adapt to the ways that work force culture is changing as a result of this incoming generation's influence. This month's Incoming column examines howrganizations are faced with the challenge to remain relevant, but must do so in a way that makes change a positive asset.

In the column, Lt. Gen. Harry D. Raduege Jr., USAF (Ret.), writes:
In coming years Generation Y will dominate the workplace, and its characteristics will influence and change the culture of the work force. Generation Y is considered a significant attribute to today's global economy-the most diverse and educated generation to date and generally very accepting of different races and ethnicities. This group enjoys opportunities to be creative, collaborative and innovative, and it seeks exciting and challenging experiences. This work force is naturally competitive but focused on meeting mission goals.

While only at the cusp of the advancing technological era, members of Generation Y are "tech savvy," expect access to information and want it with speed and accuracy. This generation is not satisfied with the passive attributes of information sharing. Its members proactively obtain information based on their emergent knowledge and solution requirements. Generation Y also leverages technology to create social networks that embrace open communication. Information originates from vast networks and cyber "networks of networks" of people, most of whom will never meet in person.

Our nation's secret weapon for future success will be the Generation Y work force. We need to learn more about, embrace and benefit from the powerful characteristics of this dynamic emerging generation. Successful leaders will recognize that our future lies with Generation Y, with intergenerational harmonization and by ensuring that an organization's culture is focused on achieving organizational purpose.

The entire column is here.

So, with that in mind, here's this month's question for discussion:

In what ways do today's leaders and employers need to change organizational culture to merge the best talents of three generations into one diverse but unified workforce?</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
