<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Snail Mail by Email with Motomail</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>July 1, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Friends and family members of U.S. Marines deployed to an operational location in Iraq can send their loved ones a message without ever visiting the mailbox. MotoMail aims to bridge gaps in communications between parties who may not have e-mail access or who just want to send a physical letter for a more personal touch. MotoMail, in conjunction with SuperLetter.com Incorporated, operates a Web site that allows users to create a message online that will be downloaded and printed out at a Marine Corps post office then physically delivered to the deployed Marine. MotoMail messages are downloaded at least once a day in the operational theaters, and the organization strives to deliver all letters within 24 hours of printing. The Delivery Status feature enables senders to keep track of their messages through the three delivery stages-Stage 1: received at the MotoMail server; Stage 2: letters downloaded to the MotoMail terminal; and Stage 3: letters have been printed and sent for delivery. The service is provided at no cost. While the service is geared largely toward Marines, troops in other military branches who are collocated with the Marine Corps can receive the mail as well. MotoMail also offers two-way services so troops can send letters back home by creating an account on MotoMail using credit cards. Letters are sent to a regional SuperLetter office determined by the first digit of the destination zip code for printing. Postage is applied, and the mail is placed in the U.S. Postal Service system. Troops can send up to five letters for free, and all additional messages cost 50 cents. Users can create accounts on the Web site as well as find answers to frequently asked questions and other resources. The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
