<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>AFCEA International announces new leaders</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>July 10, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>What's New</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Mr. Paul Cofoni, President and Chief Executive Officer, CACI International, Inc, and Ms. Natalie Givans, Vice President, Booz Allen Hamilton, have been elected to lead AFCEA International. Mr. Cofoni will serve as Chairman of the Board and Ms. Givans will serve as the first Vice Chairman of the Board.</abstract>
  <text>Mr. Paul Cofoni, President and Chief Executive Officer, CACI International, Inc, and Ms. Natalie Givans, Vice President, Booz Allen Hamilton, have been elected to lead AFCEA International. Mr. Cofoni will serve as Chairman of the Board and Ms. Givans will serve as the first Vice Chairman of the Board.

Mr. Cofoni has been a long time member of AFCEA and has served over five years on the Association's Executive Committee and Board. He succeeds The Honorable Duane Andrews, Chief Executive Officer, QinetiQ North America, in this position. As Chairman of the AFCEA International Board of Directors, Mr. Cofoni will chair the Association's Executive Committee and Compensation Committee and participate on the AFCEA Educational Foundation Board of Directors.

As President and Chief Executive Officer, Mr. Cofoni's responsibilities include executing CACI's strategy to align its core competencies, innovative tools, and best-value solutions to help the U.S. government solve its most important problems in protecting our nation and winning the global war on terrorism. Mr. Cofoni has more than 30 years of senior-level executive experience in business development, M&amp;A, strategic planning, and extensive federal market operations. His professional experience includes large-scale integrator contracts in the broad federal market sector; the defense, intelligence, and communications markets; and major commercial outsourcing and systems markets.

Ms. Natalie Givans is a life time member of AFCEA, joining in 1986. She has been active in the AFCEA NOVA chapter, serving on the Programs Committee and participating in the Young AFCEAN events as an invited speaker and mentor in recent years. She served on the Board of Directors for the AFCEA International Building Services Committee and on the Board of Directors for AFCEA International. In the past year, Ms. Givans served on the AFCEA Educational Foundation and has been active on the Diversity and Strategic Development Committees. She has been elected to serve as the first-ever Vice Chairman of AFCEA International, where she will report to the Chairman of the Board and will chair the Budget and Finance Committee.

Ms. Givans has more than 24 years of experience in system security engineering, information and mission assurance, and communications, information, and transmission security. She began her career at Booz Allen Hamilton providing engineering and analysis for the KG-84A Implementation program and developing signaling plans for the STU-III program. Today, she leads Booz Allen Hamilton's Department of Defense information and system Assurance and Resilience (A&amp;R) capability team, with over 750 subject matter experts nationwide, providing cyber defense and secure solutions to the Warfighter and the Federal Government. Her personal focus is on enterprise wide security architectures, solutions, and cyber defense. Ms. Givans was an active member of the System Security Engineering Capability Maturity Model (SSE-CMM) project, focused on ensuring that security is integrated into all acquisition and systems development lifecycles from their conception. 

"AFCEA is honored to have Mr. Cofoni and Ms. Givans as its leaders," says AFCEA International President and Chief Executive Officer Mr. Kent Schneider. "Their leadership and expertise in the C4I community is well-known, and their service to AFCEA is beyond measure. The Association's future is bright with these individuals at the helm."

For more information, including comments from and background on Mr. Cofoni and Ms. Givans, click here.
</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
