<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Incoming: The Patterns of Data Management</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>August 1, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Incoming</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>In this month's Incoming column, Lt. Gen. Harry D. Raduege Jr., USAF (Ret.) talks about how management of data is so important. He looks at it from the enterprise level, discussion trends in how organizations can streamline data management operations through consolidation of data centers. While the trend is interesting to discuss, it brings up another interesting point: Individuals are just as likely to need "data management" skills these days, what with the incredible amount of information that flows through their email in-boxes and feed readers. So, for discussion this month: How much is too much information, and how do you manage it all?</abstract>
  <text>In this month's Incoming column, Lt. Gen. Harry D. Raduege Jr., USAF (Ret.) talks about how management of data is so important. He looks at it from the enterprise level, discussion trends in how organizations can streamline data management operations through consolidation of data centers:

"It's all about the data" is a popular expression today. More and more, we've come to realize that data is the central building block for protecting, processing, sharing and storing information. And, as government and industry data owners learn to believe in these realities, they quite often decide to establish their own data centers to maintain control. On the surface, this might easily seem like the right thing to do, but it isn't always the best course to achieve effective consolidation. Being aware of data center consolidation experience and realities can save organizations large sums of money and improve operations.

You can read his entire piece here. But while the trend is interesting to discuss (and we'd welcome your comments on that as well), it brings up another interesting point: Individuals are just as likely to need "data management" skills these days, what with the incredible amount of information that flows through their email in-boxes and feed readers. So, for discussion this month: How much is too much information, and how do you manage it all?

Please share your thoughts in the comments, or discuss it on your blog with a link back to us. We'd love to hear from you! </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
