<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Gifts to Army </title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>August 19, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The overwhelming interest and generosity of the American public toward U.S. soldiers and their families prompted the Army to launch Gifts to Army as a centralized source of information for contribution and support opportunities. The Army Gift Program is an established effort, but an amendment to the law now enables the Army to accept donations that assist wounded soldiers, wounded civilian employees and their families. The goal of Gifts to Army is to answer the frequent question from the public: "What can I do to help?"</abstract>
  <text>The overwhelming interest and generosity of the American public toward U.S. soldiers and their families prompted the Army to launch Gifts to Army as a centralized source of information for contribution and support opportunities. The Army Gift Program is an established effort, but an amendment to the law now enables the Army to accept donations that assist wounded soldiers, wounded civilian employees and their families. The goal of Gifts to Army is to answer the frequent question from the public: "What can I do to help?" Rather than solicit funds, the Web site intends to inform individuals, organizations and corporations how they can donate cash, goods and services to benefit the Army community, although the site does accept online contributions. Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation (MWR) programs will process general unsolicited funds for use in Army programs. A list of supported programs as well as ideas for how much certain organizations or individuals could donate and what the money will do is available online. Site visitors can learn more about MWR programs under the "Soldiers and Families" and "Army Installations" links, with information about specific posts under the latter. There is also a "Wounded Warriors" link with information on how the Army cares for injured heroes and how the public can participate in those programs. The Gifts to Army site gives detailed information about contributing to soldier support efforts and contact information for certain programs and coordinators. Under the "How to Contribute" link, the Army instructs donors to submit written donation offers that include the value, cost to the Army and any associated conditions. The offer will be submitted to the installation or organization that will receive or manage the contribution. The section also includes points of contact for people with questions. More information about giving to Army support programs is available on the site, including an FAQ, Community Support and Other Links sections.  The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
