<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Creating Futures</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>September 24, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Service Providers</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Creating Futures offers transitioning U.S. veterans as well as individuals with disabilities, at-risk youth and dislocated workers opportunities to build careers in the information technology field. Creating Futures works with employers to identify needs and then trains individuals to fill those capabilities gaps, placing candidates in long-term jobs. The education and training programs help students obtain the technical, business and communications skills employers want.

Run through the CompTIA Educational Foundation, the program offers several online courses: CompTIA A+, CompTIA Network+, CompTIA Server+ and CompTIA Security+. The training is provided at no cost to students. Candidates are screened and notified of their acceptance into the program via e-mail.

Individuals interested in the program can fill out the application online, and employers interested in interviewing Creating Futures students for job opportunities also can submit an online form. Completing the form does not commit a company to hire anyone but demonstrates an interest in interviewing candidates or potentially hiring Creating Futures students. Additional contact information is available on the Web site for interested organizations.

Also listed online is information about donating to the program. Creating Futures accepts financial and in-kind support such as monetary gifts, donation of classroom/training seating, contributions of training materials, receipt of on-the-job-training or internships, and consideration of candidates for employment within an organization. Interested parties can donate online or by phone, fax or mail. A list with explanations of alternate donation options, such as matching gift programs and planned giving, is posted as well. 

The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
