<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Military HOMEFRONT</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>September 26, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Service Providers</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Military HOMEFRONT is the official U.S. Defense Department online resource for reliable quality-of-life information for the military community. The site has sections for troops and families, leadership and service providers so all aspects of military life are covered, from basic military needs to broader topics such as parenting and financial readiness.</abstract>
  <text>Military HOMEFRONT is the official U.S. Defense Department online resource for reliable quality-of-life information for the military community. The site has sections for troops and families, leadership and service providers so all aspects of military life are covered, from basic military needs to broader topics such as parenting and financial readiness. Troops can obtain information about various subjects, including permanent change of station moves as well as legislation and policies. The site also links to other organizations prevalent in the military community and explains special offers available to those who serve their country. An updated Survivor's Guide to Benefits (PDF), current as of July 28, is available for families whose loved ones have made the ultimate sacrifice, and other casualty assistance resources are posted as well.

In addition to offering resources, the site includes news items relevant to the military that range from information about recently revised troop support Web pages to new benefits that are available. Site visitors can find even more assistance by using the "MySTATE" feature to explore offerings in their place of residence. Individuals can sign up to receive newsletters from Military HOMEFRONT to keep abreast of the latest news, and they can use the toolbox feature to personalize the site for their needs. 


The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
