<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Wounded Warrior Resource Center</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>November 4, 2008</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The U.S. Defense Department, through Military OneSource, has established a Wounded Warrior Resource Center (WWRC) telephone number and e-mail address. Troops, veterans and their families can call (800) 342-9647 or send a message to wwrc@militaryonesource.com to request support if they have concerns or difficulties during the recovery process. Both methods of contact are operational 24/7.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Defense Department, through Military OneSource, has established a Wounded Warrior Resource Center (WWRC) telephone number and e-mail address. Troops, veterans and their families can call (800) 342-9647 or send a message to wwrc@militaryonesource.com to request support if they have concerns or difficulties during the recovery process. Both methods of contact are operational 24/7. Additional phone numbers are available for those who need help in Spanish or require a TTY/TDD connection. Military community members also can request to contact a consultant in a specific field, get counseling information or join discussion boards. Those telephone numbers and features are posted on the Military OneSource site. The resource center does not replace specialized wounded warrior programs established by the military service branches but augments that assistance for military facilities, health care services and benefits information. According to the Defense Department announcement of the center's opening, "Specially trained consultants will ensure consistent, quality customer-centric support. The consultants will identify the appropriate 'warm hand-off' to either a military service or federal agency with authority to resolve the matter. The resource center consultant will maintain communication with the caller until the issue or concern is resolved." The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
