<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Freedom Alliance</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>February 3, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>"The price of liberty is eternal vigilance." So reads the slogan of Freedom Alliance which directs all the organization's efforts. The charitable and educational foundation was founded by Lt. Col. Oliver North, USMC (Ret.), who said from the beginning that the goal would be to work to "keep America strong, keep America prosperous and keep America free." The mission of Freedom Alliance is to advance the American heritage of freedom by honoring and encouraging military service, defending the sovereignty of the United States and promoting a strong national defense.</abstract>
  <text>"The price of liberty is eternal vigilance." So reads the slogan of Freedom Alliance, which directs all the organization's efforts. The charitable and educational foundation was founded by Lt. Col. Oliver North, USMC (Ret.), who said from the beginning that the goal would be to work to "keep America strong, keep America prosperous and keep America free." The mission of Freedom Alliance is to advance the American heritage of freedom by honoring and encouraging military service, defending the sovereignty of the United States and promoting a strong national defense. Freedom Alliance carries out its mission in several ways. The organization cares for wounded veterans currently in hospitals by sending them desired resources as well as paying travel and lodging expenses for their families. Military families grieving the loss of a loved one also can reach out to Freedom Alliance for help and support. Other outreach efforts include educating the public on how to become involved citizenry through methods such as contacting elected officials and writing letters to the editor. Additional Web offerings include a column by Col. North, a link to the radio show of Freedom Alliance's president Tom Kilgannon and issues of Freedom Alliance Review. The organization also runs a scholarship program for dependent children of active duty service members who died or were permanently disabled in the line of duty, or who currently are certified as POW or MIA. Complete qualification guidelines and the application are available online. To further its ideals of a strong America in the future, Freedom Alliance runs the Military Leadership Academy. High school students attend to gain leadership abilities through mental and physical challenges based on U.S. Army curriculum. Students also tour historical sites and military bases. The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
