<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Defense Industry Stimulus Will Benefit the Economy</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>February 13, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>west2009</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Providing economic stimulus to the defense sector could be a key part of revitalizing the U.S. economy, said Linda Mills, corporate vice president and president, Northrop Grumman Information Systems Sector. Mills urged that the government take the defense industry into account as it stimulates the economy to keep and create jobs.</abstract>
  <text>Linda Mills, corporate vice president and president, Northrop Grumman Information Systems Sector, describes how important the defense industry is to the economy.Providing economic stimulus to the defense sector could be a key part of revitalizing the U.S. economy, said Linda Mills, corporate vice president and president, Northrop Grumman Information Systems Sector. Mills urged that the government take the defense industry into account as it stimulates the economy to keep and create jobs.

Defense is going to be significantly affected by our current economic crisis, Mills stated. She discussed whether it would suffer or benefit from the economic stimulus, and she pointed out that almost all of the military's equipment is made in the United States. And, defense spending often is the catalyst for enduring economic benefits.

Mills singled out C4ISR systems as being essential regardless of the direction in defense spending. There always will be demand for top C4ISR and cyber capabilities, which she likened to the five senses of the human nervous system in importance to the military.

However, she also warned about the country's dependence on networks. The nation's military and commercial networks must be reliably and predictably available and secure, and the threat to these networks cannot be overstated. Mills called for government leadership to unite all aspects of information technology industry in synergistic cooperation on security measures and practices.

</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
