<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DHS Undersecretary for Management Outlines Priorities</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>February 25, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homeland 2009</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Elaine Duke, undersecretary for management, U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS), opened AFCEA's Homeland Security Conference in Washington, DC, with both encouragement and advice for the commercial sector. The department is looking forward to partnering with industry; however, under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act, companies can expect more government oversight during acquisitions.
</abstract>
  <text>Elaine Duke, undersecretary for management, U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS), opened AFCEA's Homeland Security Conference in Washington, DC, with both encouragement and advice for the commercial sector. The department is looking forward to partnering with industry; however, under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act, companies can expect more government oversight during acquisitions.

Duke spoke about the department's five action directives, pointing out that the common theme is a review of the past, a look at the present and a plan future of the DHS. This appraisal will include taking a look at the department's strengths and weaknesses. Some of the action directives include national protection; cyber security; United States' northern borders security; integration of work among FEMA, state and local agencies; and a review initiative that will look at improving the DHS' efficiency.

After sharing some of the specific dollar amounts various DHS agencies received through the Recovery and Reinvestment Act, Duke pointed out that the theme throughout is that it highlights programs and needs that often are not in the limelight. These include additional facilities as well as improving existing facilities.

"Regarding the Recovery Act, [President] Obama is serious about accountability and visibility as we spend these dollars. Many of the issues in the act will require industry to adapt," Duke stated. Ensuring spending visibility will create new requirements, and companies that plan to work with the government should make themselves aware of them, she advised.

In terms of restructuring DHS acquisition and procurement, Duke pointed out that because the department stood up so quickly, it adopted the U.S. Defense Department's model in these areas. However, because DHS more often purchases services rather than items such as ships and aircraft, this model must be revised. DHS is now reconfiguring its acquisition processes to better reflect its procurement needs, she said.
</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
