<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Face of America 2009</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>March 4, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Benefit Events</tag>
    <tag>Supporting Our Veterans</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Dust off those bikes, take them out of the garage and get rolling for a great cause! Face of America 2009 begins April 25 in Bethesda, Maryland, to raise awareness of service members injured in the line of duty. The 110-mile bike ride, which ends April 26 in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, also raises funds for World TEAM (The Exceptional Athlete Matters) Sports, an organization that strives to increase awareness, acceptance and integration of people with disabilities through sports.</abstract>
  <text>Dust off those bikes, take them out of the garage and get rolling for a great cause! Face of America 2009 begins April 25 in Bethesda, Maryland, to raise awareness of service members injured in the line of duty. The 110-mile bike ride, which ends April 26 in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, also raises funds for World TEAM (The Exceptional Athlete Matters) Sports, an organization that strives to increase awareness, acceptance and integration of people with disabilities through sports. Face of America focuses specifically on disabled veterans by reaching out and actively including troops who have been severely injured in Iraq and Afghanistan. The ride honors wounded warriors by using sports to help integrate them back into society. World TEAM Sports wants to thank these young men and women for their service and also let them know that they still can be active members of the TEAM. The event focuses on meeting challenges, promoting camaraderie and developing the lasting knowledge that all of the participants are integral members of society. The group works with several other organizations including Soldiers' Angels, the Injured Semper Fi Foundation, and service members from military hospitals and installations around the country to put on the ride. Any service member-injured or otherwise-who wants to ride is invited to participate for free. Anyone else who wants to join in can register online at www.worldteamsports.org. Service members and sponsors also can attend the kick-off dinner the night of April 24. Civilians must pay a $50 registration fee and raise a minimum of $600 in donations. All registrations must be in by April 23 at 8:59 PDT. Additional information, including instructions on what to bring, where to stay, how to sign up as a team captain, schedule, links to registration and more, is available on the Web site. The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
