<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Commission Assesses Cyberspace and Recommends Security Measures</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>March 5, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>TechNet Tampa 2009</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>This morning at TechNet Tampa 2009, Lt. Gen. Harry D. Raduege, Jr., USAF (Ret.), a member of the Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS) Commission on Cybersecurity for the 44th Presidency, presented findings and recommendations from the commission's report Securing Cyberspace for the 44th Presidency, released last December.  The report had three major findings: cybersecurity is now a major national security problem for the United States; decisions and actions must respect privacy and personal liberties; and only a comprehensive national security strategy that embraces domestic and international aspects of cyberspace will improve the situation.

The commission made 25 recommendations for improving cyberspace operations, several of which Gen. Raduege discussed in his presentation. These include creating a Comprehensive National Security Strategy for Cyberspace; partnering with the private sector; regulating cybersecurity; using acquisition rules to improve security; revising the Federal Information Security Management Act; conducting training for cybereducation and workforce development; and conducting research and development.

Changes are necessary to improve the state of cyberspace today. Gen. Raduege said estimates put the loss of intellectual property in cyberspace each year at $1 trillion. Other problems incude the breach of 45,000 Federal Aviation Administration employees' information last month. In addition, cyberattacks against the United States and other countries continue to increase, resulting in sensitive information being stolen and comprised.

The commission's complete report can be downloaded at http://www.csis.org/component/option,com_csis_pubs/task,view/id,5157/.

Additional SIGNAL coverage is available at http://www.afcea.org/signal/articles/anmviewer.asp?a=1815.

 

 

http://www.afcea.org/signal/articles/anmviewer.asp?a=1815&amp;print=yes</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
