<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Operation: Birthday Cake</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>March 24, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Want to do something sweet for deployed service members? How about sending them a gourmet cake from Bake Me A Wish! In partnership with Soldiers' Angels, Bake Me A Wish offers two ways for folks stateside to send a special treat to troops in combat areas. The first is by purchasing The Freedom Cake, which features a layer of chocolate brownie covered with fudge frosting and topped with sprinkles and bittersweet chocolate shavings.</abstract>
  <text>Want to do something sweet for deployed service members? How about sending them a gourmet cake from Bake Me A Wish! In partnership with Soldiers' Angels, Bake Me A Wish offers two ways for folks stateside to send a special treat to troops in combat areas. The first is by purchasing The Freedom Cake, which features a layer of chocolate brownie covered with fudge frosting and topped with sprinkles and bittersweet chocolate shavings. For each Freedom Cake purchased, an identical cake will be sent to a warfighter overseas in the name of the cake recipient. The Freedom Cakes include cards, alongside U.S. flag imprints, to the recipients explaining that other cakes have been sent to military members in their names.

Loved ones also can send cakes to their specific, special military member by choosing a cake from those listed on the Web site. Five percent of the order will be contributed to Operation: Birthday Cake. Bake Me A Wish can only accept "requested" delivery dates for these cakes. It takes approximately 10 to 14 days for the baked goods to reach their destination.

Anyone who would like to make a donation to Operation: Birthday Cake or ask a question can contact Bake Me A Wish at this link.


The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
