<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>AFCEA Intelligence Announces New Writing Contests</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>May 18, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>AFCEA</tag>
    <tag>Contests</tag>
    <tag>Intelligence</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA Intelligence and the Naval Intelligence Professionals/Naval Intelligence Foundation (NIP/NIF) have joined forces to sponsor two annual writing contests. The contests provide intelligence professionals with opportunities to express themselves on topics of importance to the Intelligence Community and national security. </abstract>
  <text>AFCEA Intelligence and the Naval Intelligence Professionals/Naval Intelligence Foundation (NIP/NIF) have joined forces to sponsor two annual writing contests.

The contests provide intelligence professionals with opportunities to express themselves on topics of importance to the Intelligence Community and national security. 

In the AFCEA 2009 Essay Contest, on "Safety, Security, and Privacy, respondents are asked to address the following problem statement:

As the internal threat from terrorism has increased, the U.S. government has employed new and different methods to collect intelligence to forestall future attacks on U.S. soil. Discuss the implications of these actions on Constitutional guarantees of privacy for U.S. citizens versus the government's imperative to provide safety and security.  Include recommendations as to how this balance can be better maintained.

Top prize is $2,000 and a two-year AFCEA membership. More information on the contest, including deadline and eligibility, is available here.

The Naval Intelligence 2009 Essay Contest is sponsored by the Naval Intelligence Foundation, Naval Intelligence Professionals, and AFCEA, and underwritten in part by the Inman Foundation. Entrants can write about any subject pertaining to Naval Intelligence or intelligence support to naval forces.

Top prize includes $1,000, a five year membership in the Naval Intelligence and a two-year membership in AFCEA.  More information on the contest, including deadline and eligibility, is available here.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
