<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Military Family Support Centers Incorporated</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>June 17, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Family Resources</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Military families requiring just about any kind of help-from supplies to camaraderie-can find what they need here. Military Family Support Centers (MFSC) Incorporated, located in Salem, Virginia, is dedicated to identifying and meeting the needs of the families of deployed military members. The organization seeks to reduce the stress for troops and their families by providing ways for the community to express its gratitude through offering services, volunteering or making donations.</abstract>
  <text>Military families requiring just about any kind of help-from supplies to camaraderie-can find what they need here. Military Family Support Centers (MFSC) Incorporated, located in Salem, Virginia, is dedicated to identifying and meeting the needs of the families of deployed military members. The organization seeks to reduce the stress for troops and their families by providing ways for the community to express its gratitude through offering services, volunteering or making donations.

MFSC offers an array of support including an information clearinghouse for military and civilian programs and benefits; telecommunications support such as videoconferencing, free long-distance and broadband Internet access; social interaction through support group organization assistance and a casual meeting place staffed by caring volunteers; home/car repair assistance offering reduced and no-cost repairs by qualified volunteers; a playroom for children to use while parents handle other issues; collaboration with local charities that provide food and clothing; transportation assistance; counseling; a limited amount of in-house baby supplies and canned goods; and TRICARE insurance assistance.

The organization seeks volunteers to assist with its outreach efforts, and it solicits donations as well as sells items to raise money. More information and necessary forms are available on the Web site. Also available online is news about upcoming events, a newsletter, support links and contact information, including directions to the office. Anyone who needs assistance or knows of a military family who could benefit through MFSC's help is encouraged to contact the organization by phone or e-mail or can drop by. The center has operating hours listed, but appointments can be made for other times as well.


The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
