<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Modeling and Simulation Links</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>July 24, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Modeling</tag>
    <tag>Simulations</tag>
    <tag>Internet Works</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>In this wired and increasingly virtual world, modeling and simulation play a key role in everything from testing new products to developing weapons systems and planning military operations. Although simulations have been important for decades, new technologies enable researchers and engineers to model software and hardware accurately down to the molecular level. </abstract>
  <text>In this wired and increasingly virtual world, modeling and simulation play a key role in everything from testing new products to developing weapons systems and planning military operations. Although simulations have been important for decades, new technologies enable researchers and engineers to model software and hardware accurately down to the molecular level. Many research organizations also have a presence on the World Wide Web, which serves as both a medium and a means to experience and access research and testing data.

Defense Department Modeling and Simulation Coordination Office (M&amp;SCO)

The M&amp;SCO coordinates and synchronizes modeling and simulation activities across the U.S. Defense Department. The M&amp;SCO's home page outlines the office's policy and guidance practices, resource discovery processes and modeling and simulation standards. Visitors can access the Defense Department's standards vetting tool, which is designed to automate the online submission, storage, tracking, evaluation and distribution of proposed modeling and simulation standards. 

U.S. Air Force Agency for Modeling and Simulation (AFAMS)

As the lead Air Force agency for integrating live, virtual and constructive capabilities to support warfighters, AFAMS's mission is to ensure the appropriate representation of air, space and cyberspace in modeling and simulation. The agency is responsible for integrating and maintaining the interoperability of Air Force modeling and simulations, for coordinating Air Force modeling and simulation support for joint, interagency and coalition events and for developing and maintaining appropriate skills and knowledge for the service's personnel. 

U.S. Army Modeling and Simulation

Like its Air Force counterpart, the Army's Modeling and Simulation Directorate coordinates, integrates, guides and synchronizes modeling and simulation efforts across the service. The directorate also is responsible for meeting the Army's strategic objectives to address modeling and simulation capability gaps; supporting the modeling and simulation enterprise across the service; developing a dedicated data program; conducting joint, interagency and multinational engagement; and developing a trained work force. The home page provides links to training courses, career development tools, acronym lists, and access to modeling and simulation collaboration sites (note that an Army Knowledge Online login is required to access the collaboration pages). 

U.S. Navy Modeling and Simulation Office (NMSO)

The role of the NMSO is to coordinate Navy modeling and simulation efforts. Working closely with the U.S. Marine Corps Modeling and Simulation Management Office, the NMSO is the lead organization for Navy policy, standards and initiatives relating to modeling and simulation. The home page provides a variety of information such as resource lists of organizations, data sources, models and simulations, references and documents. Additional material is available through the site's test and evaluation community workspace and toolset guides. 

DIESIS

The goal of the Design of an Interoperable European Federated Simulation Network for Critical Infrastructures (DIESIS) project is to analyze Europe's interdependent network of critical infrastructures for potential weaknesses. Bringing together experts from Germany, Italy, the Netherlands and the United Kingdom, the project is designing a platform to support interoperable simulations and research focused on infrastructure protection. The DIESIS home page provides details about the project, program roadmaps, publications and participating organizations such as the Fraunhofer Institute for Intelligent Analysis and Information Systems, the Imperial College London, and the Italian National Agency for New Technologies. 

NATO Modeling and Simulation Group (NMSG)

A part of NATO's Research and Technology Organisation, the NMSG mission is to promote cooperation among alliance organizations, NATO member nations and Partnership for Peace nations to use modeling and simulation effectively. The NMSG site links to related information such as a code of ethics for developing simulations, interoperability standards, the NATO simulation resources library and the NATO Modeling and Simulation Standards Subgroup. Visitors can access a list of related documents examining subjects such as integrating modeling and simulation to support training and interoperability, experimentation through simulation and defining frameworks for simulation resources reusability. 
</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
