<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>AFCEA Intelligence Sponsors Two Essay Contests</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>August 12, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>AFCEA News</tag>
    <tag>Intelligence</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>AFCEA Intelligence and the Naval Intelligence Professionals/Naval Intelligence Foundation (NIP/NIF) have joined forces to sponsor two writing contests. The contests provide intelligence professionals with opportunities to express themselves on topics of importance to the Intelligence Community and national security.  </abstract>
  <text>AFCEA Intelligence and the Naval Intelligence Professionals/Naval Intelligence Foundation (NIP/NIF) have joined forces to sponsor two writing contests. The contests provide intelligence professionals with opportunities to express themselves on topics of importance to the Intelligence Community and national security.

The 2009 AFCEA Intelligence Essay Contest is on the following topic:

 Collecting Intelligence: Balancing Safety, Security, and Privacy

Problem Statement: As the internal threat from terrorism has increased, the U.S. government has employed new and different methods to collect intelligence to forestall future attacks on U.S. soil. Discuss the implications of these actions on Constitutional guarantees of privacy for U.S. citizens versus the government's imperative to provide safety and security.  Include recommendations as to how this balance can be better maintained.

Top prize is $2,000 and a 2-year membership in AFCEA. Other prizes and additional information are here.

Entries for the 2009 Naval Intelligence Essay Contest should be on any subject pertaining to Naval Intelligence or intelligence support to naval forces.

This annual contest is sponsored by the Naval Intelligence Foundation, Naval Intelligence Professionals, and AFCEA, and underwritten in part by the Inman Foundation.

Prize and eligibility requirements are here.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
