<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Games and Maps and Music--Oh My!</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>December 2, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Apps</tag>
    <tag>Web 2.0</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>As the iPhone continues to increase in fame and popularity, the applications to fill up the device are growing in number and diversity. Whether people are looking for utility or nonsense, the options are almost endless. Featured here are some offbeat iPhone applications and their Web sites as well as sites to learn more about available offerings and what people are using. And just in case the applications seem overwhelming, one Web site offers an organization solution. </abstract>
  <text>As the iPhone continues to increase in fame and popularity, the applications to fill up the device are growing in number and diversity. Whether people are looking for utility or nonsense, the options are almost endless. Featured here are some offbeat iPhone applications and their Web sites as well as sites to learn more about available offerings and what people are using. And just in case the applications seem overwhelming, one Web site offers an organization solution. 

Yappler.com Sync
Sync is an iPhone application that enhances the use of other applications. It enables users to organize their applications and share them with friends. By employing Sync, iPhone owners can create a list of all their other applications, send the list to friends (on the new iPhone), show friends which applications they like best, share the list through social media sites such as Twitter and Facebook, share the list through e-mail, embed the list in blogs and other places, and automatically update their lists. Downloading is free for Windows and Mac 10.5+ users, and a link for the download is prominently placed on the Web page.

The Sync site includes a video originally posted on YouTube that explains how the application works and how to install it. By clicking links on the Sync page, visitors can access the main Yappler site, which has a variety of other application offerings. Visitors also can ask questions, obtain help or provide feedback. Another interesting feature is the Stats page (accessible through a tab at the top of the Sync page), which has statistics on iPhone applications, including the total number of applications available for the device and various cost and price breakdowns.

1Password
Installing this application is like having a safe in your pocket, or so the manufacturers claim. 1Password and 1Password Pro allow users to save Web site login credentials, freeform secure notes, personal identity information and passwords in one secure location protected by a four-digit unlock code and a master password. It also has the ability to download data to Mac or PC desktops so users can back up all their information and restore it if necessary. The application is available for iPhone and iPod Touch. The Web site includes a short video that explains more about the application and how it works. The site also contains information about new and Pro-exclusive features. Links to purchase either version of 1Password are available on the Web site. They direct site visitors to the Apple iTunes store. 

Tapbots
Tapbots are robots for the iPhone and iPod Touch. The homepage displays two images of the iPhone, one featuring Convertbot and one featuring Weightbot. By clicking on the phones, site visitors can learn more about the applications. Convertbot is a unit conversion robot that is capable of converting to and from mixed units (feet and inches, pounds and ounces, etc.). The Weightbot application helps people keep track of their weight. Users can set their goal weight, record their weight at any interval of a day or more, view Body Mass Index and see progress in graph form. It also includes a password feature to protect those precious pound amounts from prying eyes. Photographs and movies relating to the devices also are posted on the site for more visual stimulation. The Web pages for both bots include lists of features and requirements and, of course, links to download the applications.

Action Method
Need to get organized? Action Method is a free downloadable iPhone application, but it also is available to download directly to computers. Action Method can be used alone or in conjunction with Action Method Online, which adds even more functionality and tools to the product. iPhone users can capture and manage their "Action Steps" even when iPhone has no reception such as on an airplane. The Web site explains how the application organizes projects into basic elements and how it can help enhance productivity and improve project management. The "Take a Tour" link at the top of the home page takes viewers to a page with captured screen shots that include explanations. Users also can watch a demonstration video. Site visitors can download the iPhone application or sign up for the computer version using links on the home page. 

Apptism
This site is not related to the promotion or sale of a specific application. Rather, Apptism is an iPhone application activity aggregator that tracks the activity of every application in the Apple App Store. Apptism users can monitor all application activity and quickly find specific applications. The tool offers a variety of searching, sorting and filtering options. The Web site includes detailed explanations of what Apptism can do. The site also invites developers to tell the site about their creation using the "Feature My App now!" link. News, reviews and links to top applications are available as well. Users need to create an account to access certain features. 

Like this post? Check out our blog feature, "Cool App-titude," for more blog posts about applications.


These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new Web sites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
