<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Apps for Credit Card Payments</title>
  <author>Katie Packard</author>
  <date>December 8, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Apps</tag>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>Web 2.0</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>A friend of mine recently bought an iPhone. She's a small business owner, and one of the first apps she has looked into buying is one that lets her take credit card payments through her phone. Previously, she could only accept cash or check payments, so this app will help make her business more customer friendly. There are several apps to choose from, two of which I've featured below.</abstract>
  <text>A friend of mine recently bought an iPhone. She's a small business owner, and one of the first apps she has looked into buying is one that lets her take credit card payments through her phone. Previously, she could only accept cash or check payments, so this app will help make her business more customer friendly. There are several apps to choose from, two of which I've featured here: For iPhone and iPod Touch users, the iSwipe Pro Credit Card Terminal offers a single-entry screen to process each customer's transaction. The application accepts major credit cards (VISA, MasterCard, Discover and American Express), and one account can be used for multiple iPhones. Users can e-mail receipts to their customers as well as capture customers' signatures. The app has fraud detection capabilities and lets users view transaction histories. Users will need a merchant account to get started, but iSwipe also supports PayPal. It's available for download from iTunes for 99 cents. MerchantWARE Mobile is a free app for BlackBerry users. Like iSwipe, MerchantWARE also provides e-mailed receipts as well as transaction summaries, end-of-day batch processing, secure transactions and encryption capabilities. A reference guide is also available to guide users through transactions. A merchant account is required, but the application is free to download. It can also be downloaded onto the iPhone and iPod Touch. Like this post? Then check out other featured apps in this month's Internet Works blog post. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new Web sites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
