<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Army Colonel Shares Thoughts on Reconstruction Efforts in Iraq</title>
  <author>Katie Packard</author>
  <date>December 17, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Iraq</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Col. Dan Anninos, USA, Gulf Region district commander, e-mailed a letter to the editor to offer his perspective on reconstruction efforts in central and northern Iraq.

"Some critics argue the Iraq reconstruction effort has been wasteful resulting in unwanted facilities that will not likely be maintained by the Iraqis following the withdrawal of U.S. Forces. That assertion left unchallenged may be somewhat misleading to those not fully informed on the issue."</abstract>
  <text>The following is an e-mailed letter to the editor from Col. Dionysios "Dan" Anninos, USA, Gulf Region district commander. His entire e-mail appears unedited below:

I'm currently serving in Iraq as the Gulf Region District Commander for the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers responsible for reconstruction efforts in Central and Northern Iraq. As the on-scene commander, I have a unique perspective to offer regarding our efforts here.

Some critics argue the Iraq reconstruction effort has been wasteful resulting in unwanted facilities that will not likely be maintained by the Iraqis following the withdrawal of U.S. Forces. That assertion left unchallenged may be somewhat misleading to those not fully informed on the issue.

While it's true there have been setbacks and lessons learned during the reconstruction period since 2003, it's important to note this is the largest reconstruction effort since the Marshall Plan with one major difference-this effort is being undertaken in a war zone under hostile conditions. Our efforts here have focused on rebuilding vital infrastructure such as water supply systems, sewage treatment centers, electrical power plants, schools, hospitals and health clinics, housing and transportation networks, as well as developing the capacity of Iraqis to operate and maintain these facilities. It is a complex and an ever-changing environment.

While there have certainly been some disappointments in the past, we've also witnessed many successes resulting in quality of life improvements for Iraqis across the nation. We are in fact providing hope for the citizens of Iraq by helping them become self sufficient in providing essential services. Over time  we've learned to build what they need; what they can operate; what they can  maintain while all along building intellectual capacity and teaching acceptable construction and design standards.

For example, the Nasiriyah water treatment plant near Baghdad-which was once a dumping ground for trash-was completed more than one year ago. This plant is now operated by Iraqis. It is well maintained and provides approximately 24 million gallons of clean water to more than 500,000 Iraqi citizens every day.

More than 200,000 of those residents never had clean water hook ups to their homes before the project was built. The plant can handle additional capacity once the Iraqis expand the service area.

I'm not saying there haven't been some challenges along the way. We have learned and applied a few lessons. Water treatment stations built years ago to provide clean water to remote villages for instance, have fallen into disrepair without adequate upkeep and maintenance. We're refurbishing water treatment stations now while applying lessons learned to ensure, through a series of agreements, that these projects will be maintained after they are turned over to the Iraqis before proceeding with the project.

Within the city of Kirkuk, we have built a fully functioning solid waste collection system from trash pickup to trash transfer stations to an environmentally sustainable landfill. A similar system is being considered for Mosul. Currently, this system is operating so far above expectations that we are building a second larger station north of the city based on the same design.  These trash stations are employing hundreds of Iraqis, bolstering the local economy, while taking trash off the streets and improving living conditions for local residents.

Finally, we continue to leave a legacy of engineering expertise. A prime example is our partnership with Universities of Baghdad and Anbar as we coach, train and mentor Iraqi engineers and managers across multiple city planning functions, Geospatial Information Systems, and across several engineering disciplines. These initiatives will have a sustainable and positive impact as the Iraqis take control and re-build their nation one brick at a time while improving the quality of life for their citizens.

I am extremely humbled and proud to command a workforce constantly seeking and striving to deliver quality facilities and services to the citizens of Iraq, the Iraqi police and the Iraqi Armed Forces. Each and every one of our civilians and military workforce is making history as others write about it.
As the Iraqi parliamentary elections approach and as we plan and execute a responsible drawdown, I am thankful for a workforce that dares to dream of things that never were and make them real. Thousands of our facilities and trained Iraqi associates were nothing more than figures on a spreadsheet at one time. Today they are a reality due to the hard work and deep commitment of our Soldiers and civilians serving in Iraq.

We must not allow a few disappointments to cloud the overall success of our efforts to rebuild a sustainable Iraq. The bottom line is the Iraqi people have a much brighter future now with new schools, clean water, and more reliable electricity than they've ever had before. It's far from what we're used to in the U.S., but it's a start in the right direction. In spite of what critics may say, the American public can be proud of what our Soldiers and civilians have accomplished here in Iraq.

--Col. Dionysios "Dan" Anninos, USA, PMP, Gulf Region district commander

SIGNAL thanks Col. Anninos for taking the time to write us and share his thoughts. We welcome others to comment as well. What do you think about Col. Anninos' comments? Do you agree? Disagree? Why? Let us know in the comments below. </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
