<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Santa Apps</title>
  <author>Katie Packard</author>
  <date>December 22, 2009</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Apps</tag>
    <tag>Web 2.0</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>I like to think I'm young at heart. That's why I still get excited when it snows and why a part of me still believes in Santa. In fact, I think I saw Santa (without his red suit) eating at Cracker Barrel the other day. (Does Santa travel without his elves?) Thanks to a few apps that connect kids with the jolly guy, parents can help their children keep on believing in Santa a little bit longer.</abstract>
  <text>I like to think I'm young at heart. That's why I still get excited when it snows and why a part of me still believes in Santa. In fact, I think I saw Santa (without his red suit) eating at Cracker Barrel the other day. (Does Santa travel without his elves?) Thanks to a few apps that connect kids with the jolly guy, parents can help their children keep on believing in Santa a little bit longer. The Call Santa app lets Santa talk to children on the nice list. Parents can choose from four Christmas stories that Santa reads to the children over the phone. The application costs $0.99. Call Santa is available for iPhone and iPod Touch. For more information, visit the Web site, or go to iTunes to download the application. If a phone call isn't enough, parents can arrange a video conversation with Santa on their iPhones or iPod Touch. The Video Calls With Santa application lets parents choose from three options: a nice call, a naughty call and a voice mail for Santa. Then children answer Santa's questions and follow along. The app works regardless of how children answer the questions. The Video Calls With Santa application costs $0.99 and is available for download from iTunes. And don't forget to use your smart phone to track Santa! Like this post? Then check out other featured apps in this month's Internet Works blog post. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new Web sites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
