<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Blinded Veterans Association</title>
  <author>Katie Packard</author>
  <date>February 22, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>Warfighters</tag>
    <tag>wounded warriors</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Blinded Veterans Association (BVA) is a group of blinded veterans who help other blinded veterans. It was established to help veterans and their families overcome the challenges of sight limitations. The organization offers service programs, regional groups, resources and government advocacy to improve life for blinded veterans.</abstract>
  <text>The Blinded Veterans Association (BVA) is a group of blinded veterans who help other blinded veterans. It was established to help veterans and their families overcome the challenges of sight limitations. The organization offers service programs, regional groups, resources and government advocacy to improve life for blinded veterans, whether they incurred the disability during or after active military service. The BVA also helps encourage and support blinded veterans. The services of and membership in the organization are free, and becoming a member is not a prerequisite for obtaining assistance.

Blind or visually impaired veterans, families, friends and anyone who wants to become involved are encouraged to contact the organization by letter, phone or e-mail. The BVA would like to hear from anyone who can offer ideas, thoughts and service. The Web site features contact information, instructions for making a donation or becoming a member, more detailed information about the group, news on its efforts and additional resources. 

For more Homefront Help items, check out this month's SIGNAL Connections. 

The programs listed on these pages are not affiliated with our publication or association. We highlight these independent efforts as a service to our military and our readers. For more information about these programs, please contact the organizations directly.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
