<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Keeper</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>May 5, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
    <tag>BlackBerry apps</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>Vodafone 360 apps</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>It happens to everyone. You carefully devise a password that only you can understand or remember, complete with random strings, mixed capitals and a smattering of numerals and special characters. But the catch is that you have a different version for every single site you log into. And with more and more sites asking you to log in, that's more and more passwords.</abstract>
  <text>It happens to everyone. You carefully devise a password that only you can understand or remember, complete with random strings, mixed capitals and a smattering of numerals and special characters. But the catch is that you have a different version for every single site you log into. And with more and more sites asking you to log in, that's more and more passwords. Keeper attempts to get the madness under control with an app that stores and encrypts your passwords on your mobile device. With 128-bit encryption, backup and restore functions, the ability to synch to desktop computers (with additional software) and a self-destruct button, Keeper will fit the needs of most casual Internet users. More significant to SIGNAL readers will be the credentials of the app developer, Callpod, which also provides solutions to the U.S. Military and to the Department of Homeland Security. Learn more about the application at the company's website, where you can download the appropriate version for your supported mobile device. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
