<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>DIA Awards SITE Contracts </title>
  <author/>
  <date>May 19, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>BAE Systems</tag>
    <tag>General Dynamics</tag>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>Northrop Grumman</tag>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>SITE</tag>
    <tag>SRA</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Defense Intelligence Agency (DIA) has awarded 11 contracts totaling $6.6 billion as part of its Solutions for the Information Technology Enterprise, or SITE. The indefinite-delivery, indefinite-quantity (IDIQ) contracts will last five years and extend across the defense intelligence enterprise and the intelligence community.</abstract>
  <text>The Defense Intelligence Agency (DIA) has awarded 11 contracts totaling $6.6 billion as part of its Solutions for the Information Technology Enterprise, or SITE. The indefinite-delivery, indefinite-quantity (IDIQ) contracts will last five years and extend across the defense intelligence enterprise and the intelligence community. Six large companies were awarded contracts: BAE Systems Information Technology Incorporated; General Dynamics Information Technology Incorporated; Lockheed Martin Corporation; Northrop Grumman Systems Corporation; Science Applications International Corporation (SAIC); and Systems Research and Applications Corporation (SRA). Five small businesses received contracts: BC Fed Group LLC; CenTauri Solutions LLC; Enterprise Information Services Incorporated; Red Arch Solutions Incorporated; and Worldwide Information Network Systems Incorporated. SITE is designed to improve information technology acquisition processes for the intelligence community. It replaces both the Department of Defense Intelligence Information System (DODIIS) integration and engineering support contracts and the U.S. Air Force's Intelligence Information, Command and Control, Equipment and Enhancements (ICE2) contract vehicle. Competition among the winning SITE firms for task orders begins this summer. The DIA announcement for the SITE awards can be found at www.dia.mil/publicaffairs/Press/press_051410.pdf.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
