<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>InternetWorks: Internet File Storage </title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>May 24, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>cloud computing</tag>
    <tag>file sharing</tag>
    <tag>internet storage</tag>
    <tag>telework</tag>
    <tag>Internet Works</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The hard-hitting storms that beleaguered parts of the United States this year taught the East Coast a valuable lesson-sometimes you just can't get to work. But with immovable deadlines tasks still must be accomplished. One way offices can continue to function with personnel in disparate locations (assuming they all have power) is by storing documents in locations other than organizations' computer drives. Using the Internet as a storage device enables people to continue to move work forward, even if they can't get out the front door.</abstract>
  <text>The hard-hitting storms that beleaguered parts of the United States this year taught the East Coast a valuable lesson-sometimes you just can't get to work. But with immovable deadlines tasks still must be accomplished. One way offices can continue to function with personnel in disparate locations (assuming they all have power) is by storing documents in locations other than organizations' computer drives. Using the Internet as a storage device enables people to continue to move work forward, even if they can't get out the front door.

FilesAnywhere
FilesAnywhere launched in 1999 to offer online document storage to individuals and corporations. The Web site itself is extensive, with copious amounts of data on how to use the services provided. It also offers free customer support over the telephone. In addition to basic storage and retrieval, it provides other services such as a control option, which allows multiple users to work on a document while also reducing duplicative efforts. Popular files saved on the site include basic text documents, large-scale projects and MP3s. Businesses can take advantage of private site branding. Other features include searching files by content including custom metadata, security, video and audio streaming, picture editing, and sharing files using dropbox links. The site offers three plan levels ranging from a free plan with limited features and 1 gigabyte (GB) of storage to the Web Advanced plan that costs $7.95 a month and offers 5 GBs to 500+ GBs of storage and an array of features. Corporate plans also are available.

DropBoks
DropBoks is a free, no-frills Web site that allows users to store files online. Accounts come with 1 GB of storage and accept uploads and downloads in any format up to 10 megabytes. Once visitors sign in, the site switches to an https address with encrypted, authenticated and secure files. People who want more features can upgrade their accounts for a monthly fee. Contact information is available online along with pictures and descriptions of staff members. The site also runs a blog containing information about the company and services.

FreeDrive
This personal storage and file sharing service is designed for folks who love their social networking. A FreeDrive account enables users to access their own files as well as the files of their friends within online social networks. Interested parties can even set up accounts through Facebook at http://apps.facebook.com/freedrive. In addition to the private files that people can store and share, FreeDrive has a public folder containing various items that anyone can view.

SugarSync
With SugarSync, users can access, back up and share their files even when they have no computer access. The services work with any Web-enabled mobile communications devices. Data is automatically configured for mobile viewing when people reach out for their documents, photographs or music this way. SugarSync applications for iPhone, iPod Touch, Windows Mobile and BlackBerry are available for download at no cost. In addition to its on-the-go capability, the service can automatically sync files and folders across multiple computers. Account holders can provide unlimited access to their documents or set limits as they deem appropriate. SugarSync offers a free 30-day trial. Costs for the various membership levels are listed on the homepage.

divShare
Users who transfer their files to divShare can have them automatically converted to Flash, enabling viewing, streaming and playing of the media from any browser. The share/embed options let users embed, download, e-mail and more with the click of a button and the insertion of an address. Music can be streamed and embedded in the audio player with tools to create playlists or make slideshows. Account holders can customize file download pages with names, links and logos. Upgraded accounts enable people to add links and logos to Flash video, audio and slideshow players. Each upload to the site generates a unique URL that owners can share with others. People who want more security can add a password to files or folders. Several other privacy options also are available. Facebook account holders can use that information to create a divShare account, and divShare information can be integrated with Facebook, iPhone and WordPress Plugin. Using the divShare API, Web site developers can integrate the site's services into their own applications. DivShare additionally offers two blogs, one with general information about the company and one dedicated to keeping members informed about maintenance issues. Accounts are available at various service and price levels.

These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new Web sites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
