<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Aiming for Accuracy</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>June 8, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Apps</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>Web 2.0</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The creator of an app called BulletFlight claims it could improve the accuracy of military snipers in training by calculating the trajectory of a bullet's flight path to ensure users hit the target.</abstract>
  <text>Soldiers may not have time to utilize an iPhone app in the field, but the creator of an application called BulletFlight claims it could improve the accuracy of military snipers in training. Developed by Knight's Armament Company and available through Apple's iTunes App Store for $11.99, the app eliminates some of the math involved in long-distance target shooting and calculates the trajectory of a bullet's flight path to ensure users hit the target. It allows shooters to input wind speed, atmospheric conditions and distance for the intended target. The app then dictates how users can compensate for factors such as "bullet drop," which is the impact of gravity on the bullet after it exits the barrel. BulletFlight is made specifically for three sniper rifles, including the U.S. military's M110. The company even created an iPod Touch Mount to hook an iPhone or iPod touch to the rifle making the program more accessible. The system, created by Robert Silvers, has already seen action in both Afghanistan and Iraq. It's not the first app of its kind-Web Diligence created iSnipe, which is available through the iTunes App Store for $5.99. It also predicts a bullet's path so shooters can predetermine the speed and direction of the bullet before even loading the gun. Do you believe either app has practical applications for the military during training or in the field? These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
