<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Call for Oil Spill Response Solutions</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>June 8, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>BP</tag>
    <tag>Collaboration</tag>
    <tag>deepwater horizon</tag>
    <tag>public private partnership</tag>
    <tag>U.S. Coast Guard</tag>
    <tag>News Briefs</tag>
    <tag>SIGNAL Extras</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The recently formed Interagency Alternative Technology Assessment Program (IATAP) announced last Friday it plans to collect and review oil spill response solutions from scientists and vendors.</abstract>
  <text>The recently formed Interagency Alternative Technology Assessment Program (IATAP) announced last Friday it plans to collect and review oil spill response solutions.

The U.S. Coast Guard's Research and Development Center has been providing on-site support for the oil spill response and issued a Broad Agency Announcement (BAA) along with interagency partners calling for the submission of new technology solutions. The BAA requested white papers addressing several key problem areas: sensing and detection; wellhead control and submerged response; traditional and alternative technologies; and damage assessment and restoration.

Teams will screen the results and separate them into three categories based on whether or not the solution:

1.Has potential for immediate benefit to the response effort.
2.Needs more detailed investigation.
3.Does not support a response to this incident.

The BAA can be found here using these search terms:

Deepwater Horizon Response
Solicitation Number: HSCG32-10-R-R00019
Agency: Department of Homeland Security
Office: United States Coast Guard (USCG)
Location: Contracting Office, USCG Research and Development Center

Adm. Thad Allen, USCG, the national incident commander for the BP  Deepwater Horizon oil spill, established the IATAP group, which includes  the U.S. Coast Guard, National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration,  Department of the Interior, Minerals Management Service, Environmental  Protection Agency and Department of Agriculture.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
