<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Secret Intel Business, Part 2</title>
  <author/>
  <date>June 24, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Acquisition Resource Center</tag>
    <tag>DIA</tag>
    <tag>Intelligence</tag>
    <tag>Intelligence Community</tag>
    <tag>NGA</tag>
    <tag>NSA</tag>
    <tag>Small Business</tag>
    <tag>Acquisition</tag>
    <tag>Event Coverage</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>At AFCEA International's Small Business Intelligence forum yesterday, experts revealed tips about how companies-large and small-can increase their business with member agencies of the intelligence community. But, yesterday's blog coverage was just too short to include all of the advice they shared, so here are a few more ideas.</abstract>
  <text>Yesterday's blog coverage was just too short to include the depth of advice the experts at the Small Business Intelligence Forum shared, so here are a few more ideas: -Savvy SIGNAL Scape  reader Ross Andrews, ARC Program Manager, Contractor - BVTI, beat this reporter to the punch on a very important item that should be on every small company's list if it wants to do business with the intelligence community: register with the Acquisition Resource Center. See his full comment at http://bit.ly/bXmzFM. -The road to doing business with the DIA can begin at the agency itself, where Sherry Baldwin, director of the agency's Office of Small Business Programs, has a list of individuals to contact at large prime contracting firms. The office is located at Bolling Air Force Base, Virginia, and Baldwin can reached at Sea0132@dia.mil. -Each government agency has a goal for working with small businesses that they must strive to meet. Many are close to meeting that goal, but many are not. Seek out those that need to work with more small businesses. -Know the North American Industry Classification System (NAICS) codes. -The NSA doesn't advertise its needs under its agency name, and it works with a very small community of companies, but once you're in, you're in. Network face-to-face on a regular basis with personnel from other companies and don't be afraid to market your wares. -Most members of the IC are interested in a few hot items that include fast and smart query analytics; real-time detection behaviors, security access capabilities; innovative antennas; and new battery technologies. -Be aware of and attend Industry Days. -"NGA is very committed to working with small business. You can take that to the bank." -Sandra Broadnax, small business executive, NGA -Don't rely exclusively on the IC for keeping your business afloat. Diversify. -Stay cautious and grow judiciously. -Know yourself; know your customers; know the users. -Seek out the individuals at IC agencies who are involved with acquisition and accounting so that they KNOW who YOU are. -Listen to an agency's vision, mission and challenges. Develop a white paper to solve those challenges. Once the agency agrees that your solution may have merit, go to the prime contractor working with the agency and tell it how you can solve the specific IC organization's problem. Do you have other suggestions about how to increase business with IC agencies? Don't be shy...share them here!</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
