<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Fourth of July Reflections</title>
  <author/>
  <date>July 1, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Guest Blogs</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Guest blogger James Schenck, a U.S. Army veteran and president of the PenFed Foundation, reflects on the military community as we prepare to celebrate our nation's birthday. "This Fourth of July, I ask you to join me in saluting the sacrifices of all veterans who served to defend our nation and remembering their contributions. While the nation reflects on sacrifices of veterans this Independence Day who did not return back from war, I also would like to salute members of the military who sacrificed in other ways."</abstract>
  <text>[Editor's Note: This is a guest blog from James Schenck, an Army veteran and the president of the PenFed Foundation, a military support organization.]  This Fourth of July, I ask you to join me in saluting the sacrifices of all veterans who served to defend our nation and remembering their contributions. While the nation reflects on sacrifices of veterans this Independence Day who did not return back from war, I also would like to salute members of the military who sacrificed in other ways. From the Marine whose family is struggling financially due to multiple deployments, to the sailor who couldn't buy her first house because she was overseas, to the soldier who is now relearning how to walk with his wife by his side and needs daycare for his young children: members of our military make sacrifices everyday that go unseen. As a West Point graduate, I've committed myself to a lifetime of service to my nation.  As president of the PenFed Foundation, I have the opportunity to work with an incredible team of board members and employees who are honored to serve our nation's defenders.   Independence Day is a day to reflect on what it means to be an American and the liberties and freedoms we all enjoy as a result of the sacrifices and hardships endured by our men and women in uniform. It is a day for every American to look around and say thank you to those currently serving and those who have served. We must also recognize our national security is a team effort and our military is on the front lines, but we must not forget the selfless servants within our intelligence communities, our defense contractors and the millions of Americans who go to work each day who are supporting the successes of our operations around the world. This Fourth of July make a commitment to supporting our nation's defenders and their families in any way you can. When members of our military return home to financial and medical problems, they end up losing their own freedom. Our veterans should not have to sacrifice their independence in order to guarantee ours.   James Schenck is president of the PenFed Foundation. He was a U.S. Army aviation officer flying UH-60 Blackhawk Helicopters. He served in the Office of the Deputy Chief of Staff of the Army for Operations and Plans. The PenFed Foundation has several programs that help military personnel who are struggling with financial, housing and medical issues. For more information about the PenFed Foundation, visit: www.pentagonfoundation.org   The publication of this blog message does not consititute endorsement by AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
