<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: PTSD Support</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>July 13, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</tag>
    <tag>PTSD</tag>
    <tag>Veteran Resources</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>An app created by the online support community Hope for One aims to provide support for military veterans and their families struggling with the effects of post-traumatic stress disorder.</abstract>
  <text>
	Hope for One PTSD App

An app created by the online support community Hope for One aims to provide help for military veterans and their families struggling with the effects of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD). The Hope for One PTSD app has a variety of tools that offer users resources for help and encouragement to address the way PTSD affects veterans and their wives, husbands, children, parents and other family members. The app provides a live news feed with updates related to PTSD, as well as other relevant information for veterans collected from both military and private organizations. In addition, users can access a comprehensive library of related videos, including testimonies from other soldiers and their families, information on military health resources, professional counseling, psychiatry insights and practical tips on how to seek help. Podcasts are also available with streaming audio files that can be downloaded for future use on a mobile phone or computer. The app contains links to a variety of useful websites and a fan wall, which is an interactive page where users can post comments and meet others struggling with PTSD. In addition, Hope for One PTSD comes with an optional mailing list for updates on future enhancements and programs. The app automatically updates with new content as support resources become available. The app is free and available here for both the iPhone and Android platforms. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
