<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Google App Inventor</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>July 20, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
    <tag>Google</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>You don't have to be a programmer to write programs. Just ask the team that created the Google App Inventor-a free application that helps users create new apps with simple drag and drop elements.</abstract>
  <text>
	Google App Inventor

The Google App Inventor for Android allows any user to build a mobile app from scratch for free without any programming knowledge. So just how easy is the tool? According to the New York Times, it has been tested on kids as young as sixth grade, and they succeeded in easily building their own apps. The menu-driven, user interface contains fill-in-the-blank forms, and as the user drags and drops their desired elements, the software generates the code. The application has endless possibilities for work and entertainment, and in its testing stage it has already been used by students to create the popular apps DroidMuni, ParkIt and Drum Kit. Google's program for Android is a direct contrast to the iPhone, iPad and BlackBerry app systems, which require serious coding from developers. As of this time, an official release date for the App Inventor has not been published. However, a form available from Google Labs allows users to request access to the free tool, which Google anticipates releasing in the coming weeks. Some web developers expressed concern that the app creator would lead to an explosion of poorly made apps. Others ventured that sparking interest in app creation could eventually lead to the next generation of web developers. Do you think this application will be beneficial?  These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
