<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>It's Time to Start</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>July 21, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>SIGNAL Extras</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>CWID 2011 Industry Day offers insights into event that has resulted in the acquisition of numerous technologies crucial to current operations. Past demonstrations have led to the GCCS and blue force tracking, just to name a few.</abstract>
  <text>The dust from  Coalition Warrior Interoperability Demonstration 2010 (CWID) has barely had time to settle, but plans for CWID 2011 have already begun. One of the first steps is the event's Industry Day, which begins at 8:30 a.m. on August 17 at The Conference Center at the Maritime Institute, Linthicum, Maryland.

Industry and government attendees will learn about the CWID process from start to finish. Information will include how to make the event work best for them, how to leverage CWID as an acquisition tool, the technology assessment process, and CWID's industry and sponsor requirements for participation. A panel comprising former demonstration participants will share their experiences in the event in previous years.

The Joint Chiefs of Staff sponsor CWID, an event that has resulted in many of the technologies warfighters are using in current operations. These include the High Power X-Band Satellite Communications (XTAR), which was demonstrated in 2008 and received a contract from the GSA as well as the Federal Acquisition Service for Information Technology Equipment, Software and Services. Immediate results were put into the field even quicker from a 2009 demonstration. The ReadyResponders Network, a collaborative information-sharing portal, immediately was put into place in Haiti after the earthquake in January and continues to support relief efforts there. Even technologies that warfighters now take for granted such as the GCCS and Blue Force Tracking began as CWID technology trials.

Attendance fee for the CWID Industry Day is $150 and includes lunch, snacks and a disc that contains all of the presenters' material. Online registration is available.

</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
