<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Power in the Cloud</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>August 17, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
    <tag>cloud computing</tag>
    <tag>Google</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Google introduces two new mobile apps for Android devices that take advantage of cloud computing infrastructure and advanced wireless connectivity.</abstract>
  <text>
	Apps Tap into Cloud Computing

Google held a media conference in San Francisco late last week, where they explained how advanced wireless connectivity and processing power on smart phones allows mobile apps to take advantage of cloud computing. Hugo Barra, Google product management director, unveiled a pair of new apps at the event. He demonstrated the Voice Actions for Android app, which allows users to speak commands into the phone and have the requests performed. For example, a user can say, "Call home," and the phone will automatically dial the number labeled as home in the address book. The app also enables voice Web search and the "note to self" feature, which lets users record a reminder and have it e-mail to their account. Barra also showed off the updated Chrome-to-Phone app. This program automatically transfers data, such as maps and links, from a Chrome browser straight to an Android device. A user searching on the Web can simply click a small mobile phone icon and have that information sent directly to the Android, so that when they open the app it will automatically launch that site. Google credits access to massive computer power in the cloud for its ability to design innovative mobile products that generate results. Both applications are available in the Android Market and require Android 2.2. The Voice Actions app will come preinstalled on the Droid 2 phone. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
