<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Stress Relief for Wounded Warriors</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>August 24, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>Supporting Our Veterans</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Defense Department's medical branch creates an iPhone application called iBreathe to help military personnel and veterans handle stressful situations by practicing relaxed breathing.</abstract>
  <text>A team at the Defense Centers of Excellence (DCoE) National Center for Telehealth and Technology developed an iPhone app called iBreathe, which will be available for free in the iTunes app store after January 2011. It aims to help military personnel, veterans and their family members deal with stressful situations by practicing deep "belly" breathing. DCoE researchers say high-stress situations often result in a "fight or flight" mentality, and the lingering stress can take a physical and mental toll. The iBreathe app will offer a readily accessible way to cope with this stress through relaxed breathing. Users will have access to instructional videos on deep breathing techniques; illustrations; exercises and practice sessions; a visual stress tracker; pre/post stress ratings; charted progress; a journal; and a feature that allows users to tag data points with personal notes. The app will work with the iPhone or iPod Touch, and creators say an Android version will be available in the near future. Although it's aimed at the military, the app will be available for the general public. Researchers are also developing an iBreathe application made especially for children. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
