<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: AMVETS Mobile</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>August 31, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>BlackBerry apps</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>iPod Touch apps</tag>
    <tag>Supporting Our Veterans</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>American Veterans (AMVETS) announced a new mobile app for the iPhone, iPod Touch and Blackberry that allows veterans to locate AMVETS posts, find their local service officer, connect with headquarters and research veterans' issues.</abstract>
  <text>American Veterans (AMVETS) announced a new mobile app for the iPhone, iPod Touch and Blackberry that allows veterans to locate AMVETS posts, find their local service officer, connect with headquarters and research veterans' issues. The veterans' organization and FraternalSoft Incorporated teamed up to create AMVETS Mobile, which AMVETS National Commander Duane J. Miskulin calls the "latest weapon in our communications arsenal." The demographic of veterans is changing, and the need for instant information is key, explains Jim King, AMVETS executive director. The app provides veterans with the ability to locate the nearest AMVETS posts or thrift stores using geo-location services. Users can also search for posts by name, location, area code or meeting time. It also provides information on veterans' issues by linking to the AMVETS website, Twitter and Facebook accounts and allows the user to send e-mails without leaving the app. Veterans can even keep up to date on the latest buzz with videos on the AMVETS YouTube channel. AMVETS Mobile is available for $6.99 in the iTunes App Store. It will be available in the Blackberry App World in October 2010. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
