<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Survival Pocket Reference</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>September 7, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>U.S. Armed Forces</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Outdoor enthusiasts now have access to the Defense Department's 500-page publication titled "Survival, Evasion and Recovery" with the click of a button. The iPhone app Survival Pocket Reference teaches users the survival skills implemented in the wild by the U.S. armed forces.</abstract>
  <text>Outdoor enthusiasts now have access to the Defense Department's 500-page publication titled "Survival, Evasion and Recovery" with the click of a button. The iPhone app Survival Pocket Reference teaches users the survival skills implemented in the wild by the U.S. armed forces. Field manuals used by the U.S. Army, Marine Corps, Navy and Air Force are arguably the most authoritative guides on survival. The Survival Pocket Reference app combines real tips used by the military for basic survival, first aid and recovery. The app includes instructions for creating shelters in hot and cold climates; navigating by compass and stars; building a fire; finding food and water; surviving nuclear, chemical or biological attacks; and finding edible and medicinal plants. The skills taught by the app can be adapted to any environment, including tropical, arctic or subarctic regions. It describes ways to survive in a remote area with little or no personal gear. Created by Double Dog Studios, the app is available in the iTunes App Store for $0.99. But one iTunes review may bring up a valid point:

	"This is everything it purports to be. The only thing it leaves out is how to charge your iPhone/iPad when stranded in the wilderness. Is that a poisonous plant? Oh darn, battery's dead."
Do you think a survival app such as this one could really come in handy? These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
