<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: BioLock</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>September 14, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Sliding a bar to unlock your Android device or entering a PIN? Those methods of smart-phone security could soon be a thing of the past thanks to the new BioLock app, which encrypts and locks down phones using iris and facial scanning.</abstract>
  <text>Sliding a bar to unlock your Android device or entering a PIN? Those methods of smart-phone security could soon be a thing of the past thanks to the new BioLock app, which encrypts and locks down phones using iris and facial scanning.

The BioLock app from Blue Planet Apps will be released into Beta in the coming weeks. It secures Android devices using two biometric recognition features: iris and facial scanning. The iris scan uses the colored part of the user's eye to create a unique key and the second technique uses a scan of the user's entire face. The smart phone must be equipped with a front-facing camera (available on the HTC EVO 4G) so that the user can snap an image of his or her face or iris. The phone will only unlock if the scan matches the saved data for the user.

The app creators claim the program can detect if someone tries to trick the software using a still image of the user held in front of the camera. It also claims to recognize the user's face regardless of any changes with facial hair.

BioLock doesn't just lock the phone-it can also lock applications, documents and contacts. 

The app will be released into Beta shortly, and it costs $2.99 for a 14-day public trial. Follow @blueplanetapps on Twitter for more information on when it becomes available.

These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
