<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Mobile Defense</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>September 28, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>An app for Android users protects smart phones from being lost or stolen without taking up precious battery power or memory. Mobile Defense will locate the phone down to an exact address, display it on an interactive map and sound a loud alarm through the phone's speaker.</abstract>
  <text>An app for Android users protects smart phones from being lost or stolen without taking up precious battery power or memory. Mobile Defense will locate the phone down to an exact address, display it on an interactive map and sound a loud alarm through the phone's speaker.

The Mobile Defense program from Neevo, once only available to users on the T-Mobile network, has opened to Sprint and Verizon. It runs quietly in the background of the smart-phone device and only uses battery power and memory when it is actively in use.

Once the app is installed, the user sets up a secure account that can be accessed from the Mobile Defense website. Any time the phone is lost or missing, the user can log in and click "Connect to Phone" to lock down its location. The exact address will appear on a map, and the user can lock or unlock the phone remotely and set off a loud alarm through the phone speaker.

Also, the app will alert the user immediately if someone tries to swap out the phone's SIM card. It will even give the subscriber ID and phone number tied to the new card and allow the user to issue emergency commands.

Mobile Defense has temporarily returned to closed beta in preparation for the next release. If you would like to be notified via e-mail when the app starts accepting new users, you can complete the form on the website or follow the buzz on Twitter @Neevo.

These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
