<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: A Story Before Bed</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>October 26, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Apps</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>iPad apps</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>iPod Touch apps</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Military personnel serving overseas can record a bedtime story and send it to their children for free thanks to an iPhone app called A Story Before Bed. The program offers 100,000 free recordings to help troops connect with loved ones back home.</abstract>
  <text>Military personnel serving overseas can record a bedtime story and send it to their children for free thanks to an iPhone app called A Story Before Bed. The program offers 100,000 free recordings to help troops connect with loved ones back home. Any member of the U.S. armed forces who is deploying or already deployed can sign up on the A Story Before Bed website to receive a free storybook recording. Soldiers record a story using a webcam on a Mac or PC and send it to their children using the company's iPhone, iPod Touch or iPad app or a Web browser. The recording will show a video of the user reading along with a virtual version of the actual book. The pages of the book turn as the reader goes through the story. Once children receive the video, they can watch it as many times as they want. Users can browse through a collection of more than 150 popular children's books sorted be title, publisher, age and length. More titles are added each day, and the company has already given away more than 3,500 recordings to troops overseas. The app is available for free in the iTunes App Store, and interested military personnel can register for their free recording here. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
