<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>CWID Publishes 2010 Interoperability Trial Results</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>November 12, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>General</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Technology assessors chose 11 out of 32 technology solutions from this year's event as their picks for early success. Judged on their achievement in interoperability, information assurance and warfighter/operator utility, the Top Performing Technologies range from capabilities that support ballistic missile defense to maritime traffic tracking and could be in the hands of users in six to 12 months.</abstract>
  <text>The Coalition Warrior Interoperability Demonstration  2010 (CWID 2010) final report  has been released in a Consumer Reports style and includes a list of the top 11 performing technologies. The event comprised 32 interoperability trials that focused on challenges warfighters are facing in Afghanistan in the areas of exchanging information among coalition partners, military services and government agencies. Additionally, the solutions addressed issues of command, control and communications among emergency responders. 

After conducting one to three assessments-interoperability, information assurance and warfighter/operator utility-of the participating interoperability trial solutions, the top technologies included the Virtual Intercom System, a ballistic missile defense system called FLEX, the Joint Airborne Network Control, an Italian air force command and control information system network, the Collaborative Alert Respond System and the ID Military Application Security Services. Top solutions could be in the hands of military forces and government agency personnel within six to 12 months.

The judging criteria for Top Performing Technologies (TPT) were developed in CWID 2009. The process includes establishing entrance/exit criteria at key CWID planning/decision points that can be mapped to U.S. Defense Department-mandated, standardized needs. In addition, the TPTs were chosen based on how well they met sponsor-defined requirements the funding programs, technology sponsors or Joint Chiefs of Staff set.

Trial sponsors provided metrics against which an interoperability trial performance's was assessed. Trials that demonstrated more than 50 percent performance achievement when compared to these measurements achieved TPT status.
Just days after the release of the 2010 event results, planning for the CWID 2011  event began. On November 14, the initial planning conference was underway, and the next list of technologies selected. Next year's demonstration will focus on information-sharing solutions that support the Afghanistan Mission Network construct.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
