<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: Orlando Military Discounts</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>November 18, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Orlando is a fun-filled vacation destination and many of the theme parks and hotels in the city offer exclusive deals for the military community.</abstract>
  <text>Orlando is a fun-filled vacation destination and many of the theme parks and hotels in the city offer exclusive deals for the military community. Walt Disney World has discounts on tickets, hotel rooms and cruises. It even has a military-only hotel, Shades of Green, sitting on property close to the Magic Kingdom. Current specials are listed on a website for Disney World's military discounts. For fun with an aquatic twist, SeaWorld offers military members and up to three dependents one-day passes for free admission that are available by filling out an online form. The deal is part of the Here's to the Heroes program, which also offers free tickets at other Anheuser-Busch amusement parks around the country. Military families looking for more fun can buy discounted tickets to Universal Studios at various military bases. The theme park lists participating installations and more information about the offers available on its Military Ticket Program page. Troops also can purchase tickets on base for discount admission to Kennedy Space Center, located east of Orlando, and they receive a 10 percent discount on food and retail items at the visitor complex. The Nickelodeon Suites Resort in Orlando offers a variety of special prices and support activities for the military community as well. The hotel is geared toward families with children. Many of the deals listed by these organizations expire at the end of 2010. Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
