<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>From the Front Line: New Radios Challenge Interoperability</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>December 13, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Letters to the Editor</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>SIGNAL Magazine reader takes issue with effectiveness of new radios being introduced into operations in Afghanistan.</abstract>
  <text>[Lt. Col. Joseph (Joe) Hilfiker, USA, submitted this as a letter to the editor. We invite your comments.]

I have read the NewsNet article "Handheld Radios for Afghan Coalition" in the November issue of SIGNAL Magazine. We have received a significant number of the RF-310s in RC East. Sending the RF-310 to Afghanistan has been a horrible idea, and we are trying to get them replaced with VRC-110/PRC-152s as quickly as possible.

The RF-310 has been a major step backward for coalition interoperability. The Suite B key is not interoperable with the Type 1 key used by all coalition forces. The end result is coalition forces on the battlefield with two types of comsec that cannot talk to each other. Prior to the arrival of the RF-310, coalition partners used/were issued VRC-110/PRC-152s, so we could all communicate at the tactical level. Now, they have a mix of RF-310s and VRC-110/PRC-152s that cannot talk to each other.

An example vignette: Patrol from a coalition PRT [provincial reconstruction team] operating in a U.S. Brigade Combat Team's (BCT's) battlespace and equipped with RF-310s is in an ambush. They will not be able to call for a nearby COP [common operational picture] via FM for help as their radios are not interoperable. They will not be able to call for help from the BCT they work for because their RF-310s are not compatible in SC TACSAT mode. They will not be able to talk to the aircraft orbiting overhead looking at the smoke to ask for help as their radios are not interoperable.

Lt. Col. Joseph (Joe) Hilfiker, USA
CJ-6 Director
RC-East</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
