<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool  App-titude: Brain Wave</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>December 28, 2010</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>health</tag>
    <tag>iPad apps</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>iPod Touch apps</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Brain Wave app uses soothing sounds and binaural tones to stimulate the mind and increase sleep, relaxation, focus and concentration-mental health benefits for soldiers under stress.</abstract>
  <text>The Brain Wave app for iPhone synchronizes brain waves with soothing ambient sounds to stimulate and induce different states of the mind, which can reduce anxiety and increase sleep, relaxation, focus, concentration and memory. Brain Wave, created by Banzai Labs, utilizes binaural tones combined with soothing ambient nature sounds to stimulate specific brain wave frequencies. It sends different audible frequencies to each ear, which researchers say can induce various states of mind, from alert and focused to deep sleep. Benefits of the app range from increased exercise motivation to a positive mood boost. The app contains 25 unique sound-based programs to ensure a more effective experience. Program durations range from 10 minutes to eight hours, and users can create their own custom settings. Soothing background noises include ocean waves, rain and thunder. The brain processes the binaural frequencies played over these sounds. The app has programs to target critical thinking, meditation, problem solving, confidence boost, anger relief, creativity boost, reduced anxiety, calm reflection, power naps and more. It can run in the background on the iPhone, iPod Touch or iPad while the user reads and performs other tasks. Brain Wave can be purchased from the iTunes App Store for $1.99. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
