<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Webinar: How to Deliver More Bits Per Hertz Per Dollar</title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>February 22, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>network design</tag>
    <tag>Webinars</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Join us March 10, 2011 at 12 noon as SIGNAL Editor-in-Chief Robert K. Ackerman talks with Alan Henderson, Vice President of Engineering, Globecomm Network Services Corp. about balancing mission priorities with bandwidth allocations for IP-based, hybrid terrestrial-satellite networks.</abstract>
  <text>Join us March 10, 2011 at 12 noon as SIGNAL Editor-in-Chief Robert K. Ackerman talks with Alan Henderson, Vice President of Engineering, Globecomm Network Services Corp.:

U.S. Armed Forces stand at a crossroads when it comes to demands and resources. Fighting two wars and ensuring security on a global basis, they are entering a period when every dollar of military spending will be scrutinized as never before. For the IP-based, hybrid terrestrial-satellite network, the key to success can be summarized in a few words: deliver More Bits per Hertz per Dollar, and do it today, tomorrow and every day after that. But getting maximum performance requires the right design, the right match-up of technology, and constant attention to changing conditions on the net. The military network is composed of multiple technologies from hundreds of suppliers, all supposedly interoperable but seldom right-sized for the exploding number of applications they serve. Bandwidth is always at a premium, yet keeping mission priorities and bandwidth allocations in lockstep is a continuing challenge.

In this webinar, experienced systems designers, integrators and technologists:

    * Describe network design and integration methods that maximize throughput
    * Explain how continuous monitoring of throughput and active management of protocols maintains network performance
    * Outline the principles and practices of WAN optimization

Registration and archive information for this webinar are here.


</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
