<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Divide</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>March 1, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Work hard-play hard. The new Divide app lets you integrate your work life and personal life in one smart phone.</abstract>
  <text>Work hard-play hard. The new Divide app lets you integrate your work life and personal life into one smart phone. 

Developed by Enterproid, the Divide app for Android separates your device into a secure and protected work profile for your professional data and a personal profile for your normal programs. The app lets your smart phone act like two separate devices-flipping between a walled-off, secure environment and an open environment to install apps or play games. You can use the app to set different levels of security for each profile. The two profiles look completely different, but they run side by side on your device. 

When a user installs the Divide app, it registers with the user's work e-mail account and integrates any security policies put in place by the employer. The Divide platform constantly is connected to Enterproid's cloud servers so that information technology administrators at work can access the professional portion of your device if necessary. However, your personal data always will remain completely private.

The app stores all its data in an encrypted area on the phone, and apps that run inside Divide do not communicate with the Android system. This keeps outside companies from accessing your personal data.

Divide currently is available in Beta form for Android devices. Sign up here to participate in the trial. The company hopes to bring the app to other mobile platforms in the future.

These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
