<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Army Strong Stories</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>May 10, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
    <tag>U.S. Army</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>An iPhone app launched by the U.S. Army lets soldiers post blogs anytime, anywhere as part of the Army Strong Stories program.</abstract>
  <text>The U.S. Army Accessions Command launched the Army Strong Stories app for iPhone along with a mobile website as part of its blogging and storytelling initiative. Army Strong Stories is a program from the command, which is dedicated to sharing blogs and videos created by soldiers, family members, friends and supporters. Soldiers of every rank and background can share their perspective on daily life in the military and chronicle their experiences from basic combat training to serving overseas. The blog is also open to cadets, veterans and Army-contracted civilians. 600 soldier bloggers currently participate in the Army Strong Stories campaign, and mobile connectivity is a high priority for service members looking to stay connected with their units, bases, fellow soldiers and families. The app enables users to share their story, post comments and learn more about Army services on the go. In a release from the U.S. Army, Lt. Gen. Benjamin Freakley, USA, commanding general of U.S. Army Accessions Command, said he hopes the app helps soldiers continue to share authentic stories, and he believes it reinforces the Army's commitment to embracing social media. The iPhone app is available for free in the iTunes App Store, and the mobile website version is compatible with BlackBerry, Windows Mobile and Android. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
