<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Webinar June 23: Reduce Cost and Improve Mission Success With Ethernet Encryption </title>
  <author>H. Mosher</author>
  <date>June 21, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Webinars</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Join us on June 23 at 1 p.m. for a webinar on how Ethernet encryption over other technologies can help you improve your bottom line while simplifying your network. The requirement for real-time information sharing is driving agencies to eliminate stovepipes and build converged network infrastructures to provide a common operating environment. Agencies are faced with a decision on which network architectures to deploy that will allow them to carry data over wide area networks (WANs) that connect regional commands, domestic and international facilities, data centers, and disaster recovery sites. Aligning encryption capabilities with the transport technology can provide substantial benefits to the organization.</abstract>
  <text>Join us on June 23 at 1 p.m. for a webinar sponsored by SafeNet on how Ethernet encryption over other technologies can help you improve your bottom line while simplifying your network.
The requirement for real-time information sharing is driving agencies to eliminate stovepipes and build converged network infrastructures to provide a common operating environment. Agencies are faced with a decision on which network architectures to deploy that will allow them to carry data over wide area networks (WANs) that connect regional commands, domestic and international facilities, data centers, and disaster recovery sites. Aligning encryption capabilities with the transport technology can provide substantial benefits to the organization.

During this webinar, you will learn:
How you can unlink your encryption strategy from your network architecture and implement a totally secure, full performance, high speed Ethernet WAN.
How different encryption methodologies compare from a cost and performance perspective when it comes to bandwidth needs and different connectivity models.
Click here to register.
How to determine which deployment model is best for your agencies network requirements.
</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
