<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: T.A.M.P.A. USMC Family Support</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>July 21, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
    <tag>Supporting Our Veterans</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Since 2004, this organization has offered support to Marines and their loved ones in Florida. In addition to working for active-duty families, the group reaches out to reservists, retired Marines, veterans, wounded warriors and those in boot camp or the delayed entry program.</abstract>
  <text>Since 2004, this organization has offered support to Marines and their loved ones in Florida. In addition to working for active-duty families, the group reaches out to reservists, retired Marines, veterans, wounded warriors and those in boot camp or the delayed entry program. "Family" includes not only spouses and children but also mothers, fathers, siblings, grandparents and friends. Gold and Silver Star families are always welcome to seek support as well. Though dedicated to the Devil Dog community, the organization extends its outreach to include all military branches and other patriotic supporters.

T.A.M.P.A. USMC Family Support runs several events-such as sending injured troops on vacations or recycling cell phones-throughout the year to raise funds and awareness for the military community. On August 21, the group will hold its 4th annual Run for the Fallen. The free event is a one-mile walk or 5K run starting at E.G. Simmons Park. Last year more than 750 people watched or attended, and this year the goal is to exceed 1,000 people. The group aims to have at least one participant to represent each fallen military member from Florida. Anyone interested in preregistering, donating, volunteering or additional information should contact R4F@usmcfamilysupport.org.

Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
