<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Marines Move Beyond MILES</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>July 27, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Cubic Defense Applications</tag>
    <tag>I-TESS II</tag>
    <tag>man-worn detection system</tag>
    <tag>MILES</tag>
    <tag>MOUT</tag>
    <tag>Multiple Integrted Laser Engagement System</tag>
    <tag>small arms transmitter</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Cubic Defense Applications Incorporated, San Diego, California, is being awarded more than $49 million to incrementally replace the Marine Corps's Multiple Integrated Laser Engagement System (MILES) and include the training systems of the Instrumented-Tactical Engagement Simulation System Increment I (I-TESS II) and additional weapon training system capabilities. I-TESS II equipment will be used to support direct force-on-force and force-on-target training. The I-TESS II system will consist of no less than the following components: small arms transmitter; (SAT) man-worn detection system (MDS); command and control, mobile and portable versions; and Military Operations in Urban Terrain (MOUT) building instrumentation, vehicle tracking, engagement, and association systems, hand grenade simulators, and simulated battlefield effects interface modules. The SAT will be used on the M9 pistol; M4, M16, M40, and AK-47 type rifles; the M249 squad automatic weapon; and M2 and M240G machine guns. Rocket propelled grenade and AT-4 simulators, vehicle tracking, engagement and association systems will be used to track and/or engage vehicles and fixed structures such as towers, bridges, and facilities. The MDS and range equipment will be used to instrument the individual Marine for direct force-on-force, and force-on-target engagement adjudication and will include the ability to support instrumentation functions such as position location information reporting. The I-TESS II system will be used in MOUT facilities and non-live fire maneuver ranges located at various Marine Corps bases and installations. Marine Corps Systems Command, supporting Program Manager for Training Systems, Orlando, Florida, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
