<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Webinar 9/14/11: Seamless Communication Interoperability Supporting Warfighters' Missions</title>
  <author>Henry Kenyon</author>
  <date>August 19, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Webinars</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Today, military communications deploy diverse technologies that comprise the tactical and strategic converged networks needed to support  warfighters' missions. Challenges exist in deploying and operating these networks that include a broad range of technologies including: VoIP, TDM, SatCom, cellular, tactical radios, SCIP, WiFi and GSM. Additionally, military communications must support the wide range of diverse and not necessarily interconnected networks which are comprised of legacy and emerging technologies.</abstract>
  <text>Today, military communications deploy diverse technologies that comprise the tactical and strategic converged networks needed to support  warfighters' missions. Challenges exist in deploying and operating these networks that include a broad range of technologies including: VoIP, TDM, SatCom, cellular, tactical radios, SCIP, WiFi and GSM. Additionally, military communications must support the wide range of diverse and not necessarily interconnected networks which are comprised of legacy and emerging technologies.

This SIGNAL Webinar Series event includes speakers who will provide an overview of communications platforms and solutions which support the interoperability of a wide range of interfaces and protocols, and which provide the seamless integration of legacy and emerging technologies. These will include the Department of Defense (DoD) required AS-SIP signaling, the functional requirements for Local Session Controllers (LSC) and the AS-SIP / TDM Gateway.

Speakers will also cover the efforts and results of the Joint Users Interoperability Communications Exercise (JUICE) 2011 to highlight tactical interoperability solutions and which address the challenges experienced by the Warfighter. REDCOM collaborated with industry partners who together designed and implemented a communications network comprised of Commercial off the Shelf (COTS) and Government off the Shelf (GOTS) equipment to bring cutting edge technology to the battlefield.

Register here.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
