<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: S.O.S. by American Red Cross</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>August 30, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>American Red Cross</tag>
    <tag>Android apps</tag>
    <tag>emergency preparedness</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Quickly respond to common emergency situations with the free S.O.S. app for Android from the American Red Cross and Dr. Oz. Developed by Sharecare Incorporated, the app features step-by-step video instructions with voice commands from Dr. Oz to help you handle problems as they arise. Simply follow the demonstrations and commands to confidently respond and save lives.</abstract>
  <text>Quickly respond to common emergency situations with the free S.O.S. app for Android from the American Red Cross and Dr. Oz. Developed by Sharecare Incorporated, the app features step-by-step video instructions with voice commands from Dr. Oz to help you handle problems as they arise. Simply follow the demonstrations and commands to confidently respond and save lives. The instructions cover more than 30 of the most common emergency situations, which were developed and reviewed by medical and education panels from the American Red Cross and the American College of Emergency Physicians. Any user can follow the videos, which include 3-D animation for more complicated steps, such as unconscious choking response. The section on CPR even has an audio and visual counter for real-time compressions. In addition, the app includes a Resource Guide for access to emergency care information adapted from current Red Cross training materials. Download the free app from the Android App Market.  These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
