<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Wyle Labs Walks Away with Five High-Tech Contracts</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>September 29, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>biometrics</tag>
    <tag>criminal investigation</tag>
    <tag>Defense Intelligence Agency</tag>
    <tag>ESG</tag>
    <tag>Offutt Air Force Base</tag>
    <tag>UAS</tag>
    <tag>UAV</tag>
    <tag>unmanned aerial systems</tag>
    <tag>Wyle Laboratories</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Wyle Laboratories Incorporated, Huntsville, Alabama, has recently been awarded several contracts. The first is a $49,181,949 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract to provide research and analysis to replace existing handheld biometrics, which currently lack the required reliability, quality, and supportability. Research will provide biometric system assessments, technology, and architecture enhancements, and prototype development to enable information fusion. Specific deliverables include: analysis of alternatives, configuration analysis, sensitive site exploitation, and tagging/tracking location reports. The second is a $47,595,440 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract to provide for reliability, maintainability, quality, supportability, and interoperability to develop and enhance the U.S. Army Criminal Investigation Laboratory. Research results will be used to enhance efficiencies, reliability, and interoperability of systems, equipment, and information technologies. Research will support exploitation capability requirements and apply those requirements to other geographic combatant commands to establish long-term programmatic responsibilities and identify gaps and vulnerabilities between expeditionary entities. Third is a $44,953,376 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract to provide development of reliability improvement processes and successful implementation to enhance readiness while reducing life-cycle costs for unmanned aerial systems programs utilizing reliability, maintainability, quality, supporting ability, and interoperability best practices. The fourth award is a $24,590,971 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract to provide engineering expertise to the Science and Technology Office to achieve the initiatives and goals of Defense Intelligence Agency in the area of measurement and signature intelligence. The fifth is an $11,756,257 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity requirements contract for engineering expertise for aircraft and related resource test, countermeasure, protection programs, and projects to refine and improve the emerging mission capabilities, processes, and portfolio of programs/projects and training including in-service systems and equipment. ESG/PKS DTIC, Offutt Air Force Base, Nebraska, is the contracting activity for all five awards.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
