<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>BAH Wins Three Contracts</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>September 29, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>BAH</tag>
    <tag>Booz Allen Hamilton</tag>
    <tag>critical infrastructure</tag>
    <tag>IIIMEF</tag>
    <tag>ISR</tag>
    <tag>situational awareness</tag>
    <tag>tactics</tag>
    <tag>techniques and procedures</tag>
    <tag>wargame</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Booz Allen Hamilton Incorporated, Herndon, Virginia, is being awarded three  contracts. The first is a $24,966,507 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery requirements contract to perform research and development in order to complete and deliver the "Emerging Leading-Edge Technological Advancement of Intelligence Surveillance Recon Capabilities Report", "Tactics, Techniques, and Procedures Report" and wargame/exercise lessons learned reports. These deliverables will be used to ultimately increase the situational awareness and survivability of the warfighter by helping them to better identify battlefield threats. The second is a $24,116,927 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery requirements contract to perform research and development in order to complete and deliver the capability evolution description document; the system prototype report; and the test and evaluation master plan. The Navy will use these reports for investment decisions regarding potential technologies that can best protect warfighters from threats posed by technological warfare, natural disaster, biochemical warfare, and terrorism/insurgency. And the third is a $20,768,477 cost-plus-fixed-fee, indefinite-delivery requirements contract to perform research and development in order to complete/deliver critical infrastructure facilities assessments; strategic planning technical reports; and experimentation, war gaming and exercise technical reports. The III Marine Expeditionary Force will use these deliverables to analyze and recommend methods to limit terrorist and enemy threats in a permanently deployed, overseas environment consisting of III Marine Expeditionary Force and Marine Corps personnel, equipment, facilities and staff. ESG/PKS DTIC, Offutt Air Force Base, Neb., is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
