<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>NAVMAR to Deploy Advanced C5ISR Architecture and Persistent Surveillance</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>September 29, 2011</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>C5ISR</tag>
    <tag>ISR</tag>
    <tag>Navmar</tag>
    <tag>Persistent Ground Surveillance Systems</tag>
    <tag>TigerShark</tag>
    <tag>UAV</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>NAVMAR Applied Sciences Corporation, Warminster, Pennsylvania, is being awarded a $12,436,224 cost-plus-fixed-fee order against a previously issued basic ordering agreement to continue efforts initiated under Small Business Innovation Research topic N94-178, to assess, procure, deploy, and support an advanced coalition, command, control, communications, computer, intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance equipment and system of architecture. Twenty percent of the work will be performed in Afghanistan. The company is also being awarded a $12,341,259 order against a previously issued basic ordering agreement for the assessment, procurement, and deployment of innovative intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance systems, and communication systems in support of phase three Persistent Ground Surveillance Systems. This effort also includes the assessment of unmanned aircraft vehicle (UAV) noise reducing technology, aircraft aerodynamics with increased lift and decreased drag, UAV weatherization, long endurance, submersible technology, interoperability of airborne and waterborne techniques to support ISR military operations and counter-narco-terrorism and related support hardware. The company is being awaded a third contract, a $12,336,876 order against a previously issued basic ordering agreement for the assessment, procurement, and deployment of innovative intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance systems, and communication systems, micro unmanned aircraft vehicle technology, and related hardware in support of phase three Persistent Ground Surveillance Systems. This effort also includes the procurement of 10 appropriately configured TigerShark unmanned aircraft system for precision acquisition weaponized system testing. The Naval Air Warfare Center Aircraft Division, Lakehurst, New Jersey, is the contracting activity for all three awards.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
