<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Experts to Discuss Budget Constraints and Homeland Security</title>
  <author>Maryann Lawlor</author>
  <date>February 8, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Department of Homeland Security</tag>
    <tag>Homeland 2012</tag>
    <tag>Homeland Security</tag>
    <tag>Recent Events</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Protecting any nation's citizens and institutions is difficult under any circumstances, but today's economic limitations make this task even more challenging. Government and business leaders will meet at the end of this month to tackle this topic during AFCEA International's 11th annual Homeland Security conference. Conference discussion topics include cloud computing, cyberwar, procurement, wireless broadband and social media. Small businesses' interaction with the U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS) also will be explored. Coverage will begin on February 28.</abstract>
  <text>Protecting any nation's citizens and institutions is difficult under any circumstances, but today's economic limitations make this task even more challenging. Government and business leaders will meet at the Ronald Reagan International Trade Center February 28 to March 1 to tackle this topic during AFCEA International's 11th annual Homeland Security conference. Conference discussion topics include cloud computing, cyberwar, procurement, wireless broadband and social media. Small businesses' interaction with the U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS) also will be explored. Speakers and panelists include Jim Flyzik, president, The Flyzik Group; Peter Tseronis, chief technology officer, U.S. Department of Energy; Cathy Lanier, chief of police, District of Columbia; and Bruce Walker, acting vice president, homeland security, Northrop Grumman Information Technology. Although the first day of DHS IT strategy sessions is not affiliated with the AFCEA conference, coverage of the sessions will be featured on the Coverage and Collaboration: Homeland Security 2012 Web page.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
