<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: Army OneSource</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>February 22, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Army OneSource</tag>
    <tag>Family Resources</tag>
    <tag>family support</tag>
    <tag>Finances</tag>
    <tag>iPad apps</tag>
    <tag>iPhone apps</tag>
    <tag>U.S. Army</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>A series of free Army OneSource apps provide users with resources on the go. Developed by the U.S. Army Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command, the apps make it easy to find local services, manage money and stay up-to-date on the Army Family Action Plan.</abstract>
  <text>A series of free Army OneSource apps provide users with resources on the go. Developed by the U.S. Army Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command, the apps make it easy to find local services, manage money and stay up-to-date on the Army Family Action Plan. The Army OneSource Services Locator for the iPhone or iPad lets you enter a ZIP code or city and search for services grouped by category, including deployment support and employment assistance. The app displays results in both a list and map view with simple driving directions to each location. In addition, Army OneSource Money Matters provides mobile financial tools and information. It is designed to motivate, educate and support Army soldiers and their families to save and plan for the future. The program includes resources on reducing debt, a savings calculator and a budget tool for tracking monthly expenses. Lastly, the Army Family Action Plan (AFAP) Issue Search app keeps service members in the loop on AFAP issues impacting the community. You can view the status and resolution of issues from your iPhone, iPad or iPod Touch. The app also features search tools and contact information for questions and concerns. If you have a suggestion for a Cool App-titude feature, email Assistant Editor Rachel Eisenhower at reisenhower@afcea.org. These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
