<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: Homes on the Homefront</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>March 1, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>supporting military families</tag>
    <tag>Supporting Our Veterans</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
    <tag>wounded warriors</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>This partnership between Operation Homefront and Chase Bank will give at least 100 wounded-warrior, military and veterans' families their own permanent homes this year.</abstract>
  <text>Homes on the Homefront is more than just a catchy name. This partnership between Operation Homefront and Chase Bank will give at least 100 wounded-warrior, military and veterans' families their own permanent homes this year. In addition, selectees will receive financial counseling. First priority will go to families currently living in Operation Homefront Village. Other wounded warriors, surviving single spouses of troops killed in action and post-9/11 disabled veterans also will receive priority consideration. However, all honorably discharged veterans and active duty, Guard or Reserve members who do not own a home currently but who are financially capable of sustaining one are eligible and encouraged to fill out the application.

The dwellings distributed by Homes on the Homefront come from Chase's inventory. Once selected, families will reside in the property as a tenant of Operation Homefront for one to two years. Families must pay any actual costs of property taxes, insurance and homeowner's association fees during that time. Customized transition plans will be developed for recipients. Other terms and conditions also apply to help ensure families are prepared to take full ownership of properties.

 

Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information. If you know of a program that is helping service personnel, veterans or their families please submit that information to Rita Boland, SIGNAL's news editor.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
