<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: Military Interstate Children's Compact Commission</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>March 22, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>supporting military families</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The Military Interstate Children's Compact Commission aims to replace the widely varying school-record policies that affect transitioning military students with a comprehensive approach every school district can use if their state chooses to take part.</abstract>
  <text>It's no secret that military life can be hard on families. Children of service members deal not only with the deployment of parents to dangerous places but also with regular relocations that require a transferring of records between school districts, which often have different standards. The Military Interstate Children's Compact Commission (MIC3) aims to replace these widely varying policies that affect transitioning military students with a comprehensive approach every school district can use if their state chooses to take part. Issues addressed include enrollment, placement, attendance, eligibility and graduation.

An interactive map on the commission's website displays which states participate. By clicking on one, visitors can access information about state contact officials. Children of active duty members of the armed forces, National Guard and Reserve members on active-duty orders, and veterans who were medically discharged or retired in the last year are eligible for assistance. Families can learn more on the MIC3 site or by reaching out to school liaison officers on local installations. A list of those liaisons is available on the Military K-12 Partners site.

 

Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information. If you know of a program that is helping service personnel, veterans or their families please submit that information to Rita Boland, SIGNAL's news editor.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
