<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Firms Awarded Potential $500 Million for Network and Communications Equipment</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>March 23, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>ACG Systems</tag>
    <tag>Atlantic Diving Supply Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Blue Tech Inc.</tag>
    <tag>CDW Government LLC</tag>
    <tag>Global Technology Resources Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Iron Bow Technologies</tag>
    <tag>Marshall Communications Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Mercom Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Mutual telecom Services Inc.</tag>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center</tag>
    <tag>SRC</tag>
    <tag>Strategic Communications LLC</tag>
    <tag>Tribalco LLC</tag>
    <tag>World Wide Technology Incorporated</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>ACG Systems Incorporated, Annapolis, Maryland; Atlantic Diving Supply Incorporated, Virginia Beach, Virginia; Blue Tech Incorporated, San Diego, California; CDW Government LLC, Vernon Hills, Illinois; Global Technology Resources Incorporated, Denver, Colorado; Iron Bow Technologies LLC, Chantilly, Virginia; Marshall Communications Corporation, Ashburn, Virginia; Mercom Incorporated, Pawleys Island, South Carolina; Mutual Telecom Services Incorporated, Needham, Massachusetts; Science Applications International Corporation, McLean, Virginia; Scientific Research Corporation, Atlanta, Georgia; Strategic Communications LLC, Louisville, Kentucky; Tribalco LLC, Bethesda, Maryland; and World Wide Technology Incorporated, St. Louis, Missouri, are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, firm-fixed-price, multiple award supply contract for the procurement of commercial-off-the-shelf, network and communications equipment, and related incidental support services. These contracts include options, which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these contracts to an estimated $500 million. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, South Carolina, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
