<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Air Force Awards $6.9 Billion to Multiple Firms</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>April 18, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Ace Technology</tag>
    <tag>Air Force</tag>
    <tag>Blue Tech Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Electronic Systems Center</tag>
    <tag>FedStore</tag>
    <tag>General Dynamics</tag>
    <tag>Global Technology Resources</tag>
    <tag>GTSI</tag>
    <tag>Iron Bow Technologies</tag>
    <tag>M2 Technology</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Ace Technology Partners LLC, Arlington Heights, Illinois; Blue Tech Incorporated, San Diego, California; FedStore Corporation, Rockville, Maryland; General Dynamics IT, Needham, Massachusetts; Global Technology Resources, Incorporated, Denver, Colorado; GTSI Corporation, Herndon, Virginia; Iron Bow Technologies LLC, Chantilly, Virginia; M2 Technology Incorporated, San Antonio, Texas; and Red River Computer Company, Claremont, New Hampshire, are being awarded a $6.9 billion firm fixed price, multiple award, indefinite delivery, and indefinite quantity contract for the purchase of netcentric products for Air Force customers. This contract vehicle will provide for commercially available off-the-shelf products to support the Internet Protocol Network and will include the following categories of netcentric products and associated support worldwide: (1) networking equipment, (2) servers and storage, (3) peripherals, (4) multimedia, (5) software (not included on other enterprise licenses), and (6) identity management/biometric hardware and associated software. This contract supports the Global Information Grid architecture, Defense Information Infrastructure, Air Force, and Defense Communications Systems info-structure for computer networks and telecommunications network mission areas. Electronic Systems Center, Maxwell Air Force Base, Alabama, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
