<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Firms to Provide Common Hardware Under $775 Million Contract</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>May 10, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Blue Tech</tag>
    <tag>CDWG</tag>
    <tag>Countertrade</tag>
    <tag>Dell</tag>
    <tag>GTSI</tag>
    <tag>Intelligent Decisions</tag>
    <tag>Iron Bow Technologies</tag>
    <tag>ITG/EPLUS</tag>
    <tag>Marine Corps Common Hardware Suite</tag>
    <tag>Marine Corps Systems Command</tag>
    <tag>Marines</tag>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>NCS Technologies</tag>
    <tag>World Wide Technology Inc.</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Blue Tech, San Diego, California; CDWG, Vernon Hills, Illinois; Countertrade, Arvada, Colorado; Dell, Round Rock, Texas; GTSI Corporation, Herndon, Virginia; Intelligent Decisions, Incorporated, Ashburn, Virginia; Iron Bow Technologies, Chantilly, Virginia; ITG/EPLUS, Falls Church, Virginia; NCS Technologies Incorporated, Gainesville, Virginia; and World Wide Technology Incorporated, St. Louis, Missouri, are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, multiple-award contract for commercial-off-the-shelf (COTS) computer systems, including ruggedized and non-ruggedized desktops and laptops, as well as servers and other associated computer equipment and accessories. This equipment, collectively referred to as Marine Corps Common Hardware Suite computing equipment, will provide standardized computing equipment and worldwide integrated logistics support for the Marine Corps operating forces and to the Department of Navy, while achieving the lowest cost of ownership through centralized procurement of high quality, COTS hardware. The aggregate not-to-exceed amount for these multiple award contracts combined is $775 million and represents a three-year base period with a two-year option, and the companies will have the opportunity to bid on each individual delivery order.  Marine Corps Systems Command, Quantico, Virginia, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
