<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>U.S. Navy Awards Nearly $145 Million in Command Center Support Funds</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>May 10, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>C2S2</tag>
    <tag>Centurum Information Technology</tag>
    <tag>Command Centers</tag>
    <tag>L-3</tag>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>M.C. Dean</tag>
    <tag>QinetiQ North America</tag>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>Serco</tag>
    <tag>Services and Solutions Group</tag>
    <tag>Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center</tag>
    <tag>Systems Research and Applications Corp.</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Centurum Information Technology Incorporated, Marlton, New Jersey; L-3 Services Incorporated, doing business as C2S2, Mount Laurel, New Jersey; Lockheed Martin Corporation, Herndon, Virginia; M.C. Dean Incorporated, Dulles, Virginia; QinetiQ North America Incorporated, doing business as Services and Solutions Group (S&amp;S), Fairfax, Virginia; Science Applications International, doing business as SAIC, McLean, Virginia; SERCO Incorporated, Reston, Virginia; and Systems Research &amp; Applications Corporation, doing business as SRA, Fairfax, Virginia, are each being awarded an indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, cost-plus-fixed-fee with firm-fixed-price provisions, multiple award contract for the procurement of integrated command and control engineering and technical support services for command centers. The services required include program management, technical engineering support, integrated logistics support, configuration and data management support, direct customer support, and security engineering support. These contracts include options, which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these contracts to an estimated $144.9 million. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, South Carollina, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
