<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: Dive Pirates</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>May 17, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Supporting Our Veterans</tag>
    <tag>supporting wounded warriors</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Injured in combat and looking for a chance to scuba? Then swim over to Dive Pirates--no treasure necessary.</abstract>
  <text>Ahoy matey! Whether you're looking to explore the seas with the modern equivalents of peg legs and eye patches, or seeking to share your bounty with deserving warriors, Dive Pirates is the place for you. The foundation trains, equips and provides one dive trip out of the country for individuals with disabilities-including service members injured in the line of duty-through adaptive scuba diving. Volunteers serve as trainers and buddies in the program and donations pay for the cost of equipment and trips.

Dive Pirates encourages families to participate together, with loved ones serving as the dive buddies. But veterans who don't know anyone who wants to dive are still strongly encouraged to apply. They will be matched with a buddy if they need help beyond what instructors can provide. Leadership of the foundation emphasizes that the program is about fun, camaraderie, building support networks and creating positive memories that can aid mental and physical recovery.

Any warfighter who has a clearly recognized physical disability as a result of injuries received in military service and who cannot obtain a standard open water certification is eligible. Divers also must meet a few other requirements.

Dive Pirates extends a hearty welcome (but no rum) to donations and sponsors. So pull out those Doubloons for a great cause. Argghhh!

 

Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information. If you know of a program that is helping service personnel, veterans or their families please submit that information to Rita Boland, SIGNAL's news editor.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
