<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Cool App-titude: IED IMPACT</title>
  <author>Rachel Eisenhower</author>
  <date>May 29, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>iPad apps</tag>
    <tag>wounded warriors</tag>
    <tag>Cool App-titude</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>The IED IMPACT app for iPad provides wounded warriors with a way to connect with and give back to their units. The program is designed specifically to serve the counter-improvised explosive device (IED) community.</abstract>
  <text>The IED IMPACT (Injured Military Personnel Assisting Combat Troops) app for iPad provides wounded warriors with a way to connect with and give back to their units. The program is designed specifically to serve the counter-improvised explosive device (IED) community. Through the application, members of the community can view video interviews from wounded warriors sharing their personal experiences with actual IED strikes during combat. The app "allows a more immediate catharsis for these veterans by sharing their story within a secure platform of people who appreciate the combat environment," said Ken Falke, co-founder of the program. Ultimately, the app creates a social platform for members to share life-saving lessons in a collaborative environment through videos, pictures, text and links. App features include vetted and password-screened membership; user profiles; wounded warrior recovery stories; FaceTime chats with community members and more. The free app is available from the iTunes App Store. A web version will be available later this year along with an iPhone and Android version at a later date. Shoulder 2 Shoulder, a service-disabled, veteran-owned small business, is the developer.  These sites are not affiliated with AFCEA or SIGNAL Magazine, and we are not responsible for the content or quality of the products offered. When visiting new websites, please use proper Internet security procedures.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
