<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Navy Awards Multi-billion Dollar SeaPort-e Contract to 385 Firms</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>July 13, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Navy</tag>
    <tag>SeaPort-E</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>The Navy is awarding indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity multiple-award contracts to 385 contractors that will provide for their competition for service requirements solicited by Naval Sea Systems Command, Naval Air Systems Command, Space and Naval Warfare Systems Command, Naval Supply Systems Command, Military Sealift Command, Naval Facilities Command, Strategic Systems Programs, Office of Naval Research, and the U.S. Marine Corps. The 22 functional service areas within the scope of the contracts include: research and development support; engineering system engineering and process engineering support; modeling, simulation, stimulation, and analysis support; prototyping, pre-production, model-making, and fabric support; system design documentation, and technical data support; software engineering, development, programming, and network support; reliability, maintainability, and availability support; human factors, performance, and usability engineering support; system safety engineering support; configuration management support; quality assurance support; information system development, information assurance, and information technology support; ship inactivation and disposal support; interoperability, test and evaluation, trials support; measurement facilities, range, and instrumentation support; acquisition logistics support; supply and provisioning support; training support; in-service engineering, fleet introduction, installation and checkout support; program support; functional and administrative support, and public affairs and multimedia support. These contracts are in addition to the existing 2,501 contracts previously awarded under the SeaPort Enhanced (SeaPort-e) acquisition program for services procurements. The government estimates a maximum of $5.3 billion of services will be procured per year via orders issued under the SeaPort-e multiple award contracts. The Naval Sea Systems Command, Naval Surface Warfare Center, Dahlgren Division, Dahlgren, Virginia, is the contracting activity

 </text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
