<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Multiple Firms to Support Anti-Terrorism Efforts in National Capitol Region</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>July 20, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>anti-terrorism</tag>
    <tag>BAE</tag>
    <tag>Force Protection</tag>
    <tag>Honeywell</tag>
    <tag>L-3</tag>
    <tag>M.C. Dean</tag>
    <tag>ManTech</tag>
    <tag>national capitol region</tag>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center</tag>
    <tag>VT Milcom</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>BAE Systems Technology Solutions and Services Incorporated, Rockville, Maryland; Honeywell Technology Solutions Incorporated, Columbia, Maryland; L-3 Services Incorporated, dba C2S2, Mount Laurel, New Jersey; M.C. Dean Incorporated, Dulles, Virginia; ManTech International Corporation, Lexington Park, Maryland; Science Applications International dba SAIC, McLean, Virginia; and VT Milcom Incorporated, Virginia Beach, Virginia are each being awarded a multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity, performance-based contract that utilizes fixed-price task orders for the procurement of security engineering support services, which support the operational requirements of high-value Navy and other government activities where security is of high or vital interest located in the National Capitol Region. The services required will include systems engineering, analysis, development, acquisition, integration, installation, testing, software development and maintenance, and integrated logistical support for Anti-Terrorism/Force Protection (AT/FP) Systems. Each contractor will be awarded $3,571 at the time of award. These contracts include options which, if exercised, would bring the cumulative value of these contracts to an estimated $224.9 million. Space and Naval Warfare Systems Center Atlantic, Charleston, South Carolina, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
