<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Several Firms to Support DISA Test and Evaluation Efforts</title>
  <author>George Seffers</author>
  <date>August 6, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>Alion</tag>
    <tag>American Systems Corporation</tag>
    <tag>DISA</tag>
    <tag>DITCO</tag>
    <tag>JITC</tag>
    <tag>Lockheed Martin</tag>
    <tag>ManTech</tag>
    <tag>Oberon Associates</tag>
    <tag>SAIC</tag>
    <tag>TASC</tag>
    <tag>test and evaluation</tag>
    <tag>Contract Awards</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract></abstract>
  <text>Alion Science and Technology Corporation, Alexandria, Virginia; TASC Incorporated, Andover, Massachusetts; Science Applications International Corporation, McLean, Virginia; ManTech Telecommunications &amp; Information Systems Corporation/Technical Services Group, Herndon, Virginia; Oberon Associates Incorporated, Manassas, Virginia; American Systems Corporation, Chantilly, Virginia; and Lockheed Martin Corporation, Orlando, Florida, were awarded multiple-award, indefinite-delivery/indefinite-quantity contracts with cost-plus-fixed-fee and firm-fixed-price contract line item numbers, for test and evaluation (T&amp;E) support for the Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA) Test &amp; Evaluation Executive Office and the DISA Joint Interoperability Test Command (JITC), in order to fulfill their DISA T&amp;E mission. The awardees will support tasks to perform a wide range of non-personal services to encompass testing, scientific, engineering, logistic, administrative, purchasing, and ancillary support of the DISA T&amp;E mission. The services will include all support aspects, including the operation and maintenance of the test tools, labs, networks and infrastructure, and administrative support cells. The contracts are funded by fiscal 2012 RDT&amp;E appropriations, with a minimum guarantee face value of $100,000 and a total program ceiling value of $871,417,098. The Defense Information Technology Contracting Organization, JITC Contract Support Section, Fort Huachuca, Arizona, is the contracting activity.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
