<article>
  <type>blog</type>
  <title>Homefront Help: MilitaryBenefitsReport.com</title>
  <author>Rita Boland</author>
  <date>August 16, 2012</date>
  <departments>
  </departments>
  <tags>
    <tag>support our troops</tag>
    <tag>supporting military families</tag>
    <tag>Supporting the Troops</tag>
    <tag>supporting wounded warriors</tag>
    <tag>Homefront Help</tag>
  </tags>
  <abstract>Frustrated with trying to figure out all the benefits you've earned through your military experiences? MilitaryBenefitsReport.com will handle the research for you. All you have to do is answer some questions. </abstract>
  <text>MilitaryBenefitsReport.com is the brainchild of Wolfgang Ward, a combat veteran and recipient of the Purple Heart who got fed up trying to track down all the benefits available to him from different groups. So he decided to create a resource to help anyone in the military community, from spouses to wounded veterans, find the help they need in one place. Visitors to the site answer questions explaining their current status, then they receive an email with a secure password so they can download their free customized report.

Ward and Blueprint Information Products LLC, searched hundreds of organizations, then determined who would be eligible for each offered benefit under what circumstances before putting all the information into the database used to generate the reports. The organization is asking people to help spread the word about the offering to help others avoid the frustrations Ward experienced and to make sure members of the military community have better access to the benefits they've earned.

The site lists testimonials from users in a variety of ranks and situations, including former AFCEA CEO Rear Adm. Herb Browne, USN (Ret.).

Homefront Help also has a Facebook page where visitors can gather and share information. If you know of a program that is helping troops, veterans or their families, please submit that information to Rita Boland, SIGNAL's news editor.</text>
  <imgalttext>
  </imgalttext>
</article>
